<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880817-0040
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>17
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Quayle Called A Dedicated Family Man
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Dan Quayle's sister believes the Indiana
senator won't let his candidacy for vice president hurt the family
life he and his wife, Marilyn, enjoy.
``I don't think it will be tough on the family,'' said Martha
Saddler, Quayle's sister, who lives in Huntington, Ind. ``Since
he's been in politics, we all kind of shake our heads at his hectic
schedule and wonder how he does it. But he does it and loves it.''
The Quayle family and friends were celebrating Tuesday afternoon
after George Bush announced he wants the 41-year-old Indiana
senator to be the Republican nominee for vice president.
</P>
<P>
Those who have known the Quayles for years said the senator and
his wife have remained relatively unchanged by their years in
public life.
</P>
<P>
Dan and Marilyn Quayle met as law students in Indianapolis,
married while they were still in school and remain close to many of
their friends from that period.
``One of the greatest things about him is the job of being a
senator has not changed him a bit,'' said Indianapolis attorney
William R. Neale, treasurer of Quayle's 1986 re-election campaign.
``He's the same nice guy he was in law school.''
Neale, who grew up with Marilyn Tucker Quayle in Indianapolis,
introduced Dan Quayle to his future wife at a student gathering at
the Indiana University law school in the early 1970s.
</P>
<P>
Dan Quayle, who grew up in Huntington, graduated from DePauw
University, a small liberal arts college in Greencastle, Ind.,
before going to work in the Indiana attorney general's office in
1970.
</P>
<P>
Daniel F. Evans, also a law school classmate of Dan Quayle, said
he doesn't expect Quayle's national candidacy to change him.
``I think his strength is he'll remember who his friends are
even after this,'' said Evans, who was chairman of Quayle's 1986
campaign.
</P>
<P>
Friends said the Quayles are devoted to their three children and
prefer quiet nights at home to nights out on the town in Washington.
``His family looks like the family both parties are trying to
appeal to,'' said Mitch Daniels, former political chief in the
White House and now president of the Hudson Institute. ``It's a
beautiful family. I think they'll be a real asset.''
The couple, who married in 1972, have a 14-year-old son, Tucker;
a 12-year-old son, Benjamin; and a 9-year-old daughter, Corinne.
</P>
<P>
When they campaign in Indiana, the Quayles often tour in two
groups _ the boys riding in parades with Marilyn Quayle and Corinne
and her father visiting county fairs.
``The kids are nonchalant, normal kids,'' said Mrs. Saddler.
``They take it in stride and play.''
In an interview with Indiana reporters Monday, the Quayles said
they had worried during the vice presidential speculation about the
family's loss of privacy during a national campaign.
``The total lack of privacy is going to be the biggest minus,''
said Mrs. Quayle, 39.
</P>
<P>
Quayle said he had questioned each of his children about whether
he should accept the vice presidential spot if Bush offered it.
</P>
<P>
Tucker was fascinated by the idea, Quayle said. Benjamin was
ambiguous but he thought Secret Service agents might be able to
help him on tests at school, Mrs. Quayle said.
</P>
<P>
Corinne didn't like the prospect of having her father spend more
time away from home, Quayle said.
``She told me, `Daddy, I really hope George Bush picks Bob
Dole,''' said Quayle.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880818-0023
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>18
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Republicans Quickly Elevate Quayle Into The American Pantheon
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Dan Quayle has not yet been nominated for
vice president and already Republicans are comparing him to Thomas
Jefferson and John F. Kennedy.
</P>
<P>
Sen. John Warner of Virginia, who served with Quayle on a Senate
subcommittee, told an audience that whenever he heard the Indiana
senator speak, ``I'd say, `there stands the next Thomas
Jefferson.'''
And, added Warner, ``he does have the same fire in his belly as
our great forefather Thomas Jefferson of Virginia.''
Former president Gerald Ford made the comparison with Kennedy, a
Democrat.
``In 1960, the American people voted for John F. Kennedy for
president and he was the relatively same age as Dan Quayle,'' said
Ford. ``John Kennedy had been in the House and Senate 14 years
before he was elected president and Dan Quayle's had 12 years.''
What Quayle thinks of those references isn't known. But he
doesn't like it when people say he looks like movie idol Robert
Redford.
</P>
<P>
Whether, indeed, he looks like Redford seems to be in the eye of
the beholder. In the parlance of politics, it's an issue. They are
both male. They are both blond.
</P>
<P>
The so-called resemblance became a point of contention in the
1980 Senate race and Redford took umbrage. The actor, who once
played the role of a presidential office seeker in ``The
Candidate'' sent Quayle a telegram telling him to stop the
look-alike references in his congressional campaign literature.
</P>
<P>
Quayle said the news media had made the comparison, not he, and
after he was elected sent Redford an autographed picture of himself.
</P>
<P>
And this week, he told reporters he considered the so-called
Redford look ``a stigma.'' He wasn't asked how he felt about being
painted as another Jefferson or Kennedy.
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, fellow senators were trying to publicize Quayle who,
at 41, hasn't had a chance to become a legend. He is a Republican
vice presidential candidate who is not, as Spiro Agnew once said of
himself, a household word.
</P>
<P>
To help him get known, eight fellow senators Wednesday took
turns telling reporters how much they liked him.
``We know him well,'' said Strom Thurmond, R-S.C.
``He's attractive because of his looks, he's attractive because
of his enthusiasm,'' said Sen. John McCain, R-Ariz.
``I think Dan Quayle, although he's 41 years of age, he's going
to send a message to the American people that the Republican Party
respects young people who achieve,'' said Sen. Pete Domenici, R-N.M.
</P>
<P>
Oh, yes, he's also rich, but the senators said that should not
hold him back.
``Let's not start this business of who's wealthy,'' Sen. Alfonse
D'Amato, R-N.Y.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880818-0226
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>18
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here is a transcript of the speech by Sen.
</P>
<P>
Bob Dole of Kansas nominating Sen. Dan Quayle of Indiana for vice
president at the Republican National Convention on Thursday night.
</P>
<P>
Thank you. Thank you.
</P>
<P>
Mr. Chairman, four of my congressional colleagues and I are here
for the purpose of nominating the next vice president of the United
States.
</P>
<P>
We are here to nominate one of the bright young lights in the
Republican Party, a man I am proud to say is my colleague, the
junior senator from Indiana, Dan Quayle.
</P>
<P>
You know, senators get a lot of mail. Party leaders more than
most. And almost every one of these letters asks for help with some
problem.
</P>
<P>
Well, three years ago, I received a handwritten plea from a
6-year-old girl who after several days of long, long Senate
sessions had a very special problem.
</P>
<P>
She wrote, and I quote: ``I have my second-grade play tonight.
</P>
<P>
Please make sure my daddy can come home and watch me.''
I knew Corinne Quayle was from a political family because she
invited me to come along, too.
</P>
<P>
Corinne and her brothers, Tucker and Benjamin, and their mother,
Marilyn, share Dan Quayle with the people of Indiana and the United
States Senate.
</P>
<P>
Dan Quayle is a dedicated public servant and a devoted family
man.
</P>
<P>
And whenever I needed him, whenever I needed him, Dan was there
_ ready and willing to make the tough choices, to cast the tough
votes, to transform President Reagan's vision of America into the
law of the land.
</P>
<P>
Whether it was the budget or defense, tax reform or the INF
treaty, Dan Quayle was there, a forceful advocate, and a staunch
supporter of the Reagan revolution. And now he is ready to carry
that revolution forward.
</P>
<P>
And believe me he is ready, and just let the Democrats try to
use experience as a measuring stick in this campaign. Just let them
try.
</P>
<P>
Now, I don't mean to suggest their presidential candidate lacks
experience. He's got plenty of experience, plenty of experience _
experience in raising taxes again and again, experience in vetoing
the pledge of allegiance in public schools, experience in
increasing spending year after year after year in Massachusetts.
</P>
<P>
And I just don't believe the American people want that kind of
experience in the White House.
</P>
<P>
It sounds like a Dukak-eyed idea to me.
</P>
<P>
But Dan Quayle's got experience, too. He's already spent 12
years as a congressman and a senator, tackling the vital national
and international issues that affect the lives of all Americans and
the future of our country.
</P>
<P>
That is 12 more years of national experience than Michael
Dukakis _ and he is running for president.
</P>
<P>
As I said at the start, Dan Quayle is a man I know and trust. I
am honored to nominate him for vice president, Mr. Chairman.
</P>
<P>
And for the purpose of debate only, I yield the balance of my
time to the outstanding, distinguished senior from Indiana, my good
friend, Sen. Dick Lugar.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
End Dole Text _ 1 Take
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880819-0023
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>19
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Quayle's Triumph Quickly Tarnished
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Dan Quayle's vice presidential nomination was
supposed to be a triumph for the precocious young Indiana senator,
but the dream faded overnight.
</P>
<P>
Bush's surprise choice for his running mate was supposed to
ignite a campaign that has seemed at times to suffer from lack of
inspiration, but he quickly encountered questions over his military
record and suggestions he could best serve the Republicans by
withdrawing from the ticket.
</P>
<P>
Though he found himself in danger of fizzling Thursday, Quayle
managed to stir the convention hall with his upbeat speech about
family, generations and the rosy future he foresaw under a Bush
administration.
``Let's go on to victory!'' Quayle exhorted, as the crowd
erupted in cheers.
</P>
<P>
The 41-year-old nominee delivered the speech with calm
self-assurance, sticking close to his text and avoiding his
penchant for extemporaneous remarks _ perhaps another result of the
unanticipated controversy.
</P>
<P>
Bush, who followed his running mate to the podium, said he was
``proud to have Dan Quayle at my side.'' The two will stress the
unity of their ticket as they campaign together this weekend
through Indiana, Ohio and Illinois.
</P>
<P>
But beyond the optimistic words was an unsettling undercurrent
that threatened Quayle's candidacy just as it was launched.
</P>
<P>
Retired Maj. Gen. Wendell C. Phillippi _ who worked for Quayle's
grandfather, Eugene C. Pulliam, as managing editor of The
Indianapolis News _ said he contacted the National Guard on behalf
of Quayle when the young man applied in 1969 and ``recommended him
very highly,'' the News reported.
</P>
<P>
Quayle, a hardliner on defense matters, has said he sought guard
duty so he could attend law school. A Bush aide said the matter was
discussed with the Indiana senator during the process that led to
his selection for the Bush ticket, and Quayle had denied that he
used influence to gain admittance to the Guard.
</P>
<P>
Bush aides said no thought had been given to dropping Quayle
from the ticket, as some Republicans suggested. Quayle was tense
and refused to answer reporters' questions about the topic during a
brief walk-through at the convention hall.
</P>
<P>
It was a daunting change for the senator, whose youthful vigor,
rapid political rise, striking good looks and wealth have been
compared to those of John F. Kennedy.
</P>
<P>
Quayle alluded to the National Guard issue during his speech,
saying he was proud of the six years he served. He also addressed
his relative anonymity: ``Many this week have asked, `Who is Dan
Quayle?' The people of Indiana know me and now the nation will.''
Those who addressed the convention on his behalf also pulled out
their ammunition. Sen. Bob Dole of Kansas, who placed Quayle's name
in nomination, stressed his campaign skills and sought to deflect
concerns that he lacked experience for the job.
``He's already spent 12 years as a congressman and senator. ...
</P>
<P>
That is 12 more years of national experience than Michael Dukakis,
and he is running for president,'' Dole said.
</P>
<P>
Sen. Alan Simpson of Wyoming, one of those who seconded the
nomination, said Quayle would ``bring vim, vigor and vitality'' to
the party and would bring ``sparks and voltage to this campaign.''
Whether Quayle can overcome his difficult start on the national
ticket remains to be seen. Others, notably Democratic vice
presidential nominee Geraldine Ferraro in 1984, found they could
not.
</P>
<P>
But Quayle, ever upbeat, was determined Thursday night not to be
daunted by the prospect. ``Miracles do happen,'' he told his party.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880826-0226
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Quayle's Biography Inflates State Job; Quayle Concedes Error
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Republican vice presidential candidate Dan
Quayle's official resume says he was the Indiana Consumer
Protection Division's chief investigator a year before the unit was
created, state records show.
</P>
<P>
The law creating the unit passed April 14, 1971, and took effect
July 1. Officials said Quayle served as chief investigator from
July until mid-September, when he became administrative assistant
to then-Gov. Edgar D. Whitcomb.
</P>
<P>
Quayle's Senate biography, which his campaign is using as his
official background, says he was chief investigator of the unit in
the Attorney General's office from 1970 to 1971.
``He was assigned to our section in the spring of 1971,'' said
Robert Smith, the unit's first director and now an attorney in
Indianapolis.
``He was in fact the chief investigator. He helped get the unit
set up. (But) it would not have been before 1971,'' Smith said
Friday in a telephone interview. ``We formally began operations
July 1.''
Quayle conceded Friday that the resume entry was ``inaccurate''
and said his staff had written the document.
``If it indicated that, that is inaccurate. I didn't hold that
job for two years,'' Quayle told reporters aboard his campaign
plane.
</P>
<P>
Earlier, however, Quayle spokesman David Prosperi called the
revelation of the error by The Plain Dealer of Cleveland ``a cheap
shot.''
Quayle was hired as an entry-level research assistant by the
state Attorney General's office in 1970 after he returned from six
months of basic and advanced training for the Indiana National
Guard.
</P>
<P>
Quayle, a 1969 graduate of DePauw University, was attending
Indiana University Law School at the time.
</P>
<P>
M. Stanton Evans, then an editor with the Indianapolis News,
helped arrange his job interview with the state. Evans worked for
Eugene C. Pulliam, Quayle's grandfather and publisher of the News.
``At no point in any of this did Dan Quayle ask any favors or
use any influence,'' said Evans, now with the National Journalism
Center in Washington, D.C.
``He wouldn't have been hired as a chief investigator. He was
hired in an entry-level job and was promoted to a whole bunch of
jobs on his merits. It's a nothing story,'' Evans said.
</P>
<P>
Theodore Sendak, the Attorney General at the time, recently had
surgery and is unable to comment, according to his son, Timothy
Sendak.
</P>
<P>
Patricia Gifford, a Marion Superior Court judge who was then an
assistant attorney general, said Friday that prior to the
establishment of the Consumer Protection Division, ``all complaints
and inquiries were handled by me. The legal assistant assigned to
me and utilized as my chief investigator was Dan Quayle.'' Her
statement was released by the Quayle campaign.
</P>
<P>
The Consumer Protection Division was created by the state
legislature to resolve complaints over defective products, false
claims in ads, faulty speedometer readings and mail-order fraud.
</P>
<P>
In 1980, Quayle referred to himself as a ``Vietnam-era veteran''
in campaign literature when he was running against three-term
incumbent Birch Bayh in a Senate race.
</P>
<P>
Quayle, who enlisted in the Indiana National Guard, dropped the
reference after objections by some Vietnam combat veterans.
</P>
<P>
In that same election, which he won, Quayle said he was ``on
active duty for several periods during his tenure'' in the Guard.
</P>
<P>
The statement referred to periods when Quayle was in basic training
and 15 days of camp each summer.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP881114-0006
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>14
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Quayle Likely To Be Odd Man Out In Bush White House, Pundits Say
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Dan Quayle is likely to be a ``man on the
outside'' in George Bush's White House following a vice presidential
candidacy that began in a furor but settled into obscurity, experts
say.
</P>
<P>
Encumbered by his image as a political novice who needed a bevy
of professional handlers to survive early campaign controversies,
Quayle enters a Bush administration in which he has few intimates or
allies.
</P>
<P>
Relegated in the campaign to small towns and safe GOP areas,
Quayle as vice president is likely to be given a traditional
ceremonial role _ going to political gatherings and state funerals _
rather than the advisory role that Walter Mondale and even Bush had,
some scholars feel.
``Dan Quayle is going to set the vice presidency back about a
decade or more. One thing that political scientists have been
talking about is just how much the vice presidency has grown. ...
</P>
<P>
With Quayle, it's just going to retreat to the old days of politics
and funerals,'' said Ryan Barilleaux, a professor of political
science at Miami University in Oxford, Ohio, who studies the
American presidency.
</P>
<P>
Bush rarely mentioned his 41-year-old running mate during the
campaign. When asked, Bush employed the stock lines that Quayle
would ``make an outstanding vice president'' and had been ``tempered
by steel'' as he weathered the early furor over his military
service, academic record and personal life.
</P>
<P>
The president-elect told reporters Quayle would have access to
the same papers, information and intelligence that is available to
the president. But he would go no further in describing what
assignments he would give Quayle.
</P>
<P>
Quayle says Bush has talked to him about heading a space council,
and that he assumes he'll have a role in the administration's
anti-drug efforts. ``I will be a very close adviser to the
president,'' Quayle said.
</P>
<P>
But that's not the way everyone sees it.
</P>
<P>
Both Bush and Mondale came to their vice presidential campaigns
with substantial reputations and were able to place key staffers in
important positions in the respective presidential campaigns,
Barilleaux notes.
``Dan Quayle has contributed nothing in the way of staff to the
Bush campaign. He doesn't have his own big reputation on Capitol
Hill. ... Dan Quayle has no friends in a Bush White House except
George Bush,'' Barilleaux says.
``They're going to give him a lot of window dressing, a space
council, drug task force, but he's going to be a man on the outside
... not a man who's going to be consulted in a crisis, except on a
pro forma basis.''
But Eddie Mahe Jr., a GOP consultant who worked with the Bush
campaign, says Bush is likely to give Quayle a more active role in
the administration than he had in the campaign.
``Vindication demands that. Both of them will want to prove how
right the decision was,'' Mahe says.
</P>
<P>
Democrats portrayed Quayle during the campaign as a lightweight,
a man with little or no legislative accomplishments, untested and
unqualified to be a heartbeat away from the presidency. Even some
members of Quayle's own party were dismayed at Bush's choice.
</P>
<P>
Quayle didn't help his case by making a number of celebrated
gaffes during the campaign, perhaps the worst being his garbled
explanation of the Holocaust and his declaration, ``I didn't live in
this century.''
Norman Ornstein, of the American Enterprise Institute, says
Quayle, while ``not the world's leading intellectual,'' is not ``a
complete dummy.'' He was simply thrust into a situation for which he
was unprepared, Ornstein says.
``I think he's immature. He's not stupid,'' Ornstein says.
</P>
<P>
But Quayle comes to the White House with ``a very damaging
stereotype that's developed about him that's widely believed in the
political community and that's believed by a large segment of the
electorate,'' Ornstein says.
``That's going to give him a good deal to overcome. It's going to
give him an enormous impetus to prove himself. That's going to be
difficult, given the office.''
Both Barilleaux and Stephen Hess of the Brookings Institution see
parallels in Quayle's vice presidency and those of Richard Nixon and
Spiro Agnew. The choice of Nixon was viewed as a move by Dwight
Eisenhower to appease the party's right wing, and Agnew was seen as
a political nonentity.
``The natural response is to use him (Quayle) sparingly, as Nixon
did with Agnew in 1968,'' Hess says. ``However, Quayle has four
years to prove himself, and I think you're going to see stories in
two years about how much he's learned, how much he's acted
responsibly, how far he's come from the campaign of 1988.''
Quayle admits the campaign was a learning process. After the
controversies subsided, Quayle declared his independence from his
Bush handlers, saying he would be his own man. He became more
accessible to the media but continued to adhere to the schedule
handed down from Washington and to deliver the party's scripted
message. Soon, he dropped off the front pages.
</P>
<P>
And although he occasionally spoke out in frustration at having
little control over his schedule and at ceasing to make national
news, he played the role of loyal No. 2 and even trumpeted his new
anonymity.
``We have arrived as being a traditional vice presidential
nominee because we are either on the back pages or either not on the
pages at all. That's what we're supposed to be,'' he told reporters.
</P>
<P>
That willingness to be a team player could serve him well in a
Bush White House, Mahe feels, since Bush wants ``a private adviser,
whose experience and opinion he respected ... (who) has never had
another agenda.''
``Dan Quayle owes his political life to one man and one man
alone,'' Mahe says. ``You're never going to see Dan Quayle telling
tales out of school.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA111289-0035
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>12
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
ROGER SIMON: A STRATEGY THAT BEARS REPEATING 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
One year after his election, Dan Quayle has achieved all he ever wanted: He has 
become dull. 
</P>
<P>
His coming-out party last Sunday was a true test of his new ability to not make 
news. He went on "Meet the Press." 
</P>
<P>
This was no small thing. During his entire campaign for the vice presidency, 
Quayle refused all requests from such national interview shows. He didn't 
appear on "Meet the Press" or "This Week With David Brinkley" or "Face the 
Nation." 
</P>
<P>
And he didn't do so because back then he was making too much news. His every 
slip, his every gaffe, his every goof was news. 
</P>
<P>
He was the stuff of nightly TV monologues. "A lot of people feel Quayle is just 
too inexperienced for a do-nothing job," Jay Leno once said. 
</P>
<P>
That joke was not only funny, but it got to the heart of a strange phenomenon: 
Americans didn't give a damn about the vice presidency (Mike Dukakis tried to 
make Quayle a major issue and failed), but some also felt that Quayle wasn't 
qualified for a job that had no qualifications. 
</P>
<P>
So when Quayle got to Washington, he got there with one goal: Support the 
President and make himself a very small target. Stay out of the headlines and 
give no reason for anyone to dump him in 1992. 
</P>
<P>
"We had asked him on the show a number of times," Christie Basham, senior 
producer of "Meet the Press" told me, "but he always declined. We renewed our 
request and then after saying he would not do the show, he changed his mind and 
said he would. It was the 42nd anniversary of the show and we wanted someone 
above and beyond the usual guest." 
</P>
<P>
And it says something about Dan Quayle's reputation that he would be considered 
"above and beyond" the usual guest. Normally, a vice president would not be. 
That's because vice presidents don't actually do anything. They don't run 
departments or make policy. They mostly wait for heads of state to expire. As 
George Bush once joked about his duties as vice president: "You die; I fly." 
</P>
<P>
But Quayle was considered a hot TV guest because he might screw up. He might 
make a mistake or say something outrageous or disagree with the President. 
</P>
<P>
None of this happened. The show was uneventful. Quayle answered all the 
questions put to him and he made little if any news. Some major newspapers 
didn't even bother to do a story the next day. 
</P>
<P>
It was everything Quayle had hoped for. 
</P>
<P>
I asked David Beckwith, his spokesman, why Quayle had waited so long to go on a 
major interview show. 
</P>
<P>
"Well, he wanted to concentrate on the more important part of the job," 
Beckwith said. "He wanted to solidify his relationship with the President and 
learn the inner workings of the administration." 
</P>
<P>
So why go on now? 
</P>
<P>
"It seemed like a particularly opportune week," Beckwith said. George Bush and 
Mikhail Gorbachev had announced a summit. Central America was back in the news. 
And, oh yeah, Bush had said Dan Quayle would be on the ticket in 1992. 
</P>
<P>
"And Marlin (Fitzwater, Bush's spokesman) called and just suggested we do the 
show," Beckwith said. 
</P>
<P>
The selection of Dan Quayle had been Bush's first major (and some would say 
only) decision of his presidential campaign. He had input from a number of 
people, but Quayle was George Bush's choice. 
</P>
<P>
Many thought it was a terrible choice, but there is nothing like a victory to 
give everything a rosy glow. And Bush's announcement that Quayle would be his 
running mate again was Bush's way of saying: "I didn't screw up the first time. 
I made a decision and it was the right decision and just to show you how right 
it was, I am making it again." 
</P>
<P>
And now was the time for Quayle to go on "Meet the Press" and show everybody 
just how right George Bush had been. 
</P>
<P>
I asked Beckwith if Quayle had been pleased by how the show had gone. 
</P>
<P>
"He was especially pleased with the seriousness of the questions," Beckwith 
said. "A lot of the time, you never know what you're going to get into. 
Sometimes the questions can be not particularly serious." 
</P>
<P>
A typical example of a "non-serious" question often put to Dan Quayle is: "Why 
does everyone say your wife is smarter than you?" 
</P>
<P>
But Quayle got no questions like that last week. I asked Christie Basham of 
"Meet the Press" if Quayle had asked in advance who the questioners would be. 
"Yes," Basham said, "but almost all the guests do." 
</P>
<P>
Quayle's questioners were David Broder of the Washington Post and Elizabeth 
Drew of the New Yorker, both of whom stuck to serious questions. (If Quayle had 
been told the questioners were going to be Hunter Thompson and Jimmy Breslin, I 
have a feeling Quayle might have come down with laryngitis.) 
</P>
<P>
After the show, Fitzwater called Quayle to express his, and presumably the 
President's, pleasure at how Quayle had handled himself. 
</P>
<P>
Quayle had said very little and he had said it very well. 
</P>
<P>
"The very limitations of a vice president's role don't make him an ideal 
guest," Beckwith admitted. "Almost by job description, a vice president is not 
permitted to make serious news." 
</P>
<P>
And Quayle knows his future is in sticking to that. During the 1988 campaign, I 
interviewed Quayle and I came away with one overwhelming impression: Dan Quayle 
would run for President in 1996. 
</P>
<P>
And he will do so, I believe, by being a vice president who keeps his head 
down, his nose clean and his life dull. 
</P>
<P>
After all, it worked for George Bush. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06140099
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  US; VICE-PRESIDENT; CITY; INDIANA; REACTION  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  QUAYLE'S HOMETOWN FLUSHED WITH PRIDE  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
PEOPLE in this picture-postcard town of Victorian houses and clean streets
don't care what Jay Leno or the polls or the Democrats or disgruntled
Republicans have been saying about Dan Quayle.;    Despite the fact that
President Bush's health problems have made the vice president a national
preoccupation, to people here he's just Danny Quayle from Polk Street - a
really nice guy from a really nice family that runs the local newspaper.  
</P>
<P>
He is the most important person ever to come out of this town, and even as
the world considers his fitness for the presidency, Huntington is celebrating
his life in what is ambitiously being billed as the Premiere Dan Quayle
Memorabilia Exhibit.;    To those who say Quayle does not merit his own
exhibition, Quayle devotees say with a mixture of defiance and dignity that he
is, after all, the vice president of the United States.;    "We're preserving
history," says David Schenkel, the exhibition coordinator. "A century from now
someone may want to do a dissertation on him.";    If so, Huntington will be
ready.;    Relatives, former classmates and longtime neighbors of Quayle have
donated yearbooks, report cards, poems, letters, his Little League uniform, a
coffee cup he drank from, a chair he once stood on during the 1988
presidential campaign and just about anything else he ever touched, wrote,
signed or posed for.;    The vice president's mother, Corinne, donated a lock
of his baby hair. The 1972 Indianapolis 500 queen produced a picture of
Quayle, then an aide to Indiana Gov. Edgar Whitcomb, accompanying her to the
race. And a former housekeeper turned in a 20-year-old piece of carpeting she
saved from one of Quayle's floors.;    The exhibition, which runs through May
20, was put together by the Dan Quayle Commemorative Foundation, a sort of
fan-club-turned-archive devoted to documenting the life and times of the
nation's 44th and, they say, least-understood vice president.;    "He has
taken such a bad rap," said Schenkel, a foundation board member. "If people
knew him, they'd see he's a regular person. If they had a chance to sit down
with Dan as a neighbor, they would see the extremely good values in the man.";
These are the faithful, who have long since stopped expecting "good press"
on their man. Instead they measure news reports on him by their relative
negativity, describing the best coverage as "more upbeat" or "halfway
decent.";    They defend the relatively young age of Quayle, who turned 44 in
February ("All he needs is a little seasoning"); his limited experience ("Look
at what they said about Truman - he was a haberdasher"), and his passion for
golf ("He has to have some form of relaxation"). But they are careful not to
stretch the superlatives. The description "nice" comes up a lot.;    "He's not
the fool that the talk show hosts think he is," says Dottie Watson, president
of the Republican Women of Huntington County. "He's a very nice person, a
capable person. Everybody I know says he can do it.";    That is not to say
some people don't have some friendly advice for Quayle. "If he would slow
down, talk an octave lower and think about what he's saying, I don't think
people would take him the way they do," said Jean Anne Drabenstot, the owner
of Nick's Kitchen, Quayle's favorite restaurant.;    Hayden Schenkel, chairman
of the Huntington County Democratic Party and a distant cousin of David
Schenkel, says, "Some people would shudder and shiver if he accidentally
became president of the United States. Most of the Democrats and even some of
the Republicans would say they're tickled to death to have him as vice
president, and they're 100 percent behind him. But in all due respect, we sure
hope nothing happens to President Bush.";    Quayle has declined an invitation
to attend the tribute, citing a busy schedule. Nonetheless, most of
Huntington's 17,000 residents have rallied around their native son for the
exhibition, which tracks his life from infancy through law school, from the
Senate to the vice presidency.;    The free exhibition has turned a gray room
in the town's public library into a virtual Dan Quayle museum. The display
patches together pieces of a life that until the last decade was strikingly
ordinary.;    There is Dan Quayle and his brother Chris riding horseback and
wearing cowboy hats, or sitting in front of the fireplace in their pajamas at
Christmas. There is Dan Quayle with his Vacation Bible School class, Dan
Quayle with the high school golf team, Dan Quayle at 5 or 6 years of age with
Sharon McEachern when they were named king and queen of the swim festival at
the Fort Wayne Country Club. It is all very 50s, very Middle American, almost
surreal in its innocence.;    There are windows into the workings of the
Quayle family, too. For example, his father, James, signed the report cards
when Dan brought home poor grades, and his mother signed when he brought home
good ones.;    And there are letters and poems that he wrote, which only go to
show that one does not have to be a Yeats to make it in politics. Dan wrote
this rather thoughtful verse on Nov. 22, 1960, when he was 13 years old:;   
My Dad is very very nice;    But he is not made of sugar and spice.;   
Sometimes he acts as if he has been disturbed;    But at other times he is as
cheerful as a bird.;    The exhibit also includes the 1972 newspaper
announcement of Dan and Marilyn Quayle's wedding, the wooden "Quayle 
</P>
<P>
amp;
</P>
<P>
Quayle"
shingle the couple hung when they opened their law practice here, and assorted
campaign souvenirs, including the official air sickness bag from the 1988
Republican National Convention.;    Ultimately, the foundation wants to build
a repository for the memorabilia. It has already organized a walking tour of
historic Quayle sites, like the white, ranch-style house where he spent his
early days, and Nick's Kitchen, where he likes to order tenderloins, fries and
a milkshake.;    "We want everybody to know he's a winner - I don't care what
the newspapers say," said Marge Hiner, one of the exhibit organizers. "What a
role model for our children, to know that you can be a normal person, come
from a normal family and become vice president of the United States."  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Huntington, Ind.  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>19
</DAY> 
<MONTH>05
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
