<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890925-0009
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>25
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
German Reunification Again Under Discussion as Changes Sweep Europe
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
An AP Extra
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, West Germany (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Three decades ago, a West German
politician said German reunification was a ``sleeping lioness''
that would awake one day with a mighty roar.
</P>
<P>
Now, there is growing speculation the awakening may be at hand
to create a giant political and economic machine that could
dominate Europe.
``Reunification is coming closer, but I can't say whether it
will take 10, 15 or 20 years,'' says West German conservative
lawmaker Eduard Lintner. ``We have the impression that things are
much more concrete than we could have imagined five years ago.''
The daily sight of thousands of refugees fleeing East German
leader Erich Honecker's hard-line Communist rule for the capitalist
West has revived international interest in the debate.
</P>
<P>
Once dismissed as a nostalgic daydream, the idea of German
reunification has gotten a public nod from President Bush and
something short of a categorical ``no'' from President Mikhail S.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev of the Soviet Union.
</P>
<P>
The idea makes East German leaders virtually apopletic.
``If there were a free choice under the present circumstances in
the German Democratic Republic (East Germany), certainly 80 percent
to 90 percent would vote for national reunification with the
Federal Republic of Germany,'' added the 44-year-old Lintner in an
Associated Press interview.
</P>
<P>
The West German constitution calls for a united Germany, but it
has not been a paramount concern of the West Germans in the years
since the ruins of Nazi Germany were divided into East and West at
the end of World War II.
</P>
<P>
Full national reunification would completey rework the postwar
European order mapped out by the conquering Allies. It is a
prospect that creates unease in Britain and France, and in Poland
in the East bloc.
</P>
<P>
London's prestigious Sunday Times on Sept. 10 mapped out a
possible scenario that includes massive troop reductions in Europe,
Honecker's death and further Westernization of Poland and Hungary.
``Moscow unilaterally abolishes the Warsaw Pact after guarantees
from Poland and Hungary they will not join other alliances,'' the
Times' futuristic view continued. ``West Germany withdraws from
NATO; and a referendum in both East and West Germany votes for
reunification and neutrality.''
That sort of talk is being heard more and more as Moscow loosens
its hold on the East bloc and countries like the Soviet Union,
Poland and Hungary explore democratic reforms.
</P>
<P>
The implications of pulling down the Berlin Wall and other
barriers to link the two German states are enormous and, for many,
ominous.
</P>
<P>
As much of Western Europe heads towards its own unification in
1992, the economic center of gravity would be shifted even further
to the German side with a powerhouse of nearly 80 million people _
61.1 million West Germans and 16.6 million East Germans.
</P>
<P>
West Germany is already Europe's largest exporting nation, and
despite its many flaws East Germany's economy is the envy of many
Soviet bloc neighbors.
</P>
<P>
A unified Germany could become the political focal point of a
continent already in flux, as democratic movements sweep parts of
the Soviet bloc.
</P>
<P>
Older generations recall eerie echoes of Nazi dictator Adolf
Hitler's boasting that he had brought about ``the unity of the
German nation.''
Eva Kulesza, head of research for the Soviet Union and Eastern
Europe at the French Institute of International Relations, says she
believes that ``as far as public opinion there is new sort of
mistrust toward Germany.
``This new fear of Germany is linked to German economic trends.
</P>
<P>
Germany is much stronger, much more dynamic than France,'' she
added.
</P>
<P>
Since West Germany and East Germany are at the front lines of
two competing alliances, any signs for eventual reunification would
have to come from Washington and Moscow.
</P>
<P>
During a news conference last week in Montana, Bush said that
reunification is a ``matter for the Germans to decide.''
But he added: ``If that (reunification) was worked out between
the Germanys, I do not think we should view that as bad for Western
interests.''
For his part, Gorbachev evaded the issue during a news
conference in Bonn in June, saying only, ``the situation in Europe
today was determined by historical realities.''
Outside Germany, political leaders and commentators have been
sharply divided on the issue.
``In thinking about the German Question, we ought not to be
governed by old prejudices and out-of-date assumptions,'' wrote
commentator Peter Jenkins in London's The Independent. ``The Cold
War was conducted in the name of freedom and, today, if the coming
of freedom to East Germany brings a desire for unity which finds
its echo in the Federal Republic, we ought not to be opposed.''
Willy Brandt, the Social Democrat who sought greater ties to the
East as chancellor in the 1970s, said German unity doesn't
necessarily mean a single state although he called reunification a
``hypothesis that cannot be excluded.''
As talk grows in the West, the positions against reunification
almost seem to harden in East Germany, as people leave the country
in near-record numbers. More than 100,000 East Germans are expected
to resettle in West Germany this year, leaving a gaping hole in the
Communist nation's work force.
</P>
<P>
Little is likely to change in East Germany as long as the
77-year-old Honecker and his aging comrades stay in power.
</P>
<P>
During a September 1987 visit to Bonn, Honecker called respect
for Europe's present borders a basic condition of peace.
``Socialism and capitalism can't be any more united than fire
and water,'' Honecker added on the issue of reunification.
</P>
<P>
There are virtually no indications that Honecker's successors
will be inclined to democratic reforms, let alone joining the
capitalist West.
</P>
<P>
The calls for reunification have already found a sympathetic ear
among some leaders of the Polish Solidarity movement, in the
country that suffered some of the Nazis' most brutal savagery.
``After all, the abnormal situation of the German nation
overshadows the whole of Polish-German relations,'' member of
Parliament Adam Michnik wrote on Monday in the pro-Solidarity daily
newspaper Gazeta Wyborcza, which he edits.
</P>
<P>
The renewed talk of reunification is recalling the nearly
prophetic words of Reinhold Maier, a prominent West German state
governor who later went on to head the centrist Free Democratic
Party.
``Reunification is resting in our midst like a sleeping lioness.
</P>
<P>
Tired and weak, indecisive people in West Germany are trying not to
disturb her sleep,'' Maier predicted in 1955. ``The lioness will
one day wake up, blink, snap her her tail and start to roar.''
Still, many in both East and West still agree with the 1967 quip
by Nobel Prize-winning French author Francois Mauriac: ``I love
Germany so much, I'm delighted that there are two of them.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891111-0064
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>11
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
East German Changes Spark Interest in Reunification
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The concept of a reunified Germany enjoys
support from the United States and other countries but some
analysts believe the consequences of a political and economic
German superstate could have an unsettling effect throughout Europe.
</P>
<P>
The lifting of travel restrictions by East Germany on Thursday
has breathed new life into the idea of a single German state,
drawing expressions of support from the Bush administration and
others.
</P>
<P>
But Soviet affairs expert William Hyland says that despite these
assertions, a reunified Germany is ``really terrifying to most of
the countries involved, to the West Germans, to the United States,
Soviet Union, Poland and Czechoslovakia.
``No one really wants German unity except the East German
people, and they turn out to be the decisive factor,'' says Hyland,
a one-time top aide to former Secretary of State Henry A. Kissinger.
</P>
<P>
It was just 2{ months ago when ceremonies were held
commemorating the 50th anniversary of the start of World War II, a
time when a unified Germany initiated what was to become the
slaughter of more than 50 million people.
</P>
<P>
While a recurrence of that nightmare seems remote at best under
any scenario, an undivided Germany could become the unchallenged
economic and political force on the continent.
</P>
<P>
The official U.S. policy on the reunification question was
outlined last Thursday by State Department deputy spokesman Richard
Boucher.
``Reunification has been supported by NATO and by the United
States for 40 years, and our strongly held view is that
reunification or reconciliation between the peoples of Germany must
take place in peace and freedom,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
As former National Security adviser Zbigniew Brzezinski sees it,
the reunification issue will become ``very, very active'' if a
freely elected government takes power in East Germany.
</P>
<P>
That possibility has been mentioned by East German leaders as
part of the ongoing reform process.
</P>
<P>
Brzezinski asks: ``How do we arrange for the unification of
Germany, so that it doesn't become destabilizing, so it isn't a
threat to Germany's neighbors _ France, Poland, Czechoslovakia?
``These are the issues we really have to very hard think about.
</P>
<P>
We have to think of a new structure between NATO and the Warsaw
Pact. That is our new agenda.''
Theodore Sorenson, a top aide to President John F. Kennedy when
the Berlin Wall was built in 1961, says he hopes a reunited Germany
will be forged as part of a reunited Europe.
</P>
<P>
Reunification, Sorenson says, ``will pose problems, because we
couldn't afford to have a reunited Germany outside the Western
Alliance. The Soviet Union couldn't afford to have a reunited
Germany as part of the Western Alliance.
``That's why I hope it will be a reunited Europe within which
the reunited Germany can take place,'' Sorenson says.
</P>
<P>
Bernard Rogers, a former commander of allied forces in Europe,
does not think reunification is inevitable. Some form of
federation, he believes, is more likely.
</P>
<P>
Rogers notes that Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev has said
the nations of eastern Europe can do what they want so long as they
stay in the Warsaw Pact.
``If East Germany stays in the Warsaw Pact, NATO, with the best
of its ability, would try to prevent full reunification; maybe a
confederation between the two Germanys, but not a full
reunification,'' Rogers says.
</P>
<P>
Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine, points out that
German reunification is a sensitive question for the Soviets.
``Soviet policy is based upon preventing a reunified,
economically strong and certainly militarily strong Germany,''
Mitchell says. ``There must be some serious apprehension in the
Soviet Union today, because the events of the last couple of days
certainly has made reunification more likely.''
The Bush administration says it does not foresee the dismantling
of NATO under any circumstances but, according to Hyland, the
reunification of Germany could mean the demise of the alliance.
``It may also mean the end of Western European unity, because
both have been based on a divided Germany and a divided Europe,''
Hyland says. ``If that comes to an end and 80 million Germans are
united in a confederation or a single state, it changes the entire
map of Europe.
``It changes all of the geopolitics and, in effect, ends the
period we've been in since ... the beginning of the war.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891202-0154
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>02
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
West German Leader Tries to Reassure U.S. Senators on NATO
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-East Germany
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Chancellor Helmut Kohl assured
visiting U.S. senators on the eve of a superpower summit that West
Germany will not forsake NATO to reunite with East Germany, one of
the senators said Friday.
``He strongly affirmed under no circumstances would a reunified
Germany be neutral,'' Sen. Richard G. Lugar, head of the American
delegation, said of the Friday meeting with Kohl.
</P>
<P>
Asked whether he thought the West Germans were committed to
staying in the NATO military alliance of Western nations, the
Indiana Republican said: ``Without any reservations.''
There is growing discussion in West Germany about German
reunification as a result of sweeping social and political reforms
underway in East Germany. There has been speculation that West
Germany might someday be tempted to agree to neutrality if the
Kremlin stipulates it as the price for reunification.
</P>
<P>
Kohl on Tuesday unveiled a 10-point proposal with German
reunification as its ultimate goal. But the Soviets, who suffered
millions of deaths fighting a unified Germany in World War II, have
said the idea of German reunification is ``dangerous and
unrealistic.''
President Bush and Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev are to
begin a shipboard summit off Malta on Saturday. The dramatic events
in East Germany and whirlwind reforms elsewhere in the East bloc
are likely to be a main topic of their talks.
</P>
<P>
Lugar came to Bonn with eight other members of the U.S. Senate's
arms control observer group. He said the purpose of the trip was to
``visit with the Germans on their judgments about all of these
procedures that are going on.''
U.S. Ambassador Vernon A. Walters joined the senators for their
75-minute closed-door talks with Kohl. The senators also met with
Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher and Defense Minister
Gerhard Stoltenberg during the day.
</P>
<P>
Lugar said Kohl told the Americans that reunification would be a
``procedure that depends on many events in Germany and Europe'' and
that the Soviet Union and the United States have a role to play.
</P>
<P>
Lugar said of Kohl's proposals, ``There is much to work with
there with regard to the future of Germany and the future of the
(NATO) alliance.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891207-0158
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>07
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Poland Says Any German Reunification Must Be Gradual
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The government on Thursday allowed for the
possibility of a reunified Germany, but said such a state must be
formed gradually and respect Poland's borders.
</P>
<P>
In the Solidarity government's first definitive statement on the
issue, Foreign Minister Krzysztof Skubiszewski told Parliament the
two German states could be joined as part of the process of uniting
Europe.
</P>
<P>
He said German reunification ``cannot go ahead'' of the
reunification of Europe.
``A reunited Germany will not be created tomorrow or the day
after tomorrow,'' Skubiszewski said. ``Fears and concerns appearing
every now and then, including in Poland, are unjustified, although
alertness is recommended.''
Asked about German reunification at a news conference in Gdansk,
Solidarity labor leader Lech Walesa said he prefers ``no political
changes in Europe, but there should be all kinds of economic
integrations.''
Western European countries have agreed to form an economic union
by the end of 1992.
</P>
<P>
Sweeping democratic reforms have taken hold in East Germany in
the past several weeks under the pressure of mass protests,
spurring talk of reuniting the two German states divided at the end
of World War II. West Germany has proposed a plan for greater
unity, but East German leaders reject reunification.
</P>
<P>
The specter of a powerful, reunited Germany has troubed many
Poles, especially the older ones who recall the 1939 Nazi invasion
of Poland that began World War II.
</P>
<P>
A reported surge in anti-Polish sentiment in East Germany in
recent weeks has heightened Polish anxieties.
</P>
<P>
Skubiszewski's speech seemed designed to reassure Poles that the
government does not see unification in the near future and will
insist on Poland's current borders.
</P>
<P>
Skubiszewski faulted West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl's
program for gradual German reunification, offered last week, for
not making clear that reunification would respect the existing
border between Poland and East Germany.
</P>
<P>
Some right-wing West German politicians have called for
recovering the 40,000 square miles of territory that Germany lost
to Poland at the end of World War II. The territory is about
one-third of present-day Poland.
</P>
<P>
East Germany and West Germany each separately has recognized the
border, but there has been no official assurance that a reunified
Germany would also acknowledge the border.
``One can only unite within established borders and without
territorial arguments,'' said Skubiszewski.
</P>
<P>
He also said German reunification is unlikely as long as West
Germany belongs to NATO and East Germany to the Soviet-led Warsaw
Pact military alliance.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891212-0062
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>12
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Party Admits Socialism Failed; Reunification Splits Democracy Movement
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: SUBS 3rd graf `Also today...' with 1 graf to UPDATE with Baker
meeting with Modrow. Pickup 4th graf `In another...'
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhoto LEI2
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LEIPZIG, East Germany (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Communist Party today admitted
that East Germany's socialist system has failed, and expressed
support for a type of partnership with West Germany.
</P>
<P>
The statement in the Communist Party newspaper Neues Deutschland
was one of the bluntest official assessments to date of the
country's increasingly troubled situation. It came a day after
shouting matches broke out over German reunification during
pro-democracy protests in Leipzig and Dresden.
</P>
<P>
Also today, Secretary of State James A. Baker III urged caution
on the reunification issue. He visited the Berlin Wall and met with
West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl and East German Premier Hans
Modrow.
</P>
<P>
In another development, the largest opposition movement, New
Forum, announced it will take part as a political party in the
country's first free elections, scheduled for May 6.
</P>
<P>
Neues Deutschland, in proposing a new party platform, said
``socialism has definitely failed as a social system in our
country'' and acknowledged that the ``popular revolutionary
movement'' of the past weeks had led to the scrapping of the old
system.
</P>
<P>
The paper repeated the Communists' promise to work for a new
``democratic socialism'' within a multi-party system.
</P>
<P>
During the past few weeks, both Germanys have increased business
and cultural ties but have debated what labels to use for closer
relations, since the East Berlin government rejects calls for
reunification.
</P>
<P>
Neues Deutschland urged a ``qualified partnership of both German
states'' but rejected any suggestions of resolving the ``German
question.''
During Monday's demonstrations that drew more than 200,000
protesters, the largest of them the now-weekly rally in the
southern city of Leipzig, speakers warned that the reunification
issue could fracture the popular movement that has forced the
ruling Communists into swift retreat.
</P>
<P>
One sign said ``Germany United Fatherland,'' using a phrase from
the West German national anthem.
</P>
<P>
Others, opposing reunification, urged ``No Fourth Reich'' and no
transformation of East Germany into West Germany's ``plantation.''
</P>
<P>
ADN said 40,000 people demonstrated for reunification in
Karl-Marx-Stadt, while several thousand people split into pro- and
anti-reunification groups at a rally in Dresden.
</P>
<P>
Smaller rallies were also reported by ADN in Schwerin, Potsdam,
Neubrandenburg and Halle. The agency did not say if reunification
played a role in those protests.
</P>
<P>
The rallies came shortly after the four victorious World War II
Allies met in West Berlin to discuss the latest developments in
East Germany and Berlin _ the divided city that they still
technically administer.
</P>
<P>
The meeting brought together officials of the United States,
France and Britain with Soviet officials, who have increasingly
expressed concern over calls in both Germanys to reunite the
country.
</P>
<P>
Kohl has advocated a confederation of the two Germanys, to be
followed by eventual reunification. But he stressed to reporters on
Monday that ``the goal of our policies is not to create an
overpowering Germany in the middle of Europe.'' The West German
leader advocates a reunified Germany that would respect the
security needs _ and borders _ of the rest of Europe.
</P>
<P>
Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, during a Central
Committee in Moscow on Saturday, urged the West not to try to
influence developments in East Germany. East Germany is a front
line of defense for the Soviets, who have nearly 400,000 troops in
the country.
</P>
<P>
ADN said Gorbachev would meet soon with Gregor Gysi, a reformer
who was chosen East German Communist Party chief on Saturday.
</P>
<P>
Gysi's rise followed the ouster of two sets of Communist
leaders. Since East Germans began agitating for an end to Communist
domination two months ago, public pressure has forced the opening
of the Berlin Wall and pushed the Communists to promise free
elections and relinquish their political monopoly.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900130-0202
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>30
</DAY> 
<MONTH>01
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Gorbachev Leaves Door Open to German Reunification
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-East Germany, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev met Tuesday with
East German Premier Hans Modrow and appeared to be more open toward
eventual German reunification.
</P>
<P>
Modrow told reporters after the meeting that Gorbachev ``did not
rule out such a prospect in the future, and at the same time did
not venture to set some time limits for that.''
Earlier, the Kremlin chief said any such decisions must include
the four Allied powers and take into account European opinions.
``The development of events in the world, in East Germany, in
the Soviet Union demand deep consideration and an analytical
approach to deciding this problem,'' he said in remarks reported by
the official news agency Tass.
``Time itself is acting on this process, giving it dynamism,''
Gorbachev said. ``We have to act responsibly and not decide this
important question on the streets.''
Tass said Gorbachev emphasized that talks about restructuring
relations between the two Germanys must involve ``all directly
interested governments.''
Asked by an East German correspondent about his attitude toward
reunification, Gorbachev said the question was not unexpected and
that ``no one can cast doubt'' on the reasonableness of asking it.
</P>
<P>
However, the English-language Tass translation indicated
Gorbachev could have meant there were no doubts about reunification
itself.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev's position was similar to that adopted by Communists
in East Berlin on Tuesday. For the first time, the Communists
acknowledged German unity as a long-term goal but said it must be
imbedded in the process of overcoming Europe's overall divisions.
</P>
<P>
The Soviet Union traditionally has strongly opposed any talk of
German reunification, but Gorbachev has softened that position in
adopting a policy that has allowed radical reform in Eastern Europe.
</P>
<P>
Soviets say the question of German reunification is to be
decided in the future.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev, in comments to reporters after meeting French
President Francois Mitterrand in Kiev in December, reiterated his
view that the existence of two German states is a fact based on the
outcome of World War II.
</P>
<P>
But he added, ``The present situation is the result of specific
historical events, a specific historical process on this continent.
</P>
<P>
So, history should decide the future of this continent.''
``I don't think it is a topical question today. A different
approach may create a situation that would complicate the entire
European process, including the relations between the two German
states,'' Gorbachev said.
</P>
<P>
Modrow said the two Germanys could work toward confederation in
phases with no time limit.
</P>
<P>
He said he agreed with Gorbachev that reunification must be
decided not only by East and West Germany, but all of Europe.
</P>
<P>
According to Tass, the Soviet leader said any action on
reunification must not infringe on the interests of either East or
West Germany, the four Allied powers: France, Britain, the United
States or the Soviet Union, or anyone else in Europe.
</P>
<P>
Count Otto Lambsdorff, head of West Germany's Free Democratic
Party, a partner in the governing coalition, said Tuesday in London
that Gorbachev has adopted ``a more positive attitude'' toward
German reunification.
</P>
<P>
In a TV interview on Britain's Channel 4, he also urged
``economic union'' within 18 months as a prelude to full union of
West and East Germany.
</P>
<P>
Lambsdorff said that because of East Germany's political
instability it had only two choices _ unification or chaos.
</P>
<P>
Modrow invited Gorbachev and Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov to visit
East Germany and they accepted, Tass reported.
</P>
<P>
Modrow arrived in Moscow late Monday. A Communist, he has moved
forward the country's first free elections from May to March 18 and
brought the opposition into a coalition that will govern until then.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900131-0068
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>31
</DAY> 
<MONTH>01
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
West Germans Praise Gorbachev's Comments on Reunification
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
West German officials and media today praised
Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev for softening his view on
German reunification and said it could give hope to disheartened
East Germans.
</P>
<P>
Disgraced former Communist Party leader Erich Honecker was
released from prison Tuesday night after justice officials
determined he was too frail to withstand the rigors of imprisonment
while awaiting trial on treason charges.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev said Tuesday in Moscow that he believed one Germany
was likely in the future, but he added that Germans ``should not
decide this important question on the streets.''
He referred to the growing number of demonstrations in East
Germany in support of reunification.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev's statement was his most tolerant yet on the subject
of a single Germany, which has been opposed by Communists for more
than 40 years. East German Communists on Tuesday endorsed for
reunification for the first time.
</P>
<P>
In West Germany, Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher told
West German Radio that Gorbachev had ``correctly analyzed'' the
situation and again shown his political skill.
</P>
<P>
West German officials and media praised Gorbachev's view as
``realistic'' and described it as an important sign of hope for
East Germans who have lost faith in their government.
</P>
<P>
Communist leaders launched their uphill campaign for March 18
parliamentary elections with a news conference to unveil their
``European concept'' that aims for a united and demilitarized
Europe.
</P>
<P>
Party ideologist Peter Brie said the Communists support ``the
togetherness of the German nation,'' and urged a thoughtful and
measured approach to reunification.
</P>
<P>
In an interview with the West German Bild newspaper, party
leader Gregor Gysi complained that the reunification drive is
moving too quickly.
</P>
<P>
Asked if the Communists oppose reunification, Gysi told the
newspaper: ``No, not at all. This process cannot be stopped any
more. But it is irresponsible to do things in such a way now as if
it were possible tomorrow.''
The reunification issue promises to dominate the election
campaign that will seat a new leadership in less than seven weeks.
</P>
<P>
Increasing numbers of East Germans have demonstrated for union
with wealthy and prosperous West Germany as their own economy
tumbles and an exodus of skilled workers continues unchecked.
</P>
<P>
More than 340,000 people fled East Germany last year, having
lost hope that their spartan living conditions would improve. The
devastating flight has included as many as 2,500 people daily since
Jan. 1.
</P>
<P>
The Communists are widely distrusted because of corruption
scandals that have surfaced since the peaceful pro-democracy revolt
last fall, and because they carry the blame for leading East
Germany into its current economic and political crises.
</P>
<P>
The man most blamed for the country's problems, Honecker, was
set free after an East Berlin court rejected a request that he be
kept in prison until his trial in March. He was jailed Monday.
</P>
<P>
The court decided that ``despite the severity of the charges
against Honecker, the state of the accused's health does not permit
imprisonment,'' the official ADN news agency reported.
</P>
<P>
A spokesman for Chief Prosecutor Hans-Juergen Joseph promised
that the investigation against Honecker would proceed.
</P>
<P>
ADN said the court acted on advice from two doctors who examined
Honecker independently. Honecker, 77, underwent surgery on Jan. 8
to remove a malignant kidney tumor.
</P>
<P>
Honecker was ousted from the leadership on Oct. 18, after
massive pro-democracy demonstrations. He was expelled from the
Communist Party in December and has since been accused of treason
and abusing his power.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900210-0106
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>10
</DAY> 
<MONTH>02
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Thousands Demonstrate for Unification
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Germany-Soviet, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
About 20,000 East Germans, many carrying West
German flags, demonstrated Saturday for speedy German
reunification, the official East German news agency ADN said.
</P>
<P>
As the demonstrators rallied in the southern city of Plauen,
West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl said in Moscow that Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev had given him an unequivocal promise
to respect German reunification. Kohl declared it a ``very good day
for Germany.''
Kohl and Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher also disclosed
that they expect a reunification plan with agreement of the World
War II Allies to be ready before the end of the year for
presentation to a pan-European summit meeting.
</P>
<P>
Calls for German reunification have increased since the ouster
of the hard-line Communist leadership and the opening of East
Germany's borders during the fall pro-democracy movement.
</P>
<P>
Despite reforms, nearly 2,000 East Germans, most of them skilled
workers, continue to leave their homeland daily, crippling an
economy already troubled by strikes and absenteeism.
</P>
<P>
Earlier Saturday, West German Finance Minister Theo Waigel said
the East German economy was in a ``sorrowful state'' and urged the
East German government to release details on its financial
situation.
</P>
<P>
Waigel's comments came after a day after a high-ranking official
in Bonn warned that East Germany is rapidly approaching insolvency.
``Things are escalating,'' Waigel said in an interview with West
Berlin radio. ``The economy is in a sorrowful state. The political
authority is crumbling.''
He said the Bonn government believes East Germany's foreign debt
stands at $18 billion.
``If the situation has changed, the East German government must
say so,'' said Waigel, a conservative who has been pushing for
establishment of a common currency for the two states.
</P>
<P>
Also Saturday, more than 100 East Germans protested in front of
the Soviet Embassy in East Berlin against the stationing of Soviet
helicopters in their country, ADN said.
</P>
<P>
ADN said the demonstrators held signs saying ``Gorbi, what about
disarmament?'' and ``Tanks out, helicopters in?''
The protesters, from the East German town of Prenzlau, claimed
the Soviets had backed out of disarmament plans by replacing a tank
unit that had been stationed at a military base there with
helicopters, ADN reported.
</P>
<P>
According to ADN, the demonstrators, who came from church and
citizens' groups as well as from the town council, issued a
statement calling for civilian use of the base.
</P>
<P>
Prenzlau, a town of 22,000, is located about 50 miles north of
Berlin.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900214-0157
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>14
</DAY> 
<MONTH>02
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Jewish Leader Seeks to Discuss Reunification with Germans
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-The German Question, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The chairman of the Simon Wisenthal Center has
asked to meet with the leaders of West and East Germany to discuss
``the great fear that German reunification brings to the community
of victims of Nazism.''
``I must tell you I am not among those in the cheering section
applauding the rush towards German reunification,'' Rabbi Marvin
Hier wrote Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany and Prime
Minister Hans Modrow of East Germany.
``However, if that is the inevitable course, let us at least
place on record our concerns,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Hier is the founder of the center, headquartered in Los Angeles,
which seeks to keep alive the memory of the Nazi persecution of
Jews in Germany and Nazi-conquered lands.
</P>
<P>
In nearly identical letters, he asked to meet with Kohl during
his forthcoming trip to Washington and with Modrow in Germany next
month. The letters were made available Wednsday to The Associated
Press.
``You are undoubtedly aware,'' he wrote both leaders, ``of the
great fear that German reunification brings to the community of
victims of Nazism.''
``It is not an irrational fear of the kind that one explains
away as the nightmares of victims who remain locked into their past
and lose all perspective of present reality.
``The fears are real because those who bear the scars of the
last `unified Germany' do not see their concerns being addressed in
the current reunification discussions betwen world leaders.''
Hier listed 10 points he wanted to raise. Among them were a
program to teach German schoolchildren about the annhilation of the
Jews; the creation of an agency to monitor and prosecute hate
groups; the continuation of the ``special relationship'' now
existing between West Germany and Israel; the convening of a 1992
conference of world leaders on the 50th anniversary of the
conference at which ``the final solution'' was developed; the
establisment of a German commission to protect Holocaust sites; the
banning of terrorist organizations that ``have enjoyed
respectablity in East Germany;'' a cultural exchange program
between German and Jewish organizations; German television and
radio programs on the reconciliation; restitution payments to the
families and victims of Nazism, and a German commitment to
revitalize former synagogues in East German territory.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900215-0013
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>15
</DAY> 
<MONTH>02
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
A Single Germany: No Fear of Jackboots, But Worries Nonetheless
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Historians say the world need not fear that
German jackboots will echo again on European pavements, but some
still see the rush toward German reunification as a setback _ a
step away from the integration of Europe.
</P>
<P>
For the most part, the historians say an East Germany collapsing
into chaos represents a greater threat to stability than a united
German state.
``The West Germans are moving ahead not out of nationalistic
fervor, but a perceived need to deal with a crisis,'' said Henry
Ashby Turner of Yale, author of ``The Two Germanies Since 1945.''
``There is no such a thing as indelible national character,''
Turner said. ``I don't think there is any chance that the young men
of Germany are going to slip out of their Adidas running shoes and
pull on jackboots and start running around saying, `Heil!''
He was one of several experts in German history discussing the
implications of reunification following the decision Tuesday by the
four World War II allies _ the United States, Britain, France and
the Soviet Union _ to accept the reunification of a Germany they
divided 45 years ago.
</P>
<P>
University of Chicago historian Michael Geyer, a native of
Germany, said he feared the creation of a ``strong, sovereign
nation in the center of Europe'' could reverse a more important
development _ the 40-year drive toward an integrated Europe in
which industries, banks, trade unions and even government
ministries have been collaborating across borders.
``The East German state is collapsing,'' said Geyer. ``So
something has to happen very dramatically. But they have a choice _
the Europeans and Germans and Americans. Do they want to opt for
the European card or for the German card? I think they are opting
for the German card.''
``I hear these days very little about what Gorbachev called `the
house of Europe,''' he said.
</P>
<P>
The result of a dominant ``uncomfortably strong'' German state,
Geyer added, could be a setback to the diminishment of national
borders. It could also mean, he said, that American troops might
have to stay in Europe as a counterweight to Germany.
``If I had my druthers reunifications would have happened after
1992, after the integration of the West German economy into the
economy of Western Europe,'' said Charles J. Herber of George
Washington University, expressing similar concern.
``Then there would have been fewer chances for German
adventurers,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
West Germans were aware of their European neighbors' misgivings,
said Richard Breitman of American University, and so they presented
reunification within the context of European integration. They
wanted to avoid arousing fear of a united Germany again dominating
Europe.
``Even if the history did not exist, there would be fears of
that kind,'' he said. ``We're dealing not just with rational
calculation but a whole host of emotional memories.''
For all that, Breitman said, ``One Germany is not only
inevitable, but given the successful record of West Germany over
the last 40 years, my feeling is it is better than having a regime
in chaos.''
``The only alternative to reunification,'' added Turner, is an
East Germany in ruins, ``a basket case, a Bangladesh of Europe.''
He said Germans have ``no significant interest in territorial
revisions. Those misgivings are misplaced.''
Gerhard Weinberg of the University of North Carolina, considered
a leading historian of the Nazi era, cautioned that reunification,
if mishandled, could prove explosive.
</P>
<P>
While the people of West Europe have gotten over nationalistic
distrusts, East Europeans, living in closed societies, have not, he
said, and fear of Germany is a reality in East Europe and Russia,
he said.
``I don't think the Germans are heading for Moscow again, but we
have to give people _ and the Germans have to give people _ time to
think this through and get used to it. ... Mishandled,
reunification could scare one or the other of the participants into
starting something and scare others and goodness knows where it
would end.''
Gordon Craig, emeritus professor at Stanford, said the division
of Germany has been the basis of a peace settlement ``which worked
pretty well'' but was ``abnormal and sooner or later had to be
corrected.''
German reunification, said Craig, gives the world the chance to
build a new international system, one that ``will prevent the use
of international violence.''
He added, ``We have to be careful that we don't fall back into
the kind of system that existed before the Second World War, a
Europe filled with nations that were suffering various grievances,
rivalries, disputed frontiers, driven by what they considered to be
legitimate reasons but pitted against each other _ the sort of
things that gave rise to Hitler in 1933.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900321-0057
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>21
</DAY> 
<MONTH>03
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Jewish Leaders To Meet in Berlin on German Reunification
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Berlin villa where the Nazi leadership met
to implement the ``final solution'' against Europe's Jewish
population will be the site of a World Jewish Congress conference
on German reunification.
</P>
<P>
The New York-based organization announced Tuesday that the
meeting is scheduled for May 8, the 45th anniversary of V-E Day.
``The world is expecting a Jewish statement on reunification,''
said Edgar Bronfman, the president of the World Jewish Congress.
``I think that the place where they decided on the `final
solution' is the right place to have such a meeting, and the
anniversary of the victory in Europe seems to be the right day.''
Some 100 members of the World Jewish Congress from about 70
countries will attend the conference at the villa in Wannsee,
Berlin, where on Jan. 20, 1942, high German government and party
officials adopted a plan to exterminate the Jews.
``Jews have a right to state a moral position on German
reunification and we will make a moral statement. And part of that
moral statement is to see that it (the Holocaust) doesn't happen
again,'' Bronfman said.
</P>
<P>
In the long run, he said, a united Germany can be ``a very
positive thing'' for Europe, but certain precautions must be taken
to prevent a repeat of history. For example, Germany's borders
``must be sealed in cement,'' and the country should not be allowed
nuclear weapons, he said.
</P>
<P>
Bronfman said he does not fear a resurgence of anti-Semitism
once the two Germanys are united. In fact, he said, reunification
might cause a decline in anti-Jewish feelings.
``Now that reunification is about to be a fact, they won't be
blaming the Jews'' for a divided Germany, Bronfman explained.
</P>
<P>
The conference will convene May 6 and a formal declaration on
German reunification will be issued May 8. It will be the first
meeting ever held on German soil by the World Jewish Congress,
which was founded in 1936 in response to Hitler's threats against
Jews.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-6509
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>24
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>92
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
FT  24 AUG 92 / Letter: The Bundesbank is led to the dock
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Sir, The argument for an independent central bank is that it should be free
of party political interference, not that it should conduct monetary policy
without regard to national, regional or global interests.
</P>
<P>
Whatever policy the Kohl government followed over reunification, it was
bound to unleash a large federal deficit and inflationary pressures in
Germany. As the western German population is now aware, German reunification
needs a strong, growing west German economy to finance the subsidisation of
eastern Germans' living standards until there is a sustained upswing in the
east - even if at the cost of higher German inflation than the Bundesbank
would wish.
</P>
<P>
In Europe as a whole, very high real interest rates threaten to turn
recession into depression. The governments of Europe have been remarkably
patient with the Bundesbank, although it is threatening nearly 10 years of
European effort for greater economic and political integration. Surely there
must be compromise of some economic habits to achieve the latter?
</P>
<P>
It is ironic that, just when German reunification presented a short-term
reason for Germany to shift its anti-inflationary economic and monetary
priorities, accommodating European convergence, Bundesbank intransigence is
threatening the EMU commitment.
</P>
<P>
Beyond Europe, the dominant economic forces are strongly disinflationary.
</P>
<P>
But Germany is the one economy which, for reasons of reunification, could
afford a more relaxed stand on the inflationary front.
</P>
<P>
Yet Mr Otmar Issing, the Bundesbank's chief economist, advises there are no
grounds for a cut in Germany's interest rates. This, despite the
unreliability of German money supply data.
</P>
<P>
The German government might point out to the Bundesbank that monetary
targets might be achievable only at the cost of many more than 3m unemployed
in Germany, of the destruction of the EMU programme and global depression.
</P>
<P>
A DM exchange rate adjustment within the ERM is not the answer to the
problems. We need a prolonged low-interest-rate German reunification boom.
</P>
<P>
The European currency bloc is overvalued against the dollar and yen as a
result of Bundesbank interest rate policies. And this is aggravating
recession.
</P>
<P>
A future European-wide central bank must clearly - like the US Federal
Reserve - be more accountable in the broader European political and economic
interest.
</P>
<P>
The governments and central banks of Europe and the G7 block - including the
Kohl administration - should pressurise the Bundesbank, and be prepared to
consider constitutional changes if necessary, to halt this idiocy.
</P>
<P>
Howard Flight,
managing director,
Guinness Flight
Global Asset Management,
Lighterman's Court,
5 Gainsford Street,
Tower Bridge,
London SE1 2NE
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA021290-0043
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>12
</DAY> 
<MONTH>2
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
'WAY IS FREE' FOR GERMAN REUNIFICATION, KOHL SAYS 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
BONN 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl declared on his return from Moscow on Sunday 
that "the way is now free" for German reunification. 
</P>
<P>
His meeting with Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev convinced him, he told 
West German radio, that the two German states should "enter into negotiations 
as quickly as possible" after the March 18 East German election. 
</P>
<P>
Kohl will meet with East German Prime Minister Hans Modrow on Tuesday and 
Wednesday in Bonn to discuss immediate steps in economic cooperation, including 
monetary union, to prevent the collapse of the faltering East German economy. 
</P>
<P>
"Political and economic union go hand in hand," Kohl said. 
</P>
<P>
He said that immediate steps must be taken on the economic front to "stop the 
hemorrhage of East Germans to the Federal Republic and keep them in their 
heimat," or home, in East Germany. 
</P>
<P>
Kohl said that his talks with Gorbachev - who told him that reunification is a 
matter for the Germans themselves to decide - could lead to an "economic 
breakthrough" in East Germany, which in turn could provide a "push forward" for 
all of Europe. 
</P>
<P>
Asked how soon the two Germanys could merge, Kohl declared that the March 
election has to come first, and "then I think it will all go very quickly." 
</P>
<P>
The chancellor said that almost all of the political parties and opposition 
groups in East Germany now support reunification. And after the election, he 
said, "they will want to put their programs into practice quickly." 
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev inquired about plans by West German politicians to campaign in East 
Germany, Kohl said, adding that the Soviet leader did not appear to be upset 
about such political activity. 
</P>
<P>
West Germany's Social Democratic Party is expected to campaign heavily in East 
Germany in support of a fledging branch of the party that has taken a 
surprisingly strong lead in public opinion polls. 
</P>
<P>
Major members of the party, including former Chancellor Willy Brandt, are 
scheduled to appear at rallies on behalf of the East German Social Democrats. 
</P>
<P>
With the surge of the East German Social Democrats, political analysts are 
pointing to the strange role they could play in the ultimate political fate of 
Kohl. 
</P>
<P>
Ever since reunification became a blazing issue, Kohl's standing in West German 
opinion polls has risen, and if the national elections, now scheduled for 
December, were held today, he would have a good chance of leading his Christian 
Democratic Union to victory. 
</P>
<P>
But if the two Germanys are fused before the West Germany election in December, 
the growing number of Social Democratic voters in what today is East Germany - 
who would presumably be allowed to vote in December - could easily tip the 
balance away from the Christian Democrats, pushing Kohl out of the government 
leadership. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
KOHL, HELMUT; REUNIFICATION; EAST GERMANY - FOREIGN RELATIONS - WEST GERMANY; 
USSR - FOREIGN RELATIONS - WEST GERMANY; GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>WSJ890922-0113
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> WSJ 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>12
</DAY> 
<MONTH>2
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
 East German Exodus Sparks Discussion
@  On the Possibility of Reuniting Germany
@  -
@  By Terence Roth
@  Staff Reporter of The Wall Street Journal 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE> FRANKFURT, West Germany  
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The mass emigration of thousands of disaffected East Germans has rekindled reunification talk in West Germany, where some legislators plan to begin exploring the possiblity of reuniting the two Germanys. 
</P>
<P>
No one is predicting a date for a possible reunification. 
</P>
<P>
Proponents acknowledge the risks of assuming too much of East Bloc reform trends, and most hedge their thoughts with careful references to Washington and Moscow. 
</P>
<P>
Yet growing signs of ferment in East Germany have given Chancellor Helmut Kohl's government reason to consider the possibilities. 
</P>
<P>
Eduard Lintner, parliamentary speaker on German affairs for the joint Christian Democrat and Christrian Socialist caucus in the Bundestag, said his committee has placed reunification on its October agenda. 
</P>
<P>
He said the sessions, which will include government officials and outside experts, hopefully can devise reunification models to discuss with West Germany's Western allies, particularly the U.S. 
</P>
<P>
"It has become clear to the world that the Communist system in East Germany is in trouble," Mr. Lintner said. 
</P>
<P>
"The time has come for us to show our allies, but also reform-minded people in the East, that German reunification is no longer just a theory but a subject requiring a serious appraisal of how it could come about." 
"There are still a number of imponderables," Mr. Linter conceded. 
</P>
<P>
"For instance, we want the federal government to approach our allies and get their thoughts on the reunification topic." 
The U.S. ambassador to Bonn, Vernon A. Walters, earlier this month reaffirmed Washington's policy of supporting a German reunification based on free, democratic elections. 
</P>
<P>
But Mr. Walters caused a stir by predicting that reunion could occur in the relatively near future. 
</P>
<P>
Emerging opposition to uncompromising Communist rule in East Germany has raised questions on how long East Berlin's leaders can resist the democratic reforms sweeping through neighboring East Bloc countries. 
</P>
<P>
Reforms in Poland, Hungary and even the Soviet Union have magnified East Germany's Stalinist controls. 
</P>
<P>
Fledgling protest groups, and the influential Protestant church, have begun pressing for reforms in East Germany which, if allowed to include free elections, could eventually lead to a reunited Germany, according to some Western experts. 
</P>
<P>
Dorothee Wilms, Bonn's cabinet minister for inter-German affairs, said in an interview in the newspaper Welt am Sonntag that recent polls show that between 85% and 90% of all West Germans favor a reunifed Germany. 
</P>
<P>
"The desire for reunification, a feeling of togetherness, a sense of nationhood - all this has strongly increased in recent years," Ms. Wilms told the newspaper. 
</P>
<P>
"The recent escape movement from the DDR makes especially clear that people of both German states want to live free amongst themselves," she said, but cautioned that reunification cannot occur overnight. 
</P>
<P>
The first step, she added, "is the reform process in the DDR." 
Most West German governments since 1949 have paid only lip service to the reunification goal set down in the preamble of West Germany's constitution. 
</P>
<P>
Political realities have prevented the topic from becoming a serious issue. 
</P>
<P>
Analysts say that four decades of different systems would make reunification difficult. 
</P>
<P>
Further, many West German workers worry that a mass influx of East Germans could threaten their jobs. 
</P>
<P>
Thousands of East Germans have emigrated to West Germany over the Austro-Hungarian border since Budapest ignored East Berlin's protests and opened its border. 
</P>
<P>
Close to 80,000 East German refugees have arrived in West Germany so far this year, either legally or by escaping, and a total of more than 100,000 are expected by December. 
</P>
<P>
The Soviets have joined East Berlin in criticizing Bonn for welcoming the East German refugees, and chided Hungary for violating an emigration treaty with East Germany by allowing them to leave. 
</P>
<P>
Moscow, which has tolerated reforms elsewhere in the East Bloc, is said to be concerned by conditions in East Germany, perhaps the most important of its Warsaw Pact satellites. 
</P>
<P>
Unconfirmed West German intelligence reports appearing in the West German media said Moscow fears a growing dissident movement and mass demonstrations in East Germany by next year. 
</P>
<P>
Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev accepted an invitation to attend East Germany's 40th anniversary celebration, providing an opportunity for serious discussions with Erich Honecker, East Berlin's ailing party leader. 
</P>
<P>
East Germany's Communist leadership, commented the newspaper Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, "has no illusions as to why Gorbachev is honoring their 40th anniversary. 
</P>
<P>
He certainly will not say 'well done, keep it up.'" 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
