<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06255336
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  US; COURT; JUDGE; CANDIDATE; MEETING; CONGRESS  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  SENATORS PRESSED FOR OPINIONS ON JUDGE
PARTISAN GROUPS TARGET LAWMAKERS  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
While the 14-member Senate Judiciary Committee presses Clarence Thomas to
explain his qualifications for the Supreme Court, all 100 senators are under
mounting pressure to explain their views of the judge.;   There were these
signs of pressure Tuesday:  
</P>
<P>
(check) About 300 black pastors, representing congregations totaling more
than 1 million churchgoers in 30 states, held a rally on the steps of the
Supreme Court and then lobbied their senators to support confirmation of
President Bush's Supreme Court nominee.;   The ministers were recently
organized into a conservative Coalition for the Restoration of the Black
Family and Society, with the first item on its agenda being Thomas'
confirmation.;   (check) A television ad supporting Thomas, shown in four
Southern states where senators face re-election campaigns next year, attracted
10,000 calls between Friday and Sunday, according to Gary Bauer, organizer of
the conservative Citizens Committee to Confirm Clarence Thomas, which financed
the ad's production.;   The ad carries a toll-free telephone number that
viewers are asked to call to register their support for Thomas; callers are
then sorted by states, and the state lists will be sent to the targeted
senators.;   (check) On the other side of the Thomas confirmation issue, the
National Abortion Rights Action League reported that senators had begun to
receive the first of 500,000 anti-Thomas post cards the group has provided to
the constituents of targeted lawmakers whose votes against Thomas'
confirmation are regarded as critical.;   (check) The Lawyers' Committee for
Civil Rights Under Law, a bipartisan group organized in 1963 to assist the
government in civil-rights law enforcement, announced that 86 of about 110
members of its board of directors had decided to oppose Thomas' confirmation.
</P>
<P>
The announcement said Thomas' legal philosophy reflected a "hostility to and
rejection of the core of civil rights jurisprudence."  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Washington  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>11
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, September 11, 1991
00255336,SJ1  
</DATELINE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06255421
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  US; COURT; JUDGE; CANDIDATE; SPOUSE; PROBE  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  THOMAS' WIFE ALSO UNDERGOES SCRUTINY  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Virginia Thomas is a soft-spoken, hard-working daughter of the heartland: a
brainy Omaha, Neb., lawyer who has scaled the sheer cliffs of professional
Washington; a churchgoer who invites homeless people out to lunch; a good
friend.;   Why the fuss over Mrs. Supreme Court Nominee?  
</P>
<P>
Her critics see her as more than the supportive spouse who'll accompany her
husband, Clarence, through his Senate confirmation hearings, which began
Tuesday and are likely to run through next week. They see a woman with strong
opinions on issues that are bound to come before the court.;   Some
women's-rights activists are upset by her lobbying against such issues as
comparable-worth legislation. Some religious-rights groups are troubled by her
anti-cult activities in light of her former involvement with Lifespring, a
motivational group.;   Her race draws criticism; Even the color of her skin is
being used to determine the content of Clarence Thomas's character. The fact
that she is white has drawn criticism from some blacks who see the marriage as
evidence that Clarence Thomas has rejected his roots.;   In their respective
careers, the Thomases have embraced the view that women and minorities are
hindered, rather than helped, by affirmative action and government programs.
</P>
<P>
True equality is achieved by holding everyone to the same standard, they
believe.;   Virginia Thomas has represented the conservative viewpoint in her
jobs as a staffer for a Republican congressman, spokeswoman at the U.S.
</P>
<P>
Chamber of Congress and deputy assistant secretary at the Department of
Labor.;   Clarence Thomas advocates a colorblind society, and his marriage may
be an example of that philosophy. But others see a different symbolism.;  
'Sign of rejection'; "His marrying a white woman is a sign of his rejection of
the black community," said Russell Adams, chairman of Howard University's
department of Afro-American studies. "Great justices have had community roots
that served as a basis for understanding the Constitution. Clarence's lack of
a sense of community makes his nomination troubling.";   Some religious
leaders are troubled as well. Dean Kelley, the National Council of Churches'
counselor on religious liberty, wrote a critique of Clarence Thomas that was
used as grounds for his organization's opposition to the Supreme Court
nominee. The author did not mention Virginia Thomas in his text but has said
he was concerned about her involvement in the Cult Awareness Network (CAN), a
Chicago-based organization that says it educates the public about
"destructive" cults. That involvement, he said, might affect her husband's
handling of religious-liberty cases if he shares her views on the subject.;  
During the early '80s, Virginia Thomas enrolled in Lifespring, a self-help
course that challenges students to take responsibility for their lives. She
was troubled by some of the activities and eventually broke with the
organization. Since 1985, she has been a public advocate against cult
activities.;   When she served as a labor-relations attorney at the U.S.
</P>
<P>
Chamber of Commerce from 1985 to 1989, she represented the interests of the
business community at congressional hearings on such issues as comparable
worth, affirmative action and federal child-care legislation.  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Washington  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>11
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, September 11, 1991
00255421,SJ1  
</DATELINE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06255434
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  US; COURT; JUDGE; CANDIDATE; SPOUSE; PROFILE  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  THOMAS' SPOUSE ALSO IN SPOTLIGHT
CRITICS SAY HER VIEWS COULD INFLUENCE CASES  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Virginia Thomas is a soft-spoken, hard-working daughter of the heartland. A
brainy Omaha, Neb., lawyer who has scaled the sheer cliffs of professional
Washington. A churchgoer who invites homeless people out to lunch. A good
friend.;   Why the fuss over Mrs. Supreme Court Nominee?  
</P>
<P>
Her critics see her as more than the supportive spouse who'll accompany her
husband, Clarence, through his Senate confirmation hearings, which began
Tuesday and are likely to run through next week. They see a woman with strong
opinions on issues that are bound to come before the court.;   Some
women's-rights activists are upset by her lobbying against such issues as
comparable-worth legislation. Some religious rights groups are troubled by her
anti-cult activities in light of her former involvement with Lifespring, a
motivational group.;   Skin color an issue; Even the color of her skin is
being used to determine the content of Clarence Thomas's character. The fact
that she is white has drawn criticism from some blacks who see the marriage as
evidence that Clarence Thomas has rejected his roots.;   In their respective
careers, the Thomases have embraced the view that women and minorities are
hindered, rather than helped, by affirmative action and government programs.
</P>
<P>
True equality is achieved by holding everyone to the same standard, they
believe.;   "I don't think it's fair to say she's anti-women's rights," said
Ricky Silberman, vice chairwoman of the EEOC and a friend of the Thomases. She
said Virginia Thomas opposed legislation on comparable worth because it would
have involved the government in determining wages, which is "not good for the
economy, not good for workers, not good for women.";   Conservative viewpoint;
Virginia Thomas has represented the conservative viewpoint in her jobs as a
staffer for a Republican congressman, spokeswoman at the U.S. Chamber of
Congress and deputy assistant secretary at the Department of Labor.;  
Clarence Thomas advocates a colorblind society, and his marriage may be an
example of that philosophy. But others see a different symbolism.;   "His
marrying a white woman is a sign of his rejection of the black community,"
said Russell Adams, chairman of Howard University's department of
Afro-American studies. "Great justices have had community roots that served as
a basis for understanding the Constitution. Clarence's lack of a sense of
community makes his nomination troubling.";   Religious leaders wonder; Some
religious leaders are troubled as well. Dean Kelley, the National Council of
Churches' counselor on religious liberty, wrote a critique of Clarence Thomas
that was used as grounds for his organization's opposition to the Supreme
Court nominee. The author did not mention Virginia Thomas in his text, but has
said he was concerned about her involvement in the Cult Awareness Network
(CAN), a Chicago-based organization that says it educates the public about
"destructive" cults. That involvement, he said, might affect her husband's
handling of religious-liberty cases if he shares her views on the subject.;  
During the early '80s, Virginia Thomas enrolled in Lifespring, a self-help
course that challenges students to take responsibility for their lives. A
small percentage of the program's 300,000 graduates have been deeply disturbed
by Lifespring's methods, which involve intense emotional self-examination.;  
A clean break; Virginia Thomas was troubled by some of Lifespring's activities
and eventually broke with the organization. Since 1985, she has been a public
advocate against cult activities.;   When she served as a labor-relations
attorney at the U.S. Chamber of Commerce from 1985 to 1989, she represented
the interests of the business community at congressional hearings on such
issues as comparable worth, affirmative action and federal child-care
legislation.  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Washington  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>11
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, September 11, 1991
00255434,SJ1  
</DATELINE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06256107
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  US; COURT; JUDGE; CANDIDATE; APPOINTMENT; ABORTION; CONTROVERSY  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  SENATORS DOUBTING THOMAS
ONE CALLS HIM 'ONLY PERSON IN ROOM' WITHOUT
OPINION ON ABORTION  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Frustrated Democrats on the Senate Judiciary Committee say Supreme Court
nominee Clarence Thomas is an evasive witness, but no groundswell of
opposition to his confirmation seems to be emerging.;   Several senators were
openly skeptical Wednesday over Thomas' insistence that he has no opinion on
the 1973 Supreme Court decision legalizing abortion.  
</P>
<P>
If that's so, said Sen. Paul Simon, D-Ill., "he's the only person gathered
in the room who does not have an opinion.";   Sen. Herb Kohl, D-Wis., added,
"I'm concerned about his candor, his willingness to be forthcoming." Kohl was
today's leadoff questioner as the hearings entered their third day.;   Two
pivotal members of the 14-member committee - Howell Heflin, D-Ala., and Arlen
Specter, R-Pa. - also voiced concern about Thomas' answers. But the panel's
traditional third swing vote, Dennis DeConcini, D-Ariz., said Thomas was doing
well.;   Heflin cited the "appearance of a confirmation conversion" and said
it may raise questions of Thomas' "integrity and temperament.";   But Heflin
added, "I am not at this time of any firm opinion one way or the other" on
whether Thomas should be confirmed.;   And Simon said Thomas' performance thus
far "has neither helped him nor hurt him.";   Specter blamed fellow committee
members more than Thomas in concluding, "We really haven't moved very far in
the process.";   Thomas, a black federal appeals judge, was picked by
President Bush to replace the retiring Thurgood Marshall, the high court's
only black justice.;   DeConcini said he thought the conservative Thomas
"handled the privacy questions very well" without taking a stand on abortion.
</P>
<P>
"I don't see how you could ask him to do anything more.";   Thomas expanded
earlier testimony by saying Wednesday that he believed the right of marital
privacy was "fundamental" - a status that accords it the fullest judicial
protection from government intrusion.;   But he repeatedly refused to state
his views on the 1973 abortion decision based on women's right of privacy. To
give such an answer, he said, "would undermine my ability to sit in an
impartial way on such an important case.";   Thomas, who sat alone at the
witness table with no notes or reference materials, also claimed a lack of
familiarity with the subject matter when asked about some of his former
speeches and articles.;   That moved committee Chairman Joseph Biden, D-Del.,
to give Thomas a stack of the judge's past speeches so the nominee could "help
me understand them" during future questioning.;   Thomas, testifying calmly
but warily, did offer fuller comment on another hot issue before the high
court: prayer in public schools.;   After Simon discussed the feelings decades
ago of a Jewish elementary schoolboy who left the room each day while his
classmates recited a prayer, Thomas said, "Any policy of exclusion should be
considered inappropriate.";   Outside the hearing room, abortion-rights
advocates said Thomas should not be allowed to disavow past comments they say
show he would vote to ban most, if not all, abortions.;   "His most
unimpressive testimony poses two equally disturbing possibilities: he is
either willfully misleading the committee about his views to win confirmation,
or he is a man whose convictions have shallow roots," said Arthur Kropp of
People for the American Way.;   Sen. Patrick Leahy, D-Vt., said he could not
understand how Thomas' prior statements touching on the 1973 abortion decision
could have been made without considering its content. "I'm not satisfied with
the answers," Leahy said.;   Although Thomas appeared to back away from
comments made in past speeches or articles, he told the committee, "My view is
that I have been consistent.";   Thomas' opponents believe Republicans Strom
Thurmond of South Carolina, Orrin Hatch of Utah, Charles Grassley of Iowa,
Alan Simpson of Wyoming and Hank Brown of Colorado are solid Thomas backers.; 
But they hope Sens. Edward M. Kennedy, D-Mass., and Howard Metzenbaum,
D-Ohio, will be joined by the three swing-vote senators and Biden, Leahy,
Simon and Kohl in voting against the nominee.;   Biden and Kennedy declined
comment Wednesday on their leanings.;   Metzenbaum said Thomas' refusal to
give direct answers "makes it more difficult to vote for him."; THOMAS' VIEWS;
Excerpts from Clarence Thomas' testimony:; On abortion: "I have no reason or
agenda to prejudge the issue . . . or a predilection to rule one way or
another on the issue of abortion."; On affirmative action: "The line that I
drew was a line that said that we shouldn't have preferences, or goals, or
timetables or quotas."; On natural law: "At no time did I feel, nor do I feel
now, that natural law is anything more than the background to our
Constitution."; HEAR IT, SEE IT; Senate confirmation hearings for Supreme
Court nominee Clarence Thomas are scheduled to run through Friday this week
and every weekday except Wednesday next week.; RADIO; (box) KQED, 88.5 FM Tape
delay beginning at 9 a.m.; repeated at 9:30 p.m.; (box) KPFA, 94.1 FM Live
coverage begins at 6:30 a.m.; TELEVISION; (box) C-SPAN Live coverage begins at
7 a.m.; repeated at 5 p.m.; (box) CNN Intermittent coverage.  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Washington  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>12
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, September 12, 1991
00256107,SJ1  
</DATELINE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06256124
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  US; COURT; JUDGE; CANDIDATE; APPOINTMENT; ABORTION; CONTROVERSY  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  SENATORS DOUBTING THOMAS
COURT NOMINEE SAYS HIS PERSONAL OPINION OF
ABORTION IS 'IRRELEVANT'  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Supreme Court nominee Clarence Thomas told the Senate Judiciary Committee
today it is "irrelevant" whether he holds any personal opinion on abortion,
spurring new frustration among the committee's Democrats.;   But as the
hearings' third day got under way, no groundswell of opposition to his
confirmation seemed to be emerging.  
</P>
<P>
Asked several times by Sen. Herb Kohl, D-Wis., about women's right to end
their pregnancies, Thomas said, "Whether or not I have a view is irrelevant.";
President Bush, asked at a news conference whether Thomas' claim not to have
an opinion on abortion is credible, answered, "That's a question for the
Senate to decide.";   "He's handling himself very well," the president said.
</P>
<P>
"I think he's doing a beautiful job up there. I feel more confident than ever
that he will be confirmed.";   Thomas' answers have frustrated the committee's
Democrats, who say he is an evasive witness. They also have voiced skepticism
about his backing away from stands he took in past writings and speeches.;  
Committee Chairman Joseph Biden, D-Del., began to show signs of exasperation
today during spirited questioning about the nominee's views on "natural law,"
a theory that certain rights exist independent of written law.;   At one
point, Biden accused Thomas of using "tortuous logic." Later, he referred to
one of Thomas' replies as "the most unartful dodge I've heard." After still
another Thomas answer, Biden said, "That's not the question I asked you,
judge.";   Republicans tried to deflect criticism over Thomas' refusal to
answer questions from the Democrats.;   "It is, in my view, inappropriate to
keep this up," said Sen. Orrin Hatch, R-Utah. He said Thomas had been asked
more than 70 questions about his abortion views even though Justice David H.
</P>
<P>
Souter was asked only 36 such questions during his confirmation hearings last
year.;   "What are we going to have? Sixty-four-thousand questions on abortion
before we're done with this approach?" Hatch asked. "Enough is enough.";  
Thomas said Senate confirmation of his nomination would give him "an
opportunity to serve and give back" and to "bring something different to the
court.";   "I can walk in the shoes of the people who are affected by what the
court does," Thomas said.;   Several senators were openly skeptical Wednesday
over Thomas' insistence that he has no opinion on the 1973 Supreme Court
decision legalizing abortion.;   If that's so, said Sen. Paul Simon, D-Ill.,
"he's the only person gathered in the room who does not have an opinion.";  
Kohl added, "I'm concerned about his candor, his willingness to be
forthcoming.";   Today, Kohl asked the nominee, "Is it fair of you to say to
us, for the most part, just view me on what I'm saying here this week?";  
Kohl asked the black federal judge whether he was offended by published
comments calling his appointment by President Bush a "quota.";   "That would
trouble anyone," Thomas said, adding, "I don't think it's accurate." He said
Bush assured him he was picked because he was the best qualified of those
potential nominees considered.;   Thomas is expected to continue testifying
through Friday. The committee next week will hear from other witnesses.;   Two
pivotal members of the 14-member committee - Howell Heflin, D-Ala., and Arlen
Specter, R-Pa. - also voiced concern about Thomas' answers. But the panel's
traditional third swing vote, Dennis DeConcini, D-Ariz., said Thomas was doing
well.;   Thomas' opponents believe Republicans Strom Thurmond of South
Carolina, Hatch, Charles Grassley of Iowa, Alan Simpson of Wyoming and Hank
Brown of Colorado are solid Thomas backers.;   But they hope Sens. Edward M.
</P>
<P>
Kennedy, D-Mass., and Howard Metzenbaum, D-Ohio, will be joined by the three
swing-vote senators and Biden, Patrick Leahy of Vermont, Simon and Kohl in
voting against the nominee.; THOMAS' VIEWS; Excerpts from Clarence Thomas'
testimony:; On abortion: "I have no reason or agenda to prejudge the issue . .
. or a predilection to rule one way or another on the issue of abortion."; On
affirmative action: "The line that I drew was a line that said that we
shouldn't have preferences, or goals, or timetables or quotas."; On natural
law: "At no time did I feel, nor do I feel now, that natural law is anything
more than the background to our Constitution."; HEAR IT, SEE IT; Senate
confirmation hearings for Supreme Court nominee Clarence Thomas are scheduled
to run through Friday this week and every weekday except Wednesday next week.;
RADIO; (box) KQED, 88.5 FM Tape delay beginning at 9 a.m.; repeated at 9:30
p.m.; (box) KPFA, 94.1 FM Live coverage begins at 6:30 a.m.; TELEVISION; (box)
C-SPAN Live coverage begins at 7 a.m.; repeated at 5 p.m.; (box) CNN
Intermittent coverage.  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Washington  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>12
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, September 12, 1991
00256124,SJ1  
</DATELINE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06261053
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  US; CONGRESS; COURT; JUDGE; APPOINTMENT; PROBE  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  SENATE QUESTIONING OF THOMAS ENDS
BUSH NOMINEE APPEARS HEADED FOR HIGH COURT  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Clarence Thomas completed five grueling days of Senate questioning Monday,
apparently well on his way to becoming the second black justice in the history
of the Supreme Court.;   "I have been honored to participate in this process,"
Thomas said before breaking into a broad grin and effusively gripping the
hands of his Judiciary Committee interrogators.  
</P>
<P>
The committee will continue to hear testimony for and against Thomas at
least through the end of the week, but the outcome does not seem to be in
doubt. Several committee members said they expected the committee to
recommend, by a 10-4 or 9-5 vote, that the Senate confirm Thomas. Regardless
of the outcome, Thomas said on his way out of the hearing, "I have been
treated fairly.";   Before Thomas' testimony ended, the unflappable
43-year-old federal judge was criticized, sometimes in harsh terms, by several
liberal Democrats. They accused him of being evasive and of disavowing many
controversial statements he made while an official of the Reagan and Bush
administrations.;   Thomas repeatedly explained that he made the speeches as
an advocate for administration policy, acknowledging that they often contained
overheated rhetoric.;   Sen. Howard Metzenbaum, D-Ohio, said he found it
"difficult to accept the notion that the moment you put on a judge's robe all
the views and positions which you held prior to going on the bench just
magically disappear.";   "I want to look into the window of your soul,"
Patrick Leahy, D-Vt., said to Thomas. "but I find the shade down quite a
bit.";   Sen. Edward Kennedy, D-Mass., delivered a long, stinging lecture to
Thomas, declaring: "The vanishing views of Judge Thomas have become a major
issue in these hearings.";   Kennedy listed 10 instances in which he said
Thomas had abandoned or contradicted his previous positions.;   Kennedy told
Thomas he had "walked away" from his record on the right to privacy, refused
to comment on its application to abortion and asked lawmakers "to believe that
an intelligent and outspoken person like yourself has never discussed Roe vs.
</P>
<P>
Wade (the landmark 1973 abortion-rights ruling) with another human being.";  
Moderate Republican Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, who often casts a swing
vote on the committee, said he was not troubled by Thomas' shift toward more
moderate views at the hearings.;   "I believe he's going to be a surprising
justice. I don't think you can pigeonhole this man," Specter said.;   If
Thomas is confirmed as expected, he made it clear that, for the first time in
decades, there would be not one justice on the Supreme Court who is convinced
that capital punishment is unconstitutionally cruel.;   Justice Thurgood
Marshall, whom Thomas would replace, was the last member of the court who
opposed the death penalty in all cases. Thomas told the Judiciary Committee
that "philosophically, there is nothing that would bother me personally about
upholding it (the death penalty) in appropriate cases.";   After Thomas left
the hearing room, an American Bar Association evaluation committee told the
senators that his articles in law journals were deficient in presentation,
content, scholarship and analysis.;   But those limitations were outweighed by
his "brief but highly satisfactory performance on the Court of Appeals," the
committee said, noting that "we found only one opinion to criticize and many
to praise."  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Washington  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>17
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, September 17, 1991
00261053,SJ1  
</DATELINE>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
