<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891106-0072
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>06
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Thatcher Says She'll Step Down After Next Election
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher has weakened her
position and kicked off the race to succeed her by saying she plans
to step down after winning another term, opposition leaders and
political observers said.
</P>
<P>
A pro-Thatcher newspaper today said she had merely stated the
obvious and that her statements were no ``cause for astonishment.''
Mrs. Thatcher told The Sunday Correspondent in an interview
published Sunday that she hoped to lead her Conservative Party to a
fourth successive election but said it was unlikely she would try
for a fifth.
``I think people would think it was time for someone else to
carry the torch,'' she told the newspaper.
</P>
<P>
The Sunday Times of London said in a commentary: ``Mrs. Thatcher
has committed a colossal blunder.''
``She has given the riders for the Tory succession their
starting orders years in advance of the actual race,'' the
newspaper said.
</P>
<P>
The next election must be held by the summer of 1992, but it is
expected Mrs. Thatcher will call it in 1991.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Thatcher, who turned 64 last month, has never previously
made it clear in public when she plans to retire as party leader.
</P>
<P>
She was elected in 1979, the first female prime minister in Europe,
and won re-election in 1983 and in 1987, when she said she planned
to ``go on and on.''
Earlier this year, Mrs. Thatcher overtook Liberal Lord Asquith's
1908-1916 tenure as prime minister to become Britain's longest
continuously serving prime minister of the 20th century.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Thatcher's popularity is the lowest of any prime minister
since opinion polls began in Britain 50 years ago, and senior
colleagues have publicly admonished her to change her leadership
style following the surprise resignation of her treasury chief,
Nigel Lawson.
</P>
<P>
Lord Callaghan, former Labor prime minister whom Mrs. Thatcher
defeated in 1979, said her comments had ``considerably weakened her
position.''
If her party wins the next election, it is expected Mrs.
</P>
<P>
Thatcher would step down before her term ends to allow her
successor to choose a time to call a new election.
``My guess is that the Tory party will want someone as leader
who could take them through the next Parliament,'' Callaghan said.
</P>
<P>
If Mrs. Thatcher resigns while in office, her successor elected
by the party automatically becomes prime minister with approval of
Queen Elizabeth II, but convention dictates that he or she seek a
mandate in a general election as soon as possible.
</P>
<P>
The Sunday Times speculated she would step down by 1994. Mrs.
</P>
<P>
Thatcher would celebrate her 69th birthday that year and her
husband, Denis, will be 79 and ``his age may have been a factor in
her decision,'' the newspaper said.
</P>
<P>
The newspaper predicted the opposition Labor Party will try to
promote leader Neil Kinnock as ``the occupant-in-waiting of 10
Downing St., who is ready, able and willing to complete a full
term.''
Kinnock called Mrs. Thatcher's comments ``the interview of
someone preparing herself for quitting. Mentally, Margaret Thatcher
is preparing herself for packing her bags.''
In an editorial today, the pro-Thatcher Daily Telegraph said
Mrs. Thatcher was merely stating the obvious by indicating she
would not seek a fifth term.
``Even were she not to fight a fifth election, Mrs. Thatcher
could yet enjoy seven more years in charge,'' it said.
``By then she would be in her 70s, and her devoted husband a
decade older ... Nonetheless, what other politician would be
expected to entertain an inquiry about his or her intentions in
seven years time? And can it really be a cause for astonishment
that Mrs. Thatcher is unwilling to commit herself to political
activity in her mid-70s and beyond?''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP901122-0100
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Foreign Leaders Pay Tribute To Mrs. Thatcher's Courage
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Britain-Politics, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's international
admirers praised her courage and achievements Thursday after she
announced she would resign. Even her foes tempered scorn with
praise for a formidable adversary.
</P>
<P>
Said President Bush, ``I will miss her.''
He called her ``an outstanding ally of the United States,''
adding, ``You always knew where she was and what she believed.''
Vitaly Ignatenko, spokesman for Soviet President Mikhail
Gorbachev, told the independent Interfax news agency: ``Political,
economic and cultural ties between our countries have become of
greater importance'' in the Thatcher era. ``Our relations ... were
marked by constructivism and dialogue.''
The reluctance Mrs. Thatcher showed toward increasing European
unity was the source of most criticism. But in a joyful and
unambiguous response, Iraq saw the Persian Gulf crisis as cause of
her downfall.
</P>
<P>
Bitterness was undisguised in the comment from Argentina's
Nicanor Costa Mendez, foreign minister during his country's 1982
Falklands War with Britain.
``I can't say that it makes me sad,'' he said. ``I believe that
the extreme positions - unnecessarily extreme, unjustifiably
extreme - of the prime minister were one of the causes of the war,
and one of the biggest impediments to achieve agreement after.''
Socialist President Mario Soares of Portugal singled out ``her
systematic opposition to the advances of the European Community.''
``During her long mandate,'' he said, ``the preoccupations of
social justice receded many times before purely development
objectives, causing a climate of discontent in British public
opinion to which Mrs. Thatcher appeared insensitive.''
But Soares also lauded the British prime minister as a
``determined politician (who) took courageous positions on critical
occasions in international life and without doubt marked an era in
the contemporary history of her country.''
German Finance Minister Theo Waigel noted, ``Despite her
critical position on some questions of European integration, she
accomplished a great deal for European politics.''
A neutral letter from Socialist President Francois Mitterrand of
France told Mrs. Thatcher she had ``marked an important moment in
the history of your country and that of Europe.''
Iraqi government spokesman Naji al-Hadithi said growing
opposition to her hard line against Iraq over its invasion of
Kuwait ``buried Mrs. Thatcher'' just as the 1956 crisis over
Britain's attack on the Suez Canal ruined former Prime Minister
Anthony Eden.
</P>
<P>
Britain stepped in after Egypt nationalized the canal.
</P>
<P>
On Thursday, Britain announced it was nearly doubling its troops
deployed in the gulf as part of the multinational force arrayed
against Iraq, sending 14,000 more soldiers to join the 16,000
already in the region.
</P>
<P>
South African President F.W. de Klerk praised Mrs. Thatcher, who
opposed sanctions on South Africa, for standing up to world
pressure and standing by Pretoria.
``She had faith in South Africa's ability to solve its problems
in a democratic way ... She had the courage of her convictions,''
he said.
</P>
<P>
Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir of Israel saidafter hearing of
her resignation that Israel ``feels a moment of sorrow because we
all know this special personality, Mrs. Thatcher, who did many
things and was an outstanding leader.''
Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu of Japan said the British prime
minister ``is a rare leader of firm convictions who was invigorated
the United Kingdom and I feel great regret that she has withdrawn
from the front line.''
Belgium's prime minister, Wilfried Martens, applauded ``the
determining role she played during more than 10 years in her own
country and on the international scene.''
Said Prime Minister Bob Hawke of Australia, ``Even those like
myself who have been at odds with Margaret Thatcher on particular
issues have admired her courage and tenacity of purpose.
``Whatever the forces arrayed against her, she was always
prepared to pursue with the utmost vigor those positions in which
she believed.''
Dutch Prime Minister Ruud Lubbers said, ``In the many years that
she placed such an important stamp on the policies of the United
Kingdom, Mrs. Thatcher has shown that she does not avoid making
difficult decisions that she deems to be in the nation's interest.
</P>
<P>
This, too, is such a decision which deserves respect.''
Former French President Valery Giscard d'Estaing, now a
legislator in the European Parliament, said Mrs. Thatcher's
decision to quit was ``dignified and courageous.''
``Margaret Thatcher will be seen with Winston Churchill as the
greatest British prime minister of the last 50 years. The curtain
has fallen on the Iron Lady. She deserves our congratulations.''
Even European Commission President Jacques Delors, Mrs.
</P>
<P>
Thatcher's archenemy in Europe, spoke of his ``high esteem'' for
her, despite their differences.
</P>
<P>
Alfred Dregger, parliamentary leader of Germany's governing
Christian Democratic Union, said Mrs. Thatcher played a major role
in securing Western solidarity in the ``historical conflict for
freedom and democracy. We thank her for that.''
Former President Reagan spoke with great warmth of his closest
foreign ally.
``Margaret Thatcher's resoluteness played a key role in ending
the Cold War,'' he said. ``She stood up to the Soviets and let them
know she meant business. Her deep and abiding dedication to the
principles of liberty and democracy served as an inspiration to
oppressed peoples everywhere who knew that Margaret Thatcher would
never waver in her belief that all men and women are entitled to
live in freedom.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP901123-0002
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With Thatcher's Demise, US Loses Its Staunchest Ally
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
An AP News Analysis
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
For almost a decade, Margaret Thatcher was
regarded at the White House as America's best friend, the trusted
ally whose strong views reinforced the conservative tone of
administration policies.
</P>
<P>
Among Western allies, she was alone at Ronald Reagan's side in
1986 in supporting the U.S. bombing of Libya. In the Persian Gulf
crisis, she boldly joined with George Bush in sending troops to the
Middle East.
``You always know where she was and what she believed,'' Bush
said upon hearing of her decision to resign. ``She has always been
an outstanding ally of the United States,'' he said. ``I will miss
her.''
There were many doubters around the world when Reagan arrived in
Washington with an economic program of free-market capitalism that
seemed out of step with the times. Mrs. Thatcher wasn't one of the
skeptics; she was advocating a similar program at home.
</P>
<P>
They shared rocky relations with organized labor. Reagan
successfully fired the nation's air traffic controllers, dealing a
devastating blow to labor. She, too, smashed restive unions.
</P>
<P>
On foreign policy, she frequently was more right wing than
Reagan - certainly more so than Bush.
</P>
<P>
Reagan never made any secret of his special affection for the
British prime minister. They were ideological soulmates and called
each other Ronnie and Margaret. At international gatherings, they
usually were side by side.
</P>
<P>
Two years ago as they met for the final time before Reagan left
office, the president said he was leaving the White House with
``considerable satisfaction in the knowledge that Margaret Thatcher
will still reside at No. 10 Downing Street.''
She later wrote him a ``Dear Ron'' letter in which she praised
him as ``a great president, one of the greatest.''
Like Reagan, she was deeply suspicious of the Soviet Union.
</P>
<P>
Together they advocated a hard line toward Moscow and championed
military readiness - even though she was the first to recognize
Mikhail S. Gorbachev as a leader she could do business with.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Thatcher encouraged the huge Pentagon buildup that Reagan
nurtured under the theme of peace through strength. She was a big
backer of U.S. efforts to install medium-range missiles in Europe
and always seemed cautious - perhaps reluctant - when it came to
disarmament.
</P>
<P>
When Argentina and Britain clashed militarily over the Falkland
Islands, the United States was forced to make a painful choice
between two allies. Ronnie sided with Margaret.
</P>
<P>
Washington's special relationship with London seemed to slip
when Reagan left power. Bush and Mrs. Thatcher disagreed publicly
last year over her government's decision to deport Vietnamese and
Cambodian ``boat people'' who were fleeing their countries to Hong
Kong.
</P>
<P>
Bush, a veteran of world politics, knew many leaders around the
globe. Mrs. Thatcher suddenly seemed to be just one of the gang.
</P>
<P>
The Berlin Wall was collapsing and it appeared as if Bush found
German Chancellor Helmut Kohl more interesting than Mrs. Thatcher.
</P>
<P>
She was merely one in a parade of foreign dignitaries who got the
prized invitation to visit Bush at Camp David this year.
</P>
<P>
Nevertheless, Bush said he expected the ``special relationship''
between the United States and Great Britain to remain on a ``steady
keel.''
Mrs. Thatcher did her part, demonstrating her loyalty. For
awhile she and Bush were seemingly alone in their suspicions of
Gorbachev's unilateral cutbacks in troops and arms in Europe, and
appeared uncertain how to respond.
</P>
<P>
Under intense pressure from Congress, Bush began to warm to the
Soviet leader. Now they seem almost best of friends.
</P>
<P>
On the Persian Gulf, Bush said he would not rule out possible
military force, and ordered a huge buildup of troops to make his
threat credible. Mrs. Thatcher, characteristically, was tougher.
</P>
<P>
She said that unless Saddam Hussein got out of Kuwait soon, the
West would have to use military force to dislodge him.
</P>
<P>
She called Saddam ``a loser,'' and the state-controlled Iraqi
news agency replied that she was an ``old hag.''
Now, she is leaving. No one suspects that Britain's new
leadership - whoever it is - will take a soft line toward Iraq.
</P>
<P>
Yet, if the going gets tough, it might have been comforting for
Bush to be able to hear the tough old line from Thatcher.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP901123-0062
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Reagan Heaps Praise on Thatcher as She Heads Off Into Political
Sunset
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Britain Politics, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Former President Reagan thanked British Prime
Minister Margaret Thatcher for backing him up when other allies
backed down, heaping praise on his political soulmate as she heads
off into the sunset.
``Margaret Thatcher was a completely reliable ally and partner
of the greatest personal integrity,'' Reagan said in a statement
after Mrs. Thatcher announced her impending retirement.
``I could always count on her wise counsel, her firm support,
and her loyal friendship,'' Reagan said.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Thatcher on Thursday succumbed to the challenge mounted by
Michael Heseltine, who resigned as her defense minister in 1986.
</P>
<P>
Reagan and the prime minister dubbed the Iron Lady formed a
formidable duo in the 1980s and made no secret of their mutual
regard. They often stood side-by-side at international gatherings
and called each other Ronnie and Margaret.
</P>
<P>
Two years ago, as they met for the final time before Reagan left
office, the president said he was leaving the White House with
``considerable satisfaction in the knowledge that Margaret Thatcher
will still reside at No. 10 Downing Street.''
Reagan, who spent Thanksgiving with friends at his Bel-Air home,
called her resignation in the face of strong opposition a
``selfless and courageous decision in what she believes is the best
interests of her country.''
The former chief executive was always grateful to Mrs.
</P>
<P>
Thatcher's support of his conservative approach to foreign affairs
during his own eight-year tenure.
</P>
<P>
In 1986, when the U.S. bombing of Libya was criticized by world
powers, Mrs. Thatcher was the only ally who supported Reagan and
allowed the bombers to fly from British bases.
</P>
<P>
When Britain fought Argentina for the Falkland Islands, the
United States was forced to choose between two allies. Reagan sided
with Mrs. Thatcher.
</P>
<P>
She also encouraged Reagan's nurturing of the huge Pentagon
buildup, and backed U.S. efforts to install medium-range missiles
in Europe, despite opposition from NATO allies.
</P>
<P>
Both leaders adopted a hard line toward the Soviet Union, but
were quick to warm up to Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev as
the Cold War thawed.
</P>
<P>
Reagan credited Mrs. Thatcher's ``resoluteness'' for playing a
key role in ending the tensions between the Western democracies and
the Eastern Block.
``She stood up to the Soviets and let them know she meant
business,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Both were ardent advocates of the free market and private
enterprise.
</P>
<P>
While the United States became mired in debt in the era of
Reaganomics, the British economy thrived on Mrs. Thatcher's radical
policies during her nearly 12-year rule. Average earnings were up
by nearly one-third and more Britons owned their homes during her
tenor.
</P>
<P>
Like Reagan, however, Mrs. Thatcher was accused by liberals of
widening the gap between the rich and poor in her country, and both
clashed with organized labor.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP901126-0053
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
British Women Say Thatcher Set Good Example But Little Else
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Margaret Thatcher set the example of what a woman
could achieve in British society, but her critics say she did
little else to help women along.
</P>
<P>
For some, it was enough that her political career reached the
heights.
</P>
<P>
One woman wrote to The Independent newspaper last week that her
7-year-old daughter wondered what title Mrs. Thatcher's successor
would hold, since ``he couldn't be called prime minister, that's a
girl's name.''
Emma Nicholson, a Conservative Party lawmaker, said it was once
unthinkable that a woman would ever be a British prime minister.
``She has broken the mold once and forever,'' Ms. Nicholson said in
an interview.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Thatcher, who trained as a chemist before studying law,
said she viewed herself as prime minister, not as a woman. She
believed the battle for women's rights had been largely won and was
no believer in feminism.
``What has it ever done for me?'' she once asked.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Thatcher, who stepped down on Thursday, urged women to get
involved in politics, but did little to pull them up the ladder.
</P>
<P>
Several female lawmakers were appointed to junior executive
posts in various ministries, but the only woman to serve in a
Thatcher Cabinet was Baroness Young, leader of the House of Lords
from 1981 to 1983.
``The truth is that although Mrs. Thatcher is a woman, she
doesn't believe in the advancement of women,'' Clare Short, a Labor
Party lawmaker, said last month.
</P>
<P>
Edwina Currie, a former junior health minister, said any other
prime minister would have had several women in and out of the
Cabinet.
``It's Margaret's fault that the only people standing (to
succeed her) wear trousers,'' Mrs. Currie said last week. Trree men
are vying to succeed her as Conservative Party leader and thus
prime minister in a vote by party lawmakers set for Tuesday.
</P>
<P>
Traditional male attitudes remain strong in Britain, from the
upper-crust, all-male clubs of London to the topless women pictured
daily in the tabloid press.
</P>
<P>
Women are paid less than men and are poorly represented in
management jobs and in Parliament.
</P>
<P>
However, campaigners for women rights say there are encouraging
signs at the grassroots.
``The critical mass of women have entered middle management in
government and business,'' said Lesley Abdela, a founding member of
the 300 Group.
</P>
<P>
The group seeks equal representation for women in the 650-seat
House of Commons, which now has 43 female members.
</P>
<P>
Women represented 43 percent of the British labor force in 1988,
compared with 40 percent in 1979 when Mrs. Thatcher became prime
minister. Britain has a higher proportion of working women than
other European Community countries.
</P>
<P>
Though Mrs. Thatcher never made a priority of women's issues,
she did introduce some helpful legislation: tax concessions for
workplace nurseries; independent taxation for married women; and
legislation to compel absent fathers to pay child benefits.
</P>
<P>
But as prime minister, she angered feminists by often
emphasizing women's traditional roles of homemakers and
care-givers.
</P>
<P>
Angela Rumbold, the Conservative Party's minister for women's
issues, contends that an ``enormous amount'' has been done for
women during the Thatcher years.
``I'm not sure what she could have gone beyond promoting people
who were there just because they were women,'' she said in an
interview. ``Margaret Thatcher is a great meritocrat. She believes
in getting people to succeed on their merits.''
Jo Hawkins of the 300 Group, which is seeking equal numbers of
women in the House of Commons, believes Mrs. Thatcher's
extraordinary abilities made it difficult for her to understand the
needs of the average woman.
``She would say that anybody can do it, just stick to your
principles and get up and do it,'' Ms. Hawkins said. ``I think
because of her character, her personality and her amazing
self-confidence, she isn't aware of how the normal person
struggles.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA040689-0198
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>6
</DAY> 
<MONTH>4
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
GORBACHEV, THATCHER TALK 4 HOURS; 
SESSION COVERS WIDE RANGE OF SUBJECTS; THEY 'LOVE TO ARGUE' 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
LONDON 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher 
today argued passionately during a four-hour meeting that covered subjects 
ranging from disarmament to reports of Soviet bomber sales to Libya, officials 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Reopening a European peace offensive that was disrupted by the Armenian 
earthquake, Gorbachev had "extremely frank exchanges, animated, warm, 
passionate and solemn," said a Thatcher spokesman, requesting anonymity. 
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev also hit the streets of London, stopping his motorcade to shake hands 
with about 20 people in a crowd of several hundred who cheered him outside 
Westminster Abbey. 
</P>
<P>
The Thatcher spokesman said the Soviet leader and the staunchly anti-Communist 
prime minister "love arguing." 
</P>
<P>
Emerging from her 10 Downing St. residence into the icy rain with Gorbachev at 
her side, Thatcher told reporters: 
</P>
<P>
"The talks have been very deep, very wide ranging and very friendly, and as 
always we got to grips with the real issues." 
</P>
<P>
The spokesman said Thatcher asked Gorbachev about a report from Washington that 
Moscow sold up to 15 long-range fighter-bombers to Libya, which Britain accuses 
of sponsoring terrorism. Gorbachev did not respond, he said. 
</P>
<P>
Although the two leaders could make no progress on the bomber issue, the 
spokesman said the Soviet and British foreign ministers, meeting separately, 
would most likely discuss the matter at length. 
</P>
<P>
He said Thatcher also accused the Soviets of having been "not as frank as they 
should be" about their chemical weapons arsenal. 
</P>
<P>
He quoted Gorbachev as replying: "If you aren't fully satisfied, then quite 
clearly we have to have more exchanges. We have got to try better to convince 
each other." 
</P>
<P>
Another area of disagreement was Gorbachev's goal of eliminating all nuclear 
weapons from Europe. Thatcher believes the deterrence of nuclear weapons 
prevents war. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA112090-0165
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>20
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
THE PRESS; 
TORIES' TORMENT: WHAT TO DO WITH THATCHER? 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Flamboyant former Defense Minister Michael Heseltine's challenge to Prime 
Minister Margaret Thatcher for leadership of the Conservative Party has caused 
a political sensation in Britain. A crucial first vote of Tory Members of 
Parliament (MPs) is scheduled for today, and if Heseltine should wrest control 
of the party from Thatcher - the longest-serving British head of government in 
modern times - she would also have to give up the prime minister's job that 
she has held since 1979. 
</P>
<P>
 Here's a sampling of editorial comment on the contest that has stirred 
Britain: 
</P>
<P>
 "The Thatcher era in British politics is almost over. . . . It is more likely 
than not that she is finished altogether. The coup de grace may not be 
delivered at this moment. The nature of the era that comes afterward is far 
from clear. But as a political force, she is condemned at best to an 
unrelenting rear-guard action which will end sometime in a humiliating abyss. . 
. . 
</P>
<P>
"The party may sullenly support her now, but they will ask the question again 
in the spring, knowing that if they do not do so the country will ask the same 
question even more pitilessly when the general election comes. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"An alternative, however, stares her in the face. . . . It is to acknowledge 
that an era has passed, and preserve its achievements by standing down, 
releasing her lieutenants and urging her party, in the interests of a vanished 
unity, to support Mr. (Foreign Minister Douglas) Hurd." 
</P>
<P>
 - Thatcher biographer Hugo Young in The Guardian 
</P>
<P>
"The contest for the leadership of the Conservative party . . . should not be 
occurring. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"It would be foolish to deny that, today, the prime minister is politically 
beleaguered as never before. . . . But the task of the Conservative party, in 
the year and more that remains before the next general election, must be to 
rally to enable Mrs. Thatcher to rebuild her personal position, and give her 
the confidence and support to win the fourth term she deserves." 
</P>
<P>
 - The Daily Telegraph 
</P>
<P>
"Who could have guessed . . . from watching the prime minister answer questions 
in the Commons that she was fighting for her life? She was as brisk and 
well-briefed as ever. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"Bloodied Margaret Thatcher may be. Bowed she most certainly is not." 
</P>
<P>
 - Daily Mail 
</P>
<P>
"British Conservative MPs must be prepared to reject Mrs. Thatcher when they 
vote in the party's leadership election. . . . It is no longer in the interests 
of the United Kingdom, which are now inextricably linked with the development 
of a strong and united Europe, for her to remain in office. 
</P>
<P>
"The European derives no satisfaction from reaching this conclusion. Apart from 
her domestic achievements in reviving the British economy in the 1980s, Mrs. 
Thatcher has contributed much more to the development of the European Community 
than she is often given credit for. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"But The European believes that her nightmare vision of Europe, of 
ill-intentioned people trying to destroy democracy, is not shared by most of 
the British people. They reject her view that pooling of sovereignty is no 
different from surrender. . . . 
</P>
<P>
 "The Conservative Party faces a stark choice. Either it will reelect Mrs. 
Thatcher and see the United Kingdom slip into isolation as it is left behind 
the rest of the Community. Or it can choose a new leader who is prepared to 
participate genuinely in the argument about economic and political union." 
</P>
<P>
 - The European 
</P>
<P>
 "A prime minister in total command for 11 years could not be unseated, and 
cherished policies abandoned, without an explosion within the party. It would 
take a Solomon to heal the divisions and prevent civil war. Frankly, we cannot 
see Mr. Heseltine in that role. 
</P>
<P>
"The Sun also deeply questions his ability to be a successful or even adequate 
prime minister. . . . This is the man who for the past five years has professed 
loyalty to the government and yet has been its most divisive force. We discern 
just one constant loyalty - and that is to Michael Heseltine." 
</P>
<P>
 - The Sun 
</P>
<P>
"Mrs. Thatcher deserves better than to be dismissed in the shoddy and demeaning 
manner some Tory MPs are minded to have in store for her. To be defeated by the 
people in a general election, as was Winston Churchill in 1945, that was an 
honorable rejection. To be brought down by a vote of censure in the House of 
Commons, as was Neville Chamberlain in 1940 - even that was a constitutionally 
respectable form of political demise. But what they are proposing to do to Mrs. 
Thatcher, unquestionably the greatest peacetime prime minister of this century, 
is quite simply unworthy. Her fate could be sealed, if her opponents have their 
way, behind closed doors in smoke-filled rooms. . . . Persons of quality were 
always accorded the dignity of execution by ax or firing squad, rather than the 
humiliation of hanging. These plotters would like to dispatch Mrs. Thatcher, 
who almost single-handedly has won three elections, by the political equivalent 
of the rope. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"You can find Heseltines wherever you go. But there is only one Mrs. Thatcher. 
Handle with care. This valuable object is irreplaceable." 
</P>
<P>
 - The Sunday Telegraph 
</P>
<P>
"This newspaper has long maintained that the best result in the next general 
election would be for Margaret Thatcher to lead the Tories to a fourth victory. 
Sadly, the course of events has conspired to make that unlikely. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"The British have never liked Margaret Thatcher; but as long as she delivered 
the goods they respected her, and voted for her. When her government fails (as 
it has recently), that lack of affection turns to growing resentment. For 
reasons that are probably unfair and undeserved, Mrs. Thatcher is now a victim 
of that strongest public mood of all: time for a change. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"Mrs. Thatcher is right to feel bitter that a prime minister with her track 
record and prestige can be so easily challenged. If she goes, the manner of her 
ousting will leave much to be desired; no other party could so lightly dispose 
of its leader in government, this side of an election, largely for reasons of 
unpopularity. But the Tories have a nose for survival in power unmatched by any 
other party in the democratic world, and politics is an unforgiving business. 
The issue before Tory MPs . . . is not the reelection of Margaret Thatcher, it 
is the defeat of (opposition Labor Party leader) Neil Kinnock. That requires 
saying a reluctant goodby to Mrs. Thatcher, and the endorsement of Michael 
Heseltine." 
</P>
<P>
 - The Sunday Times 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
NEWSPAPERS - ENGLAND; ENGLAND - POLITICS; THATCHER, MARGARET; HESELTINE, 
MICHAEL; CONSERVATIVE PARTY (ENGLAND); LEADERSHIP 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA112190-0001
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>21
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
THERE'LL ALWAYS BE AN ENGLAND; 
BUT MARGARET THATCHER WON'T ALWAYS BE PRIME MINISTER 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Embattled Margaret Thatcher remains leader of Britain's Conservative Party, and 
so the country's prime minister - but only barely. She has survived a vote of 
confidence taken by her party colleagues in the House of Commons, winning 204 
votes against 152 for former defense minister Michael Heseltine. But under Tory 
party rules, that margin, representing something less than a ringing 
endorsement, forces Thatcher to face a second round of voting on Tuesday. Other 
candidates could choose to stand against her, perhaps diluting the opposition 
vote and letting her claim the simple majority she needs to stay as party head. 
But her reelection is hardly assured. 
</P>
<P>
Polls show the Tories would do better in the next national elections with 
someone other than Thatcher leading them. But elections don't have to be called 
until mid-1992; Thatcher's public standing could conceivably increase by then. 
Thatcher has served as PM longer than anyone in this century. She led her party 
to victory in three elections, steered it through the war with Argentina to 
reclaim the Falklands, faced down the miners union in a long strike, moved - 
often drastically - to reverse Britain's economic decline and won a prominent 
place on the world stage. 
</P>
<P>
But 11 1/2 years in office is a long time. Memory and feelings being what they 
are, it is the mistakes and irritations of this long tenure that are more 
likely to be immediately recalled, while its achievements are left to history 
to salute. Thatcher is seen as having become increasingly autocratic at home 
and a somewhat tiresome scold within the European Community. Her government is 
deeply identified with high interest rates, inflation and a flat tax on every 
adult (in place of the property tax) that is generally regarded as hugely 
unfair. Ultimately, in the cold calculus of politics, the question that will 
most decisively sway Conservative MPs is whether they are more likely to win 
the next election with Thatcher at their head or someone else. Next week will 
bring the answer. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA112390-0008
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
THE ROMANCE IS OVER; THE ANGLO PARTNERSHIP PALES; 
THATCHER: SHE WAS A SYMBIOTIC ALLY TO REAGAN AND THEN BUSH; SHE SIMPLY LOST HER 
OWN PARTY'S ALLEGIANCE. 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
President Bush lost an irreplaceable pin supporting his mission in the Persian 
Gulf on Thanksgiving Day. He heard the news of Margaret Thatcher's resignation 
as he celebrated the holiday in the Saudi desert - and it clearly came as a 
shock. In the State Department, too, it came as a shock. Americans who had come 
to take Thatcher for granted during her 11 years of power were not prepared for 
her passing. 
</P>
<P>
Thatcher had told the world that she would fight to a second ballot after her 
narrow failure to retain the premiership outright on Tuesday. The feeling 
everywhere was that Thatcher always stuck to her word. So no problem. Pass the 
turkey. 
</P>
<P>
Thatcher's friends all over the world had reckoned without the British 
Conservative Party, which had looked at the opinion polls, the bad economic 
news and an unpopular new tax and smelled a loss at the next election. They had 
reckoned without the hatred for the flamboyant Michael Heseltine among the 
middle-ranking party figures who risked losing their jobs and future prospects 
if the unpredictable "Tarzan" came to power. 
</P>
<P>
It was an extraordinary scene in the palace of Westminster on Wednesday night 
as one by one her own Cabinet members trooped sheepishly into Thatcher's office 
and told her, in their chosen code, that they "couldn't support her over the 
weekend" in the second round of secret balloting on the party's leadership. 
Therefore, if Heseltine was to be beaten, it had to be by someone else. After 
"sleeping on it," as one of her closest advisers put it, Thatcher reluctantly 
concluded that she had to go. Thus did the toughest fighter for shared British 
and American values since Winston Churchill become the first prime minister to 
be forced out of office by the Conservative Party since the failed war leader 
Neville Chamberlain. 
</P>
<P>
When George Bush recovered from his Thanksgiving surprise, he was generous in 
his praise. Two years ago, his words would have rung hollow. The President 
began his term in office without much trust in her. He had seen the influence 
she exerted over Ronald Reagan and was keen to be seen as his own man. He had 
heard her doubts over the pace of German reunification and the integration of 
Europe, and had been persuaded by his advisers that she stood against the 
United States' best interests. 
</P>
<P>
Gradually, however, that changed. At the beginning of the Persian Gulf crisis, 
the President deliberately sought Thatcher's analysis. It was her assessment of 
the threat to international security posed by Iraqi aggression that, according 
to British and American sources, set the moral framework for Operation Desert 
Shield. The pivotal moment was when she fielded press questions about Iraq on 
Bush's behalf in the Colorado mountain garden of the U.S. ambassador to 
Britain, Henry Catto; that marked the public turning point. She was able to 
articulate what Bush sensed was right. And he was able to defer to her without 
embarrassment, seeming almost gentlemanly in allowing her to go first. 
</P>
<P>
Bush is unlikely to reach such a rapport with any of her three potential 
successors. Heseltine is an exceptionally powerful orator, but it hard to see 
that helping the tongue-tied American President. Douglas Hurd, the urbane 
foreign secretary, is an English James Baker; the President already has a James 
Baker. John Major, the chancellor of the Exchequer and Thatcher's own choice to 
succeed her, may have views very close to Bush's. But he is mild-mannered, 
slightly clumsy and, although widely liked and admired by his friends, is 
almost wholly without international experience. 
</P>
<P>
The issue is no longer the Anglo-American "special relationship." It is 
Margaret Thatcher and Ronald Reagan who will go down in history as Washington 
and London's "last romantics." They were the ones who would each ditch their 
closest friends in order to support the other: Reagan when overruling Jeane 
Kirkpatrick's objections to the Falklands campaign, and Thatcher when blocking 
her own right wing's protests at the U.S. bombing of Libya from British bases. 
They shared the conviction that communism could be rolled back - and she 
helped persuade him that Mikhail Gorbachev was a man who could be trusted. The 
powerful enunciation of that belief - and its eventual vindication - may be 
the last great achievement of the special postwar Anglo-American alliance. 
</P>
<P>
George Bush and Margaret Thatcher had something more simple in common, a 
pragmatic relationship of mutual respect and support that benefited both. 
</P>
<P>
British policy toward Iraq will not change suddenly under a new prime minister. 
The doubling of the size of the British gulf force on Thursday attempted 
emphatically to prove that. But as time goes by, Britain's allies will find 
that many certainties have passed along with Margaret Thatcher. If seductive 
deals emerge to save the face and the atomic-weapon factories of Saddam 
Hussein, her steadfastness will be sorely missed. 
</P>
<P>
And if Europe becomes more inward-looking and protectionist, blame those who 
booted out the prime minister whose final words to her Cabinet were, "It's a 
funny old world." Her memoirs deserve a more dignified title. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA120890-0055
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>8
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
IT'S NOW 'LADY THATCHER,' BUT SHE'LL STICK WITH 'MRS.' 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
LONDON 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Queen Elizabeth II awarded former Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher the coveted 
Order of Merit on Friday and made her husband a baronet, which is a hereditary 
knighthood. 
</P>
<P>
From now on Denis Thatcher will be formally addressed as Sir Denis and his wife 
as Lady Thatcher, although she insisted Friday she wished to be known simply as 
"Mrs. Thatcher." 
</P>
<P>
"I have done pretty well out of being Mrs. Thatcher," said the former prime 
minister, who resigned Nov. 22 during a fight for the leadership of the 
Conservative Party. 
</P>
<P>
Palace insiders said Friday that one reason for the quick award of the Order of 
Merit, restricted to only 24 eminent men and women, was the queen's desire to 
demonstrate that there is no animosity between Britain's two most prominent 
women. 
</P>
<P>
In the past, Buckingham Palace sources and journalists assigned to the royal 
court have said that the two did not get along. 
</P>
<P>
"This puts (to rest) rumors that the queen and Mrs. Thatcher didn't like each 
other," said Harold Brooks-Baker, director of Burke's Peerage and an authority 
on the royal family. 
</P>
<P>
As a member of the Order of Merit, created in 1902, Thatcher joins such 
luminaries in the world of arts, science and politics as philosopher Isiah 
Berlin, historian Veronica Wedgwood, writer Graham Greene, violinist Yehudi 
Menuhin and artist Sidney Noland, as well as honorary member Mother Teresa. 
</P>
<P>
Deceased recipients include Prime Minister Winston Churchill, Gen. Dwight D. 
Eisenhower, missionary Albert Schweitzer and actor Lawrence Olivier. 
</P>
<P>
Contrary to some reports, the OM, as it is popularly called, does not precede 
all other British royal honors but ranks behind the Order of the Garter, which 
dates from 1348. 
</P>
<P>
Thatcher said she was "deeply honored and moved" by the award. 
</P>
<P>
At the same time, the queen gave a baronetcy to Thatcher's husband Denis, the 
subject of fictional letters from No. 10 Downing Street invented by the 
satirical magazine Private Eye about life as the prime minister's consort. 
</P>
<P>
Baronets date from 1611. Sir Denis' title passes upon his death to his son, 
Mark, who is married to an American, and will eventually pass to Mark 
Thatcher's son, Michael. 
</P>
<P>
With an OM, Thatcher can continue to serve in the House of Commons as the 
member from the North London constituency of Finchley. 
</P>
<P>
Burke's Brooks-Baker believes that Thatcher eventually should be made a 
hereditary countess, which in Britain is the female equivalent of an earl. 
Traditionally, retiring prime ministers of Britain were granted earldoms, 
although Churchill, for one, refused a peerage, preferring to remain in the 
House of Commons. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
THATCHER, MARGARET; THATCHER, DENIS; HONORS; ENGLAND - POLITICS 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
