<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880217-0100
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>17
</DAY> 
<MONTH>02
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Statistics on Six Decades of Oscar
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Oscar Nominations Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The motion picture industry's most coveted
award, Oscar, was created 60 years ago and 1,816 of the statuettes
have been produced so far.
</P>
<P>
Weighing 8{ pounds and standing 13{ inches tall, Oscar was
created by Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer studios art director Cedric Gibbons,
who went on to win 11 of the trophies.
</P>
<P>
Oscar, manufactured by the R.S. Owens Co., Chicago, is made of
Britannia metal, copper plate, nickel plate and gold plate. From
1942 to 1944, the trophy was made of plaster, but winners were
later presented with the real thing.
</P>
<P>
According to the Academy of Motion Pictures Arts and Sciences,
the only engraving mistake was in 1938 when the best actor trophy
given to Spencer Tracy for ``Boy's Town'' read: ``Best Actor: Dick
Tracy.''
The Academy holds all the rights on the statue and ``reserves
the right to buy back an Oscar before someone takes it to a pawn
shop,'' said Academy spokesman Bob Werden.
</P>
<P>
The most-nominated film was ``All About Eve'' in 1950. It got 14
nominations. ``Ben-Hur'' in 1959 was the most-awarded film with 11,
and Walt Disney was the most-awarded person with 32.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880325-0239
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>25
</DAY> 
<MONTH>03
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Oscar Countdown: The Overlooked
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Oscar Snubs The Best and The Brightest
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
What do Charlie Chaplin, Greta Garbo, Cary
Grant, Alfred Hitchcock and Steven Spielberg have in common? They
have never won Academy Awards for their individual achievements.
</P>
<P>
Such flagrant omissions are often cited by critics as evidence
of the unfairness of Hollywood's highest prize. Oscar's 60-year
history is filled with examples of the film world's highest
achievers being overlooked by the Academy of Motion Picture Arts
and Sciences.
</P>
<P>
The latest casualties are directors James L. Brooks, whose movie
``Broadcast News'' was nominated though he wasn't, and Spielberg
who was left out in the cold with his ``Empire of the Sun.''
Although ``Broadcast News'' won seven major nominations,
including best picture and three acting categories, Brooks was
strangely overlooked by the Academy's directing branch.
</P>
<P>
Since no movie has ever won a best picture Oscar without its
director at least being nominated, the chances of the once-favored
``Broadcast News'' to be a big winner at the awards ceremony on
April 11 have been significantly reduced.
</P>
<P>
Brooks did better in 1984 when his ``Terms of Endearment'' took
the lion's share of Oscars, including best picture and director.
</P>
<P>
Spielberg's ``Empire of the Sun'' won six nominations this year,
none of them major and none for director. Two years ago, ``The
Color Purple'' received 11 nominations but not for him as director.
</P>
<P>
The Directors Guild nevertheless named him best director that year.
``I'm floored by this,'' Spielberg said upon receiving his DGA
award. ``This is the last thing I expected to happen. ... If some
of you are making a statement _ thank God _ I thank you for that.''
Why the Spielberg slight? Some observers cite the fact that only
257 directors nominate for the Academy Awards, and many are
veterans who might not look kindly on the young man whose films are
the biggest moneymakers in history (``Jaws,'' ``E.T.,'' ``Raiders
of the Lost Ark'').
</P>
<P>
The Academy appeared to make amends last year by presenting
Spielberg with the Irving Thalberg award for ``consistently high
quality of production.'' There was no mention of the fact that
Spielberg is primarily a director, not a producer.
</P>
<P>
The Thalberg award has come in handy to acknowledge giants who
were overlooked for individual awards. The recipients have included
Cecil B. DeMille, Stanley Kramer, Alfred Hitchcock, Ingmar Bergman
and Mervyn Leroy.
</P>
<P>
The honorary award has also proved useful to salve the Academy's
conscience. Charlie Chaplin received one at the first Academy
Awards for his creation of ``The Circus'' and again at the 44th
awards for ``the incalculable effect he has had in making motion
pictures the art form of this century.''
Douglas Fairbanks, Judy Garland, Noel Coward, Ernst Lubitsch,
Fred Astaire, Gene Kelly, Harold Lloyd, Greta Garbo, Maurice
Chevalier, Stan Laurel, Cary Grant, Lillian Gish, Edward G.
</P>
<P>
Robinson, Groucho Marx, Howard Hawks and Jean Renoir are others who
have received honorary awards.
</P>
<P>
Cary Grant once remarked that he never expected to win an
Academy Award. ``I'd have to blacken my teeth first,'' he quipped,
alluding to the Academy's fondness for actors who portray bums and
downtrodden characters.
</P>
<P>
Alfred Hitchcock also had a lighthearted comment on why he
failed to win an Oscar: ``I suppose it was a matter of
carelessness.''
The overlooking of classic films and the industry's most
talented filmmakers has provided historians with cause for dispute.
</P>
<P>
For example, ``Citizen Kane,'' which customarily places No. 1 on
polls of the greatest American films, was nominated in 1941 for
best picture (there were 10 nominees in those days), for Orson
Welles' performance, direction and co-scripting with Herman
Mankiewicz, Gregg Toland's camera work, plus art direction, sound,
music and editing.
</P>
<P>
The only Oscar for ``Citizen Kane'' was for the script. ``How
Green Was My Valley'' was named best picture.
</P>
<P>
Billy Wilder's classic comedy, ``Some Like It Hot,'' failed to
be nominated as best picture, as did Chaplin's ``Modern Times,''
Hawks' ``Red River'' and Woody Allen's ``Manhattan.''
Oh, well. Oscar might use Joe E. Brown's final line from ``Some
Like It Hot'': ``Nobody's perfect.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880328-0206
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>28
</DAY> 
<MONTH>03
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
From AP Newsfeatures
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With BC-APN-Oscars
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
HOLLYWOOD (AP) _ Like all great contests, the annual Academy
Awards ceremony has generated a wealth of statistics and trivia
over its 60 years of existence, all carefully chronicled by Oscar
historians.
</P>
<P>
Here, courtesy of the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and
Sciences, are 20 questions about Oscar:
1. What actress has received the most Oscars? Katharine Hepburn,
4.
2. What actor has received the most Oscars? Walter Brennan, 3.
3. What director has received the most Oscars? John Ford, 4.
4. Who is the most nominated actress? Katharine Hepburn, 12.
5. Who is the most nominated actor? Laurence Olivier, 10.
6. Who is the most nominated director? William Wyler, 12.
7. How long was the longest Oscar ceremony? 3 hours, 45 minutes
in 1985.
8. What film has won the most Oscars? ``Ben-Hur,'' 11, 1959.
9. What was the most nominated picture? ``Gone With The Wind,''
``Mary Poppins'' and ``Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf,'' each with
13.
10. What studio has won the most Oscars? MGM, with nearly 200.
11. Who was the youngest performer to win an Oscar? Tatum
O'Neal, 10, supporting actress, ``Paper Moon,'' 1973.
12. Who was the oldest performer ever to win an Oscar? Groucho
Marx, 83, an honorary award in 1974. George Burns is the oldest
actor to win a performing Oscar, 80, for the ``The Sunshine Boys''
in 1976.
13. What actor won a posthumous award? Peter Finch, ``Network,''
1976.
14. What father-son team won Oscars in the same picture? Walter
Huston, supporting actor, and John Huston, director-writer, ``The
Treasure of Sierra Madre,'' 1948.
15. What actor was nominated in two categories for the same
role? Barry Fitzgerald, ``Going My Way,'' 1944. He won in the
supporting category.
16. Who decapitated his Oscar while practicing golf swings
indoors? Barry Fitzgerald. His 1944 supporting actor statuette was
subsequently replaced by the Academy.
17. What performers have refused their Oscars? George C. Scott
and Marlon Brando.
18. How many people view the Oscar ceremony on television? Last
year, the Oscarcast was seen by one billion people in 79 countries.
19. Who holds the record for the fastest televised reading of
the famed Academy rules? Actor-comedian John (Federal Express)
Moschitta, 25 seconds, 1983.
20. What multiple Oscar winner has never appeared to collect her
award? Katharine Hepburn, all four times.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890323-0218
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>03
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
$Adv 24
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
For Release Fri PMs, March 24 and Thereafter
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Oscar Ballot Comes Under Scrutiny As Some Allege Team Voting
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Oscar selection has come under scrutiny as film
studios go to new lengths to pull votes out of the Academy of Motion
Picture Arts and Sciences.
</P>
<P>
And with the flood of Oscar vote enticements _ from free coffee
mugs to complimentary buffet dinners _ Academy members are
acknowledging that some Oscar voting is done by committee, in
violation of the rules. Secretaries, spouses and friends, several
Academy members say, are marking ballots in what is supposed to be
the entertainment industry's most esteemed awards competition.
``It's like a local election of judges,'' said Academy member
Harry Clein, who said he's witnessed team voting. ``A lot of people
don't know who the candidates are. So they take a look at who's
around them and see what the consensus is.
``As far as elections go, it's not bad. But I've never been
through an election in Argentina.''
Dan Lyle, who oversees the Oscar balloting for the accounting
firm Price, Waterhouse Inc., said that there is no guarantee that
Academy members have actually filled out their own ballots.
``All we know is that a properly numbered ballot has been
returned,'' he said. ``Members are on the honor system to fill out
the ballot themselves.''
More than 4,600 members were given ballots this year for the 61st
Annual Academy Awards, which will be telecast on March 29 from the
Shrine Auditorium in Los Angeles. Academy members vote on their area
of specialty. The Academy's actors branch, for example, is the only
group to select nominees in the four acting categories.
</P>
<P>
Since the voting is done secretly _ members do not sign their
ballots _ the ballot's authenticity is ensured solely by a numeric
control number, Lyle said. Ballots are invalidated only if there is
more than one vote in a given category, and only the votes in that
specific category are not tallied, he said.
</P>
<P>
Nominations for acting, directing, art direction and all
specialized categories are handled by select branches and committees
composed of Academy members.
</P>
<P>
All voting members of the Academy can participate in the best
picture nominations and may vote for the final awards in all
categories. Winners for best documentary feature, best animated
short film and best live-action short film are chosen by only those
members who have seen all the nominees.
</P>
<P>
Academy constituent Julian Blaustein said that most of his
colleagues take the voting very seriously. ``I don't even vote (in a
category) if I'm not familiar with the pictures in that category.
... And I've never told someone to vote for a film, even when I've
done some of them.''
Meanwhile, other Oscar voting rules are perhaps being broken,
speculates veteran Academy member Millard Kaufman. ``Although you're
asked to vote in the nominations for five pictures, I think a lot of
people figure out that they have a better chance if they just vote
for their own picture and leave the other four blank,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Given the tremendous impact both an Oscar nomination and an Oscar
victory have on a film's fortunes, it's not entirely surprising that
a certain degree of artifice might surround the Oscars.
``The Last Emperor'' took in $18.9 million, close to half the
film's gross, after it won last year's best picture trophy. More
than 70 percent of the revenues generated by 1986's best picture,
``Platoon,'' came after the film was nominated. On average, a best
picture award is worth about $20 million these days.
</P>
<P>
A $500,000 Oscar promotional campaign mounted by a studio,
therefore, can be a good investment. In the case of this year's
awards, a flurry of Academy-oriented newspaper advertisements,
banquets, complimentary gifts and photo mailings tied to five late
releases appears to have been remarkably successful.
</P>
<P>
This year, all best picture nominees and the large majority of
top acting nominees came from movies released in December: ``The
Accidental Tourist,'' ``Dangerous Liaisons,'' ``Rain Man'' and
``Working Girl'' were all released after Dec. 16.
</P>
<P>
While these five movies might be good, the nearly complete
exclusion of films from the rest of the year has highlighted the
studios' mastery of Oscar marketing.
``I think the Academy Awards are crap,'' said Terry Gilliam,
director of ``Brazil'' and the current ``The Adventures of Baron
Munchausen.''
``It's about selling films is all it's about,'' he said. ``It's
one more way of flogging some films. When `Brazil' got nominated (in
1986), they asked me to be a member of the Academy. And I wouldn't
join. I just don't want to be a part of that at all.''
And at least one prominent Academy member, director Carl Reiner,
says that the manipulation of Oscar voters has reached new depths.
</P>
<P>
Reiner said that Universal Studios' all-out effort to bag votes for
Sigourney Weaver, a best actress nominee for ``Gorillas in the
Mist,'' could lead him to vote against the film.
``I have in my house more color reproductions of Sigourney Weaver
and a beautiful gorilla than I need,'' Reiner said of promotional
material sent to his home. ``We've got to tell the Academy to stop
this advertising. I'm getting turned off on the pictures I like.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890324-0014
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>24
</DAY> 
<MONTH>03
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
As Commercialism Creeps In, Academy Fights To Save Oscar Integrity
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Free enterprise has collided with the Academy
Awards, and everybody's trying to pick up the pieces.
</P>
<P>
With Oscar statuettes selling at auction for more than $10,000
and a Chicago trophy company casting alleged Academy Award clones,
the National Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences is
scrambling to make sure Oscar's golden sheen isn't tarnished by
Hollywood hucksterism.
``If you know about an infringement and fail to object to it, you
risk having your trademark become public domain,'' said Bruce Davis,
the Academy's executive administrator, in explaining the lawsuits
the organization has filed to protect its beloved hunk of
electroplated pewter.
</P>
<P>
But despite the Academy's crusade against crass commercialism,
this year's awards ceremony will feature a new merchandising
wrinkle: Some 800 limousines delivering the most famous stars to the
Oscar telecast will be equipped with door-mounted coolers jammed
with Diet Coke, Coca-Cola Classic and other Coca-Cola Co. beverages.
</P>
<P>
When the limo doors swing open in front of the Shrine Auditorium
and the celebrities tumble out, the Coke logo will be on display in
front of an audience that includes millions around the world.
``It seemed like a good marketing opportunity,'' said Coca-Cola
spokesman Ira Gleser. ``The Academy approached our local bottler in
Los Angeles and said we're going to have a lot of thirsty people.''
But even as the Academy embraces this new intrusion of
merchandising, it has lashed out at whatever else it considers a
blemishing of the Oscar name.
</P>
<P>
When MGM-UA, the distributor of ``Rain Man,'' published newspaper
advertisements touting the film's Oscar nominations before the
nominations were even announced, the Academy issued a harsh
statement condemning MGM-UA's promotional gamble. After the ads
appeared, ``Rain Man'' collected nine nominations.
``We regard this as a serious matter, and we have communicated
our concern,'' said Richard Kahn, president of the Academy.
</P>
<P>
For nearly 50 years, the Academy has maintained strict security
around both the nominations and the award winners. It also has
envisoned the statuette itself as something of an icon.
</P>
<P>
So auctioning the Oscar has greatly distressed the Academy.
</P>
<P>
The Collector's Book Store, local sponsors of monthly
entertainment memorabilia auctions, has sold off seven Oscars in the
past year, including the best picture trophy for 1951's ``An
American in Paris'' ($15,760), Marlon Brando's best actor prize for
1954's ``On the Waterfront'' ($13,000) and the black and white
interior decoration Oscar for 1941's ``How Green Was My Valley''
($17,715).
</P>
<P>
None were sold by the original recipients; heirs or friends who
had later received the trophies put them on the block.
</P>
<P>
When Malcolm Willits, the book store's owner, announced that he
would hold a February auction for the 1957 best-picture trophy for
``Around the World in 80 Days,'' the Academy said enough, initiating
a court action that, for now, has blocked any future trophy sales.
</P>
<P>
The Academy insists that a contract signed by Oscar winners
mandates that they will not sell the trophies without first offering
them to the Academy for a nominal fee.
``But now that the word is out that these awards are worth
$10,000 to $50,000, people are reluctant to sell them back to the
Academy for $10,'' Willits said.
``The Academy has created something of great value here. This is
the most famous award in the world _ the most instantly recognizable
award. The Nobel Prize might be a greater honor, but people know
more about what an Academy Award looks like.
``And they're very limited, too. There's not too many of them
around. ... Twenty years ago, you wouldn't have a movie poster in
your living room unless you were a college student. Now, you can go
into Beverly Hills homes and there's a movie poster, and the darn
thing's worth $10,000 or $20,000 dollars.''
When the Academy won a court order temporarily blocking future
auctions, Willits decided to sell his store. ``It seemed to be the
final straw. I don't like lawsuits,'' he said. ``I'm getting older
and I'd like to write movie scripts.''
Yet the Academy has lost its most recent attempt to save its
trophy's integrity: A copyright infringement suit brought against
the Houston International Film Festival was dismissed March 16 in a
California federal court.
</P>
<P>
The Academy had claimed the Lone Star Statuette, designed and
built by Chicago's Creative House Promotions, was ``practically
identical'' to the Oscar. The court found otherwise.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890330-0123
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>30
</DAY> 
<MONTH>03
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
61st Oscars: Way Too Much, And Some New Award Categories
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Spencer Tracy's acting technique was simply
``less is better,'' and that helped make him the screen's greatest
actor. The Tracy credo is recommended to future producers of
Academy Award shows.
</P>
<P>
Wednesday night's orgy of self-congratulation was dazzling,
glamorous and all those familiar Hollywood adjectives. Also too
much.
</P>
<P>
Too many endless production numbers. Too much forced
conversation between couples. Too many awards with meaning lost to
the general public.
</P>
<P>
The use of ``couples, co-stars, compadres and companions,'' as
presenters for the 61st Academy Awards at the Shrine Auditorium was
clever but wearing.
</P>
<P>
The best Oscar shows have been emceed by Will Rogers, Bob Hope,
Johnny Carson and other funnymen who provided continuity as well as
a leavening of pomposity.
</P>
<P>
The brightest moments of the 61st Awards came from Billy
Crystal, Robin Williams and Bob Hope, but they were all too brief.
</P>
<P>
Tom Selleck remarked that Douglas Fairbanks Sr. handed out the
first awards in 1929 in five minutes. The present awards could be
staged in two hours instead of the 3 hours and 15 minutes they took
Wednesday night on ABC-TV.
</P>
<P>
But the show will never be shorter. Reason: The time is needed
to sell all those 30-second adds at $375,000 per.
</P>
<P>
Since the Academy Awards are a night of superlatives here are a
few more:
The most heartfelt acceptance: Dustin Hoffman.
</P>
<P>
The most intelligent acceptance: Jodie Foster.
</P>
<P>
Warmest reception: Lucille Ball and Bob Hope.
</P>
<P>
Best looking legs: Cyd Charisse.
</P>
<P>
Second-best looking legs: Martin Short.
</P>
<P>
Worst desecration of an icon: Snow White portrayed as a whining
would-be starlet.
</P>
<P>
Best comedy routine: Billy Crystal imitating Yul Brynner as Babe
Ruth.
</P>
<P>
Best walk-on music: ``The Second Time Around'' for Melanie
Griffith and Don Johnson.
</P>
<P>
Least promising rock singer: Rob Lowe.
</P>
<P>
Most overworked butt of jokes: Vice President Dan Quayle by
Crystal, Hope and Williams (twice).
</P>
<P>
Most prevalent fashion: Strapless gowns.
</P>
<P>
Seemingly endless number: ``Oscar Winners of Tomorrow.''
Most relentless double entendre: Bo Derek and Dudley Moore.
</P>
<P>
Most questionable taste: Kurt Russell's ``proposal'' of marriage
to Goldie Hawn.
</P>
<P>
Most mentioned agent: Michael Ovitz of Creative Artists Agency.
</P>
<P>
Most recurrent dance routine: The Rockettes-like line of kickers.
</P>
<P>
Best exchange of banter: Sean Connery, Michael Caine and Roger
Moore.
</P>
<P>
Most welcomed elimination: Singing of the nominees for best song.
</P>
<P>
Most stunning beauty: Michelle Pfeiffer
Worst reader of Teleprompter: Walter Matthau.
</P>
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
<P>
Editors: Wednesday's ceremony was Bob Thomas' 45th Academy
Awards.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891110-0043
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>10
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Oscar Trophy Has No Copyright
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Oscar statuette, one of the most
recognizable images in the entertainment world, has no copyright
protection, a federal judge has ruled.
</P>
<P>
The small Academy Award statue is part of the public domain,
U.S. District Court Judge Laughlin Waters said in a ruling released
Thursday.
</P>
<P>
The decision was a setback for the Academy of Motion Picture
Arts and Sciences, which had sued a Chicago-based manufacturer of
an employee-incentive trophy similar to the Oscar.
</P>
<P>
Academy President Karl Malden said the ruling ``comes as a shock
to me.'' The academy said it would appeal.
</P>
<P>
The academy claimed that the Star Award, the trophy look-alike
made by Creative House Promotions, violated copyright laws, diluted
the academy's trademark and represented unfair competition.
</P>
<P>
The Star Award depicted a naked, muscular male much like the
Oscar, just two inches shorter and holding a star instead of a
sword. It had a gold finish similar to the Oscar, and stood on a
circular gold cap mounted on a cylindrical base.
</P>
<P>
Although Waters acknowledged that the Creative House trophy is
``very similar'' to the Oscar, he rejected all of the academy's
legal claims, saying that the statuette became part of the public
domain prior to Jan. 1, 1978, the effective date of the Copyright
Act of 1976.
</P>
<P>
The film industry's top award was distributed from the first
ceremony in 1929 until about 1941 without the ``c'' mark indicating
a copyright.
</P>
<P>
The judge ruled, too, that the Oscar not only was an honorary
award but also was used to promote the film industry, and therefore
did not have a ``limited purpose,'' as required by the copyright
act.
</P>
<P>
The academy noted that the ruling applied only to the statuette
and that the academy's trademark and service marks for the Oscar
and the Academy Award names and symbols are unaffected.
``We are surprised that the court would base its decision on
events which occurred half a century ago, overlooking the
meticulous fashion in which the Academy has protected the integrity
of its institutional symbol for decades,'' Malden said in a
statement.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900220-0065
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>20
</DAY> 
<MONTH>02
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Director Spike Lee Has Pointed Remarks in Talk at Syracuse
University
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Spike Lee may have been wearing a
Georgetown University cap and sweatshirt, but he got a far warmer
reception from Syracuse University students than he did from
Academy Award voters.
</P>
<P>
In a lecture and question-and-answer session Monday, Lee
shrugged off the academy's icy treatment of his latest movie, ``Do
the Right Thing,'' and blamed it on generational politics.
</P>
<P>
The 1989 film, widely hailed by critics, received only two
Academy Award nominations, and isn't being considered for best
picture or best director.
</P>
<P>
The academy's membership consists mainly of ``old people,'' the
32-year-old Lee said. He said they were ``a lot more comfortable
with the black chauffeur in `Driving Miss Daisy''' than with the
angry characters in his film.
``I still feel we made the best film of the year,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Asked if racism might have been involved in the academy
nominations, Lee replied, ``Racism's involved in everything.''
Despite the cap and sweatshirt, Syracuse students welcomed him
as one of their own.
``He's an African-American, one of the first ones to make it (as
a producer and director), and he's addressing the issues and
concerns affecting our community,'' Syracuse senior Deron Harris
said. ``That's why we're so proud of him.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA033089-0190
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>30
</DAY> 
<MONTH>3
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
SOMETHING FOR EVERYONE . . . ALMOST; 
ACADEMY VOTERS SURVEY THE FIELD, AND SPREAD THE WEALTH 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Well, it did turn out to be "Rain Man's" evening, but not until the last few 
minutes, and if there was a message in Wednesday night's Academy Awards 
results, it's that parity has returned to Hollywood. 
</P>
<P>
For two-thirds of the show, the academy voters seemed determined to give an 
award to every film nominated. As it was, 10 different movies split 17 awards, 
the most winners for one year in this decade. 
</P>
<P>
The major awards made the forecasters look smart and the academy predictable. 
"Rain Man" did win the grand prize (and three other big ones) and "Mississippi 
Burning," with just one Oscar for cinematography, did get punished for its 
highly publicized historical muddling. 
</P>
<P>
But gone, for a refreshing change, was the slate voting that has turned many 
recent Academy Awards shows into one-note evenings that kept some deserving 
people out of the Oscar resale market. 
</P>
<P>
"Rain Man," its director Barry Levinson, Hoffman and the screenwriters (the two 
of several who worked on it) may have fulfilled their roles as favorites, but 
there were no sure things elsewhere, and people looking for early patterns had 
to throw away the form. 
</P>
<P>
The final score shows "Rain Man" with four Oscars and "Dangerous Liaisons" and 
"Who Framed Roger Rabbit" with three each. But there were seven other films 
with one award each. 
</P>
<P>
Whether the spread represents a change in voting habits, or an absence of a 
film to rally around, it made for a great show and in some cases, the awards 
helped right some wrongs in the nominations process. 
</P>
<P>
That "Who Framed Roger Rabbit" won three of the six awards for which it was 
nominated may save the academy some embarrassment for neglecting the one 1988 
film sure to be regarded as a classic. 
</P>
<P>
The good news for observers of voter psychology were the awards given to films 
that were not box-office hits. The voters tend to favor those films that are 
both of substance and commercially successful (thus: "Rain Man"), and whether 
they even bother to see the other nominees is often questioned. 
</P>
<P>
This year, several winners came from films that failed to ring up big numbers 
at the box office: Jodie Foster as best actress from "The Accused," Geena Davis 
as best supporting actress from "The Accidental Tourist." 
</P>
<P>
More surprising were the awards given to "Bird" and "The Milagro Beanfield 
War," films that divided critics and sent moviegoers off to the video store 
looking for alternatives. 
</P>
<P>
Both films were flawed, but the sound editing done for "Bird," which seamlessly 
blended old jazz recordings with fresh studio cuts done by contemporary 
musicians, was brilliant and deserved the award its four-man sound team won. 
</P>
<P>
David Grusin's Oscar for scoring "The Milagro Beanfield War" overcame even 
bigger odds, winning over popular John Williams' score for "The Accidental 
Tourist." 
</P>
<P>
The selective mood of the voters is a reflection of the kind of year the film 
industry had, and whether the spread is a quirk, one can hope it suggests a 
trend. 
</P>
<P>
The 1988 slate of films was, on total, a marked improvement over recent years. 
The industry is still adjusting to its changing - its older and more demanding 
audience - and that means a wider variety of films. Nominees this year 
represented as wide a range of material as any in years, and they produced more 
winning films. 
</P>
<P>
The events last night played hell with the office pool, but it made for a 
better show. Maybe it's the start of something new. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
ACADEMY AWARDS; 1988 (YEAR); MOTION PICTURES; HONORS; RAIN MAN (MOTION 
PICTURE); HOFFMAN, DUSTIN; FOSTER, JODIE; LEVINSON, BARRY; KLINE, KEVIN; DAVIS, 
GEENA; AWARDS 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA033189-0114
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>31
</DAY> 
<MONTH>3
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
DISNEY SUES OVER USE OF SNOW WHITE AT OSCARS 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Who would have thought that Snow White, of all people, would become the source 
of Oscar night's only major glitch? 
</P>
<P>
The Walt Disney Co. filed suit in Los Angeles federal court Thursday against 
the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, charging copyright 
infringement of its Snow White character and unfair competition. 
</P>
<P>
The famous fairy tale character, portrayed by singer-dancer Eileen Bowman, 
opened Wednesday night's Academy Awards ceremonies with an elaborate, 10-minute 
song-and-dance routine. But Disney contends that the character was used on the 
show without the company's permission. 
</P>
<P>
"We have great respect for the academy and for all that it does," Frank Wells, 
Disney's president and chief operating officer, said Thursday in a prepared 
statement. "We were therefore greatly surprised and dismayed when we viewed 
last evening's Academy Awards ceremonies to see that our Snow White character 
had been used extensively without our permission." 
</P>
<P>
Wells said the suit was filed only after the company asked the academy to 
publicly apologize for its unauthorized use of the character, which debuted in 
a 1937 full-length cartoon film. 
</P>
<P>
"If such a statement had been agreed to by the academy," Wells said, "we would 
have considered the matter ended. For its own reasons, however, the academy 
unfortunately did not accede to our request." 
</P>
<P>
Disney spokesman Erwin Okun did not provide any details of Thursday's 
negotiations with academy officials over an apology, except to say that the 
academy's offer "was not to our satisfaction." 
</P>
<P>
Bruce Davis, the academy's executive administrator, declined comment, saying 
top officials needed time to assess the suit. 
</P>
<P>
"We haven't gotten any official notification of this," Davis said, adding that 
he learned of the legal action from a reporter. 
</P>
<P>
Ironically, the academy is extremely protective of the Oscar name and statuette 
copyrights and is quick to object to the image's unauthorized use. 
</P>
<P>
Number Kept Secret 
</P>
<P>
Alan Carr, who produced the Oscar show, had ordered that the details of the 
opening number be kept secret until Wednesday night's ABC telecast. 
</P>
<P>
But in its suit, Disney says a company representative learned of the plans 
early in the week. The company claims that the academy refused to respond to 
its inquiries until Wednesday afternoon. 
</P>
<P>
At that point, the Disney statement said, the academy, "through a legal 
representative, denied to Disney that the Academy Award program contained any 
material deleterious to the interests of Disney, without revealing the 
academy's intention to feature Disney's Snow White." 
</P>
<P>
Carr could not be reached for comment Thursday. 
</P>
<P>
The Snow White character - as portrayed Wednesday night by Bowman - was 
created by Steve Silver, who for 15 years has used the character in the San 
Francisco musical revue "Beach Blanket Babylon." 
</P>
<P>
Disney files dozens of suits a year against individuals and companies that copy 
its characters, particularly in consumer products. 
</P>
<P>
"We sue all the time," Okun said. 
</P>
<P>
But Okun said the company, which won four Oscars Wednesday night, has never 
sued Silver over his use of the Snow White character in that production. The 
spokesman, however, did not preclude the possibility of a future lawsuit. 
</P>
<P>
"We look at these characters as the heart and soul of the company," Okun 
explained. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
SNOW WHITE; CARR, ALAN; BOWMAN, EILEEN; WALT DISNEY CO; ACADEMY OF MOTION 
PICTURE ARTS AND SCIENCES; ACADEMY AWARDS; SUITS; COPYRIGHT; CARTOON CHARACTERS 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
