<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891115-0199
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>15
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Severe Weather Erupts Over Mississippi Valley, Southeast
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with lethal tornado in Alabama;
picks up 3rd graf pvs, `People in ...; INSERTS 2 grafs after 8th graf pvs,
`Thunderstorms crossing ...,' to UPDATE with storms hitting Georgia, Ohio.
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Thunderstorms wreaked havoc across the middle Mississippi Valley
and the Southeast on Wednesday with lethal tornadoes, wind up to
100 mph and hail up to the size of baseballs.
</P>
<P>
At least four tornadoes pounded the Huntsville, Ala., area. One
twister smashed into a residential district, a shopping area and a
school, killing at least two people and causing dozens of injuries,
police said.
</P>
<P>
Southern Illinois was also hard hit by the storms, with one
woman killed by a falling tree, about 20 people injured and power
lines downed.
</P>
<P>
Elsewhere, snow fell from the northern Rockies to the upper
Great Lakes, while unseasonably mild weather continued in the East.
</P>
<P>
People in Alorton, Ill., a village of 2,700 about five miles
southeast of East St. Louis, were injured when trees fell on their
houses or mobile homes, said Bill Gamblin of the St. Clair County
Emergency Services and Disaster Agency.
</P>
<P>
At Parks College in Cahokia, Ill., eight miles south of East St.
</P>
<P>
Louis, aircraft hangers were twisted and flattened and small
aircraft tossed around the airport by high winds, the National
Weather Service said.
</P>
<P>
Storms in the area generated wind estimated at 80 to 100 mph,
the weather service said.
</P>
<P>
The thunderstorms developed along and ahead of a strong cold
front and swept eastward from Missouri and Arkansas.
</P>
<P>
Thunderstorms crossing northeastern Arkansas whipped up high
wind which blew away metal roofing being installed on a high school
gymnasium at Lepanto and dumped hail up to 2 inches in diameter at
Leachville.
</P>
<P>
Heavy thunderstorms, possibly a tornado, struck the north
Georgia town of Palmetto late Wednesday, causing extensive damage,
authorities said.
</P>
<P>
In central and southwest Ohio, thunderstorms packing winds up to
66 mph destroyed barns and a trailer home and tore the roofs off
several buildings. Some injuries but no fatalities were reported.
</P>
<P>
An afternoon thunderstorm in east-central Alabama formed a
tornado which damaged at least one home, and the Clay County
Sheriff's office said an unknown number of people were injured in
one house.
</P>
<P>
Thunderstorms sweeping across Tennessee spun off a tornado in
southeastern Madison Country, and dropped hail as big as baseballs
north of Jackson, the weather service said.
</P>
<P>
Hail stones as big as tennis balls fell near Huntingburg, Ind.,
the weather service said.
</P>
<P>
The heaviest rainfall during the six hours up to 1 p.m. EST was
1.22 inches at Peru, Ind.
</P>
<P>
Wind up to 65 mph damaged roofs, power lines and trees in parts
of Kentucky and Louisiana, the weather service said.
</P>
<P>
Severe thunderstorms also developed over Alabama and South
Carolina during the afternoon, and the weather service reported a
tornado north of Greenwood, S.C.
</P>
<P>
Other showers and thunderstorms, with locally heavy rain, were
widely scattered along the northern Atlantic Coast.
</P>
<P>
Light snow associated with an arctic cold front extended from
eastern Wyoming and northeastern Colorado into western Minnesota.
</P>
<P>
Snow also fell across parts of northern Wisconsin and Upper
Michigan.
</P>
<P>
As much as 1 to 2 feet of snow was possible by Thursday morning
along the Lake Superior shore of Wisconsin.
</P>
<P>
Strong northwesterly wind ushering the cold air into the
north-central states gusted above 40 mph during the afternoon,
creating wind chill readings colder than 25 degrees below zero.
</P>
<P>
Snow, high wind and rapidly falling temperatures associated with
the cold front briefly produced near-blizzard conditions in
Nebraska late Wednesday morning.
</P>
<P>
Unseasonably warm weather continued in the East with afternoon
readings in the 60s in New England, and in the 80s over Florida,
southern Texas and southern Louisiana.
</P>
<P>
Wednesday morning's low for the Lower 48 states was 9 degrees
above zero at Ely, Nev.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891116-0035
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
URGENT
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Deadly Twister Smashes Huntsville, Ala.
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to UPDATE with 15th fatality; picks up 4th
graf pvs.
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhotos ATN1, HUN1,2,3; LaserGraphic
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A tornado slammed into a shopping
district, a residential area and a school Wednesday, killing at
least 15 people, injuring more than 300 and trapping people in cars
and homes, authorities said.
``It's total destruction where the tornado hit. Cars are piled
on top of each other under piles of rubble where buildings used to
be,'' said Danny Cooper, state emergency management director in
Montgomery.
</P>
<P>
Emergency officials in Huntsville reported 15 confirmed deaths,
said Henry Jurnigan, a duty officer with the state Emergency
Management Agency in Montgomery. Mayor Steve Hettinger said 305
people were injured and about 500 displaced by the tornado that
struck while streets of this northeastern Alabama city filled with
rush-hour traffic.
</P>
<P>
Rescue teams with cranes and floodlights searched the rubble
through the night for injured or dead.
``Several people are still trapped in vehicles and apartment
complexes and shopping areas,'' said police spokesman Ben Jennings
after the twister touched down between 4 and 4:30 p.m. in the
city's south section.
``It may be tomorrow before we have a final count,'' Gov. Guy
Hunt said at the state's disaster center in Montgomery.
</P>
<P>
The governor dispatched 50 National Guardsmen, along with search
and rescue equipment.
</P>
<P>
Rescuers picked through piles of rubble 10 to 14 feet deep, and
Cooper said police were unable to determine the extent of the
damaged area. Rescuers also were hampered by darkness and plunging
temperatures.
``We're even having a few snowflakes,'' said Cooper. High
temperatures in Huntsville were expected to be in the 30s Thursday,
he said.
</P>
<P>
Witnesses said the downtown Jones Valley Elementary School, the
Waterford Square and adjacent Queensbury apartment complexes were
reduced to rubble by the tornado.
``The only thing left standing was a door frame,'' news
photographer Mike Mercier said of the school, which was empty of
staff and pupils when the tornado hit. Police reported one person
killed in a car outside the school.
</P>
<P>
Authorities said at least five were killed at Waterford Square
apartments, three at a business school, Southern Junior College,
which is located in a converted movie theater, and others in
scattered areas.
``Rescuers are digging in the rubble,'' state trooper W.L. Kelly
said. He said two people were killed when the twister hit house
trailers in rural areas east of Huntsville. The fifth death was
reported near the shopping district.
</P>
<P>
The city is home to Marshall Space Flight Center and the Army's
Redstone Arsenal, but no serious damage was reported from the space
agency or weapons testing center.
``We've called in troopers from around the state to help,''
Kelly said.
</P>
<P>
Telephone communication and electricity were disrupted by the
tornadoes and WAAY-TV, the only station still broadcasting,
reported widespread damage.
``It came in with a huge roar, an enormous amount of water, and
it just started shaking and tearing at everything it could get hold
of,'' said real estate broker Ike Carroll, who was in his car when
the twister struck.
``It started picking cars up and pushing them around, ... some
of them upside down, some of them just strewn around,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Heavy overhead power lines ``started snapping just like a circus
performer would snap his whip,'' Carroll said.
``All of these heavy arcing, flashing lines that were just
popping and snapping over the top of us ... it was as if you were
looking into an arc-welder, they were so bright,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
WAAY reported at least one person died when the roof of a
business collapsed from winds that overturned cars in the area. A
nearby shopping center also was damaged.
</P>
<P>
Humana Hospital administrator David Miller said doctors were
having difficulty reaching the hospital because of blocked roads.
</P>
<P>
The National Weather Service earlier said a tornado hit the east
Alabama hamlet of Mellow Valley, severely damaging at least one
home and causing some injuries. Weather officials said people were
trapped inside a collapsed house.
</P>
<P>
A spokeswoman for the Clay County Sheriff's Department said
people were injured at one house in a rural area 30 miles east of
Sylacauga.
</P>
<P>
Another tornado touched down about 1:30 p.m. as severe weather
swept across much of Alabama and the National Weather Service
placed most of the state under a tornado watch.
</P>
<P>
A third tornado was reported shortly before 3:30 p.m. crossing
the Coosa River near Titus in east Alabama, the Weather Service
said.
</P>
<P>
In Georgia, five people were injured, four critically, and at
least 200 people evacuated after a tornado struck two mobile home
parks and an interstate highway near Palmetto, about 25 miles
southeast of Atlanta, authorities said.
</P>
<P>
Authorities in southwestern North Carolina said a pair of
storm-spawned tornadoes struck around 10:45 p.m., destroying a
vacant house in Henderson County.
</P>
<P>
The National Weather Service also reported tornadoes inflicting
minor property damage in Kentucky and Mississippi.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891116-0184
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Powerful Storm Pushes North, Brings Floods and Destruction to Northeast
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A powerful storm system brought strong winds and heavy
thunderstorms to the Northeast on Thursday, causing flooding and
widespread property damage. Seven children died when a wall
collapsed in a school cafeteria near Newburgh, N.Y.
</P>
<P>
Tornadoes were reported in New Jersey, Delaware, Virginia and
New York, although the National Weather Service was unable to
confirm them. The same storm system caused tornadoes in seven
states in the South and Midwest on Wednesday, and was blamed for 17
deaths in Huntsville, Ala.
</P>
<P>
The storm was particularly violent because it occurred along a
line of extreme variations in temperature. High temperature records
fell in advance of the storm and sharply colder weather lurked
behind it.
</P>
<P>
Record highs were recorded in Binghamton, N.Y., where it was 61
degrees, Bridgeport, Conn., (66), and Burlington, Vt., (69). A
record was also set in Miami, where it was 89.
</P>
<P>
Thunderstorms continued across the Ohio Valley overnight and
during the morning. Storms that might have been tornadoes damaged a
residence and a store near Richmond, Va., and uprooted about 600
feet of trees near Wilmington, Del. Other storms that might have
been tornados were reported near Peekskill, N.Y., and Piscataway,
N.J., during the afternoon.
</P>
<P>
Strong thunderstorms caused a concrete-and-glass wall to blow in
on a cafeteria during lunchtime at the East Coldenham Elementary
School near Newburgh. Seven children were killed and 18 injured.
</P>
<P>
There were reports of damage from strong thunderstorms and gusty
winds in eastern Virginia, Maryland, Delaware, New Jersey, eastern
Pennsylvania and eastern New York state. Winds gusted to 65 mph in
Baltimore, 76 mph in Lancaster, Pa., and 100 mph at Great Valley,
Pa.
</P>
<P>
A tornado watch was posted for northeast New York state, much of
Vermont and much of New Hampshire.
</P>
<P>
Thunderstorms also produced locally heavy rain and flooding. A
flood warning was posted over portions of upstate New York. Nearly
two inches of rain fell east of Utica, N.Y., at the Little Falls
Reservoir, which overflowed and caused flooding.
</P>
<P>
Water was eroding the Lyons Pond Dam near Dolgeville, N.Y.,
causing flooding there.
</P>
<P>
Snow was falling west of the cold front. A winter storm warning
was posted for northwest Wisconsin, in the snowbelt near Lake
Superior. Winter storm warnings were posted for much of lower
Michigan, northwestern upper Michigan and north central Indiana.
</P>
<P>
Winds gusted to 63 mph at Whitefish Point, Mi., and near
blizzard conditions extended over eastern upper Michigan.
</P>
<P>
Overnight snowfall across upper Michigan included 12 inches at
Van Riper State Park and 10 inches near Neguanee.
</P>
<P>
Heavier snowfall during the 6 hours ending at 1 p.m. EST
included 4 inches at Houghton Lake, Mich., 3 inches at Marquette,
Pellston, Saginaw and Sault Ste. Marie, all in Michigan, and 2
inches at South Bend, Ind.
</P>
<P>
Heavy snow warnings were posted for the northwest and northern
mountain portions of Pennsylvania. A snow squall warning was posted
for northeast Ohio.
</P>
<P>
Cold weather was expected to invade the Southeast, with warnings
of freezing overnight temperatures posted for Friday morning in
Georgia, Alabama, northwest Florida, most of Mississippi and all
but extreme southeast Louisiana.
</P>
<P>
The low temperature for the nation Thursday morning was 8
degrees below zero at Bismarck, N.D.
</P>
<P>
Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 7
degrees at Fergus Falls, Minn., to 88 degrees at Miami, Fla.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891116-0191
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Southern Tornadoes, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: INSERTS items on Illinois and Ohio, changes death toll to 27
to reflect Illinois death, SUBS West Virginia item to CORRECT location
of Jefferson County.
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here is a state-by-state look at the tornadoes and severe
thunderstorms that have killed at least 27 people, injured more
than 500 and left hundreds homeless since Wednesday:
</P>
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
<P>
_Alabama: Seventeen people were killed in Huntsville on
Wednesday when a tornado touched down just before rush hour,
causing major damage. There were 463 injuries and about 1,000
people left homeless, authorities said. Three people were injured
in an earlier tornado in Clay County in eastern Alabama.
_District of Columbia: Heavy thunderstorms packing 50-60 mph
winds swept through the Washington area during the Thursday morning
rush hour, flooding some streets. About 10,000 customers lost
power, mostly in the Maryland suburbs. No injuries were reported.
_Georgia: 19 people were injured, four critically, and at least
200 people were evacuated Wednesday after a tornado struck two
mobile home parks and an interstate highway near Palmetto, about 25
miles southeast of Atlanta.
_Illinois: Strong winds Wednesday morning destroyed about 15
homes and killed one woman in St. Clair County in southwestern
Illinois. Damage was estimated at $3 million to $5 million.
_Indiana: A tornado was spotted Wednesday afternoon around
Richmond, close to the Ohio border. It ripped the top off a silo
and tipped a semi-trailer into a ditch. The driver was slightly
injured.
_Kentucky: The storm Wednesday left at least 28 people injured;
damage was estimated at $2.5 million or more. A storm believed to
have been a tornado cut a mile-long swath of destruction through
the town of Flaherty in Meade County. Damage was also reported in
Bullitt, LaRue, Hardin and Pendleton counties.
_Maryland, Delaware: Heavy winds on Thursday leveled a church
building in Kent County, Md., lifted roofs from buildings in
Baltimore and cut power to tens of thousands of utility customers,
authorities said. Reports of tornado damage came from Kent County,
Md., and Hockessin, Del. National Weather Service officials were
unable to immediately confirm the reports. No injuries were
reported.
_Mississippi: Scattered damage and power outages were reported
Wednesday after radar showed tornadoes in Neshoba and Kemper
counties in the east-central portion of the state. No injuries were
reported.
_New Jersey: High winds and tornadoes were blamed for one death,
at least four injuries and widespread damage and power outages
Thursday. A tornado touched down in Piscataway shortly after noon,
collapsing on house and damaging 10 to 12 others. One person
suffered a minor injury. A bridge connecting Elizabeth with New
York City was closed after two tractor trailers overturned in heavy
winds; one truck driver died and a passenger was injured. Two minor
injuries were reported in Bergen County.
_New York: A severe thunderstorm Thursday sent a tree crashing
through an elementary school roof in Newburgh, about 60 miles north
of New York City, killing at least seven children and injuring 18,
authorities said. In New York City, a woman was killed by a 12-foot
steel beam that apparently had blown off her apartment's water
tower. Tornadoes were reported in Peekskill, just north of the city.
_North Carolina: A pair of tornadoes were reported Wednesday in
Henderson County, where a vacant house was destroyed. No injuries
were reported.
_Ohio: High winds described by local authorities as a tornado
hopscotched across north-central Ohio on Wednesday, ripping roofs
off barns and houses, destroying farm sheds and damaging trailer
homes. One man was hospitalized from a lightning strike and a woman
was slightly injured by flying debris.
_Pennsylvania: High winds and funnel clouds ripped off roofs and
downed trees in eastern Pennslyvania on Thursday, shattering
windows in Philadelphia skyscrapers. No serious injuries were
reported, but at least 75,000 customers in southeastern
Pennsylvania lost power.
_South Carolina: A tornado Wednesday downed power lines and
damaged 20 houses near Greenwood. No injuries were reported.
_West Virginia: High winds knocked over trees, ripped roofs off
houses and toppled a trailer early Thursday in Jefferson County,
just west of Frederick, Md., injuring four members of one family,
two seriously. The National Weather Service said the storm probably
was a tornado.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891116-0198
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Huntsville Picks Up Pieces One Day After Killer Tornado
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: Fixes paragraphing in 1st 2 grafs; SUBS 2nd graf to raise reference
to Illinois death; SUBS grafs 10-13, `The cafeteria ... Hughes said' with
6 grafs to UPDATE with up to 125 children in school, dead ages 7 to 8,
four injured critically, power outages in Connecticut; picks up 14th graf,
`Tornadoes were ...'
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhotos HUN1,2,3,5,10,13, MFD1, LaserColor HUN10
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A violent storm that spun tornadoes across the South and Midwest
blew north Thursday, knocking a cafeteria wall down on top of
lunching schoolchildren in upstate New York. The two-day toll was
at least 27 dead and hundreds injured.
</P>
<P>
The cafeteria cave-in claimed the lives of seven children near
Newburgh, N.Y., and deaths also were reported in New York City, New
Jersey and Illinois. Seventeen people died Wednesday in Huntsville,
Ala., when a tornado packing 250 mph winds struck virtually without
warning, laying waste to a wide swath of the city.
</P>
<P>
The storm churned around a collision of record warm air and
extremely cold air. The result was tornadoes and unusually severe
thunderstorms.
</P>
<P>
By far the worst damage was in Huntsville, where an estimated
1,000 people were left homeless and National Guardsmen stood watch
against looting Thursday.
</P>
<P>
No bodies were believed left in the rubble, but portions of the
city resembled a bombing target. A shopping center and clusters of
apartment buildings were leveled. Cars were piled atop each other.
</P>
<P>
Utility poles had been snapped like twigs.
</P>
<P>
The National Weather Service said the tornado path had covered
between eight and 10 miles and that its wind speeds were as high as
250 mph.
``It's like taking six to 10 city blocks and putting them in a
blender and putting it on liquefy,'' said rescue worker Bob Caraway.
</P>
<P>
As the storm moved north on Thursday, it knocked over trees and
ripped the the roofs off houses in West Virginia, injuring four
members of one family, two seriously. The storm also caused
flooding in Washington, D.C., blew the windows out of skyscrapers
in Philadelphia and destroyed a house in Piscataway, N.J.
</P>
<P>
A truck driver died when his tractor-trailer overturned in high
winds on a bridge connecting Elizabeth, N.J., and New York City. A
New York City woman died after being hit by a steel beam blown off
a water tower.
</P>
<P>
In Wyckoff, N.J., high winds knocked a power line onto a gas
line, sparking a fire that forced the evacuation of 20 homes,
according to police. No houses were burned.
</P>
<P>
The cafeteria collapse occurred at the East Coldenham Elementary
School in Newburgh at about 12:30 p.m., when from 113 to 125
students in first, second and third grades were eating lunch, said
Newburgh police Chief John Kulisek.
</P>
<P>
State Police and survivors said they believed the school was hit
by a tornado, but the National Weather Service said it could not
confirm that until investigators went to the scene.
</P>
<P>
The center section of a cinder-block and glass wall fell in on
the cafeteria, showering the pupils with glass and concrete.
``You are talking about huge concrete blocks that fell on top of
the kids,'' state police Lt. Robert Hughes said.
</P>
<P>
Seven children ages 7 and 8 were killed and 18 others were
injured, four critically, officials said.
</P>
<P>
In eastern Connecticut, more than 75,000 Northeast Utilities
customers lost power in the afternoon, and 18,000 remained without
power at 9 p.m., spokeman Jeffery Kotkin said.
</P>
<P>
Tornadoes were reported Wednesday in Mississippi, Alabama,
Georgia, South Carolina, North Carolina, Kentucky, Ohio and
Indiana. A severe thunderstorm in Illinois claimed one life and
caused several million dollars in damage.
</P>
<P>
Altogether, the storms were blamed for at least 27 deaths and
more than 500 injuries over the two days.
</P>
<P>
In Alabama, Gov. Guy Hunt said he would ask President Bush to
declare Huntsville a disaster area to open the door to millions of
dollars in federal relief. Mayor Steve Hettinger said no firm
damage estimates were expected until Friday, but he put the number
of homeless at 1,000.
</P>
<P>
Hunt assigned nearly 200 Guardsmen to assist in the cleanup and
help law officers guard against looting. Police spokeswoman Susan
Williamson said there had been minor looting the night of the storm
but no arrests.
</P>
<P>
The temperature, which had risen to 73 before the storm
Wednesday, plunged into the 30s early Thursday while rescuers
worked through the night under the glare of floodlights.
</P>
<P>
The lights, powered by generators, produced an eerie glow in a
area that was otherwise largely without power. Tall cranes lifted
the heavy rubble, while workers with flashlights picked through the
smaller pieces.
</P>
<P>
As daybreak came, people began returning to the scene, some to
look for valuables in ravaged cars or businesses, others simply out
of curiosity. Many carried cameras or videocassette recorders.
</P>
<P>
Police Maj. Robert Moder said there was no indication that
anyone was left in the rubble.
``We don't have any reports of people missing,'' he said
Thursday morning.
</P>
<P>
Moder said 463 people were injured and more than 150 of those
required at least overnight hospital treatment. Authorities had
said 19 people were killed but later lowered the death toll by two.
</P>
<P>
All but one of the victims, who ranged in age from 7 to 67, were
killed along Airport Boulevard, a busy thoroughfare that seemed to
be a guide for the tornado on its deadly march. The other victim
perished on the city's outskirts, authorities said.
</P>
<P>
Most of the dead were in apartments and stores that were torn
into twisted wreckage, or in cars blown off the pavement.
</P>
<P>
The tornado seemed to catch everyone by surprise.
``It was fast,'' said Lucy Lee Rusk, who moved to a Red Cross
shelter after her apartment was battered by debris. ``It was like
one big pop and that's when everything went.''
The National Weather Service had issued a severe thunderstorm
warning at 3:54 p.m., but the tornado struck with no real warning,
said Brenda Page of the service's office. A tornado warning was
broadcast at 4:39 p.m., two minutes after the twister was sighted
on the ground at the old Huntsville airport.
</P>
<P>
Ms. Page said radar showed a strong storm but not the conditions
usually visible during tornadoes.
</P>
<P>
Danny Cooper, director of the Alabama Emergency Management
Agency, said three people were seriously injured in an earlier
tornado that hit a home in Clay County in eastern Alabama. He said
a tornado in northwestern Alabama's Lauderdale County destroyed
three homes.
</P>
<P>
Alabama Power Co. reported Thursday that violent winds had
battered the switchyard of the Farley Nuclear Power Plant near
Dothan on Wednesday night, causing about three gallons of
concentrated PCBs to spill. A spokesman said no one was injured,
the nuclear plant was not affected and a cleanup of the
cancer-causing chemicals was under way.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA111689-0160
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
ALABAMA TORNADO KILLS 14; 300 INJURED; OTHERS TRAPPED 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
HUNTSVILLE, Ala. 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A tornado slammed into a shopping district, a residential area and a school 
Wednesday, killing at least 14 people, injuring nearly 300 and trapping many 
others in their cars and homes, police said. 
</P>
<P>
"Several people are still trapped in vehicles and apartment complexes and 
shopping areas," said police spokesman Ben Jennings after the twister touched 
down between 4 and 4:30 p.m. in this northeastern Alabama city. 
</P>
<P>
Mayor Steve Hettinger said 14 deaths had been confirmed, with 285 people 
injured and about 500 displaced by the tornado that struck while city streets 
were filled with rush-hour traffic. 
</P>
<P>
Gov. Guy Hunt, at the state's disaster center in Montgomery, said rescue teams 
with cranes and floodlights would search the rubble through the night for 
injured or dead. "It may be tomorrow before we have a final count," he said. 
</P>
<P>
The governor said 50 National Guard troops were dispatched to the city, along 
with search and rescue equipment. 
</P>
<P>
Witnesses said the downtown Jones Valley Elementary School, the Waterford 
Square and adjacent Queensbury apartment complexes were reduced to rubble by 
the tornado. 
</P>
<P>
"The only thing left standing was a door frame," news photographer Mike Mercier 
said of the school, which was empty of staff and pupils when the tornado hit. 
Police reported one person killed in a car outside the school. 
</P>
<P>
Authorities said at least five were killed at Waterford Square apartments, 
three at a business school, Southern Junior College, which is located in a 
converted movie theater, and others in scattered areas. 
</P>
<P>
"Rescuers are digging in the rubble," state trooper W. L. Kelly said. He said 
two people were killed when the twister hit house trailers in rural areas east 
of Huntsville. The fifth death was reported near the shopping district. 
</P>
<P>
"We've called in troopers from around the state to help," Kelly said. 
</P>
<P>
The city is home to Marshall Space Flight Center and the Army's Redstone 
Arsenal, but no serious damage was reported from the space agency or weapons 
testing center. 
</P>
<P>
Telephone communication and electricity were disrupted by the tornadoes and 
WAAY-TV, the only station still broadcasting, reported widespread damage. 
</P>
<P>
"It came in with a huge roar, an enormous amount of water, and it just started 
shaking and tearing at everything it could get hold of," said real estate 
broker Ike Carroll, who was in his car when the twister struck. 
</P>
<P>
"It started picking cars up and pushing them around . . . some of them upside 
down, some of them just strewn around," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Heavy overhead power lines "started snapping just like a circus performer would 
snap his whip," Carroll said. 
</P>
<P>
"All of these heavy arcing, flashing lines that were just popping and snapping 
over the top of us . . . it was as if you were looking into an arc-welder, they 
were so bright," he said. 
</P>
<P>
WAAY reported at least one person died when the roof of a business collapsed 
from winds that overturned cars in the area. A nearby shopping center also was 
damaged. 
</P>
<P>
Humana Hospital administrator David Miller said doctors were having difficulty 
reaching the hospital because of blocked roads. 
</P>
<P>
The National Weather Service earlier said a tornado hit the east Alabama hamlet 
of Mellow Valley, severely damaging at least one home and causing some 
injuries. Weather officials said people were trapped inside a collapsed house. 
</P>
<P>
A spokeswoman for the Clay County Sheriff's Department said people were injured 
at one house in a rural area 30 miles east of Sylacauga. 
</P>
<P>
Another tornado touched down about 1:30 p.m. as severe weather swept across 
much of Alabama and the National Weather Service placed most of the state under 
a tornado watch. 
</P>
<P>
In Georgia, five people were injured, four critically, after a tornado struck 
two mobile home parks and an interstate highway near Palmetto. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
TORNADOES; STORMS - ALABAMA; CASUALTIES; DISASTERS - ALABAMA; DISASTER 
VICTIMS 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
