<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900621-0186
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>21
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Iran Earthquake Caught Victims Asleep in Fragile Homes
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The earthquake that devastated Iran early
Thursday took tens of thousands of lives because people were asleep
in fragile homes built on flood plains, an earthquake expert said.
``Most casualties from earthquakes are caused by something
falling on top of you,'' said Russ Needham, a geophysist with the
U.S. Geological Survey that monitors ground motion around the world.
</P>
<P>
The quake hit at 12:30 a.m. in Iran, when most of the people
were in their homes, Needham said Thursday in a telephone interview
from Golden, Colo.
</P>
<P>
At least 25,000 people died and thousands were injured in the
quake, which demolished scores of villages and buried thousands of
people in the rubble of their homes, Iranian officials said.
</P>
<P>
Needham said most structures in that area are built of a
ceramic-type brick or adobe that collapses easily.
``It's very similar to what we had in Armenia,'' he said of the
Dec. 7, 1988, earthquake that killed about 25,000 people.
</P>
<P>
A Soviet parliamentary report later blamed the high number of
fatalities on shoddily built buildings.
</P>
<P>
The Armenian quake was measured at 6.9 on the Richter scale, but
Thursday's earthquake shook the earth with a magnitude of 7.7.
</P>
<P>
The shock wave traveled through the mountainous section of
coastal Iran where most of the buildings are built on a flood plain
of loosely deposited soil that shifts in an earthquake and allows
structures to collapse, he said.
</P>
<P>
The 7.7-magnitude quake was the largest ever recorded in that
area, where two major plates of the earth's crust meet, Needhams
said.
``Iran is in a very active seismic region,'' he said, and that
there have been many smaller quakes.
</P>
<P>
Twelve earthquakes greater than magnitude 7 have occurred in
Iran during the last 30 years, Needhams said.
</P>
<P>
A quake of magnitude 7 is considered a major earthquake, capable
of widespread, heavy damage in populated areas.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900622-0025
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Iran Earthquake Caught Victims Asleep in Fragile Homes
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The earthquake that struck northern Iran brought
reminders of another quake that devastated Soviet Armenia in 1988.
</P>
<P>
Like Thursday's earthquake in Iran, the Dec. 7, 1988, earthquake
in Armenia killed about 25,000 people. Most died in structures that
collapsed when the quake hit.
``It's very similar to what we had in Armenia,'' said Russ
Needham, a geophysicist with the U.S. Geological Survey.
</P>
<P>
The Armenian quake was measured at 6.9 on the Richter scale, but
Thursday's earthquake shook the earth with a magnitude of 7.7
according to the U.S. Geological Survey.
</P>
<P>
In the Iranian quake, the casualty count was pushed up by the
fact that people were indoors and asleep at the time, just after
midnight. Many of the victims lived in fragile homes built of a
ceramic-type brick or adobe that collapses easily.
</P>
<P>
In the Armenian quake, a Soviet parliamentary report later
blamed the high number of fatalities on shoddily built buildings.
``Most casualties from earthquakes are caused by something
falling on top of you,'' said Needham in a telephone interview from
Golden, Colo.
</P>
<P>
The quake struck an area of Iran where most of the buildings are
built on a flood plain of loosely deposited soil that shifts in an
earthquake and allows structures to collapse, Needham said.
</P>
<P>
The 7.7-magnitude quake was the largest ever recorded in that
area, where two major plates of the earth's crust meet, he said.
``Iran is in a very active seismic region,'' he said, and that
there have been many smaller quakes.
</P>
<P>
Twelve earthquakes greater than magnitude 7 have occurred in
Iran during the last 30 years, Needham said.
</P>
<P>
A quake of magnitude 7 is considered a major earthquake, capable
of widespread, heavy damage in populated areas.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900623-0022
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Group Claims Iran Underreporting Earthquake Casualties
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iran-Quake
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhoto WX21 of June 22
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iran is deliberately underreporting the number
of casualties from Thursday's massive earthquake out of fear of a
political backlash, leaders of a group seeking to overthrow the
country's Islamic leadership say.
``The regime is very much fearful of public outrage,'' said
Shahin Gobadi, spokesman for the People's Mojahedin of Iran.
``They're very much afraid of the political aftershocks.''
As Gobadi spoke Friday, members of the organization denounced
Iran's government at a noisy rally held in a park across the street
from the White House.
</P>
<P>
Northern Iran was stuck Thursday by an earthquake measuring
between 7.3 and 7.7 on the Richter Scale. Iran has told the United
Nations that the death toll is at least 36,000, but Gobadi said his
organization has received estimates closer to 100,000.
</P>
<P>
Gobadi said the country cannot properly assist earthquake
victims because its treasury has been spent in a war with
neighboring Iraq and against internal opposition.
``They have been very late in assisting the people,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Sympathy for the earthquake victims was a secondary issue for
the chanting, flag-waving rally participants, who also carried
signs criticizing their native country.
</P>
<P>
Planning for the event began three weeks before the earthquake,
but part of the Friday's activities focused on Iran's stricken
residents.
</P>
<P>
Gobadi said shoddy housing in which the government forced people
to live was the cause for the widespread loss of life.
``This regime has brought them nothing but devastation and
misery. This regime has devoted all of its resources to a senseless
war with Iraq and to oppression of the people at home,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
A U.N.-sponsored cease-fire was declared last year after eight
years of the Iran-Iraq war.
</P>
<P>
Iran's Islamic republic was established in 1979 after Shah
Mohammad Reza Pahlavi was deposed by Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini
and militants seized the U.S. Embassy in Tehran, taking 66
Americans hostage.
</P>
<P>
The United States broke diplomatic relations with Iran in April
1980. The shah died in exile in July 1980, U.S. hostages were freed
six months later and Khomeini died last June.
</P>
<P>
Gobadi said his 25-year-old group had helped depose the shah but
had no part in organizing the Islamic republic.
``Even in this tragedy for which we grieve we cannot trust the
regime in Iran,'' Rep. Mervyn Dymally, D-Calif., told an estimated
3,000 people attending the rally.
``There were many, many victims before this tragedy and there
are victims now whose needs need to be addressed by the people of
the United States,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Dymally, a member of the House Foreign Affairs Committee,
praised President Bush's offer of humanitarian aid to Iran but said
Bush must make sure the assistance is channeled through
non-government groups.
</P>
<P>
The State Department said Friday that Iran was willing to accept
earthquake relief from the American Red Cross and other U.S.
humanitarian organizations.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900624-0011
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>24
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Radical Paper Blames U.S., In Part, For Quake Damage
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>TEHRAN, Iran (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An anti-American newspaper in Iran said
Sunday the United States is partly to blame for the death of tens
of thousands of people in last week's earthquake.
</P>
<P>
The ``criminal role of America in Iran's past became evident
once again in the recent earthquake,'' the Jomhuri Islami said in
an editorial reported by the official Islamic Republic News Agency.
``Our people, even under the rubble, chant `Death to America'
and pray to God to cut off the hands of the United States ... even
those hands stretched out to help,'' it said.
</P>
<P>
It argued that by ``plundering Iran's oil and other resources''
for 25 years, the United States had prevented the use of even a
small part of the national wealth for urban development projects
and ``advanced (anti-seismic) building construction systems.''
``Even after its expulsion from Iran, the U.S. government by
imposing economic sanctions and launching several other plots,
halted the renovation of the country,'' the editorial added.
</P>
<P>
The newspaper was implying that with these actions the United
States had blocked the diversion of funds to earthquake safety
measures.
``If the United States has real humanitarian objectives and
intended to help the Iranian nation, it should do only one thing,
stop hatching plots,'' the newspaper said.
</P>
<P>
It called on Iranians to reject relief offers by the United
States and ``other governments whose hands are stained with the
blood of the Iranian people.''
Iran, at odds with the United States since the 1979 seizure of
hostages at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran, has said it would welcome
relief from the American Red Cross and other U.S. humanitarian
groups. The two nations have no diplomatic ties.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900625-0036
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>25
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Tons of Relief Supplies Arriving, But Distribution Difficult
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>TEHRAN, Iran (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Planes loaded with food, medicine and tents
are converging on earthquake-stricken Iran from around the world,
among them the first private American relief mission to the country
in more than a decade.
</P>
<P>
Authorities now are faced with the difficult task of getting
supplies into the affected areas. More than 60 aftershocks jolted
the quake zone in northwestern Iran on Sunday, triggering
landslides along one key relief route.
</P>
<P>
Tehran radio said Sunday that 68 relief aircraft had landed at
Tehran's Mehrabad airport during a 24-hour period. Among them was a
plane carrying medicine and other supplies from the United States.
</P>
<P>
Another plane carrying U.S. government aid was due today.
</P>
<P>
The shipment that arrived Sunday was the first of its kind to be
accepted by Iran since the hostage crisis of 1979-80, when 52
Americans were held at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran.
</P>
<P>
Two countries that also have suffered devastating earthquakes in
recent years, the Soviet Union and Mexico, were among those sending
assistance to help victims of Thursday's quake.
</P>
<P>
Leaders of Iran's Arab neighbors, including Iraq, which waged an
eight-year war with Iran, issued statements of sympathy and support.
</P>
<P>
Pope John Paul II called on the international community to help
earthquake victims, asking for ``a real and generous demonstration
of solidarity with our brothers. Let us pray that their suffering
is alleviated.''
The Vatican was among the many international donors.
</P>
<P>
Eleven planes from West Germany ferried in 145 tons of supplies
plus a field hospital with two medical teams. Nine flights arrived
from Turkey. The Spanish Red Cross sent medicines and food; India
sent medicine. The Austrian Red Cross shipped tents, blankets and
medicine.
</P>
<P>
Bernard Kouchner, the French secretary of state for humanitarian
action, arrived in Iran on Sunday to coordinate French assistance
and evaluate future needs, Radio France Inter said. The French
government has sent a civil defense team of 195 people and 18
search dogs along with at least 24 tons of equipment. The
Saudi-based 46-member Organization of the Islamic Conference, an
umbrella organization for the world's estimated one billion
Moslems, issued an ``urgent appeal to the international community
and especially Islamic countries and organizations to hasten with
emergency aid for the Iranians ...''
AmeriCares, a private U.S. relief organization based in New
Canaan, Conn., flew in the 42 tons pounds of supplies that arrived
Sunday.
``To be on the ground here in Tehran is a very special feeeling
for us,'' said Stephen M. Johnson, president of AmeriCares.
</P>
<P>
A spokeswoman for the U.S. Agency for International Development
said a Red Cross charter flight carrying $225,000 worth of supplies
donated by the U.S. government would arrive in Tehran this morning.
</P>
<P>
Iran is believed to have influence with the Shiite Moslem
extremists holding 16 Western hostages, including six Americans, in
Lebanon. The longest-held is Terry Anderson, chief Middle East
correspondent of The Associated Press. He was kidnapped March 16,
1985.
</P>
<P>
The Soviet Union sent in medical teams and supplies from Soviet
republics bordering Iran. More than 200 medical personnel arrived
from the Soviet Union, which also sent medical supplies, trucks,
trailers, ambulances, cranes, buses and water tankers.
</P>
<P>
The December 1988 earthquake in Soviet Armenia left at least
25,000 people dead. Mexico, which lost at least 10,000 people in a
1985 earthquake, is sending food, medical supplies and blankets,
officials said Sunday.
</P>
<P>
In Lebanon, the Iranian-backed Hezbollah, or Party of God, said
its members were donating 10 percent of their salaries to help the
victims. That would amount to about $500,000, according to
Hezbollah sources, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900626-0010
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Contributions for Iranian Relief Light, Expected to Pick Up
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Americans who rushed to donate money to help victims of the
Armenian earthquake 18 months ago are responding more slowly to
last week's killer earthquake in Iran. But relief agencies said
they expect contributions to pick up.
``There's a hierarchy of responsiveness,'' said Dick Colenso,
associate executive director of World Concern, a private relief
agency based in Seattle. ``Something happens in Europe, there's a
very large response, Asia, a pretty good respons
down to the Middle East ... thee. When you get dynamics change.''
Colenso said, however, that contributions will ``surge upward''
as news spreads of the earthquake's destruction.
``As ... you get the disaster translated into the lives of
individuals instead of mass numbers, people begin to respond. They
relate to that,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
At least 50,000 people were reported killed and 200,000 injured
in the earthquake that struck Thursday.
</P>
<P>
AmeriCares, a private agency based in New Canaan, Conn., brought
the first shipment of supplies from the United States into Iran on
Sunday.
</P>
<P>
The shipment was the first of its kind to be accepted by Iran
since the hostage crisis of 1979-80, when 52 Americans were held at
the U.S. Embassy in Tehran. Iran is believede-scale structure in the universe.
</P>
<P>
AWARDS: National Award for Science and Technology, 1978; Chinese
Academy of Sciences Award 1982; New York Academy of Sciences Award,
1988.
</P>
<P>
POLITICAL DISSENT: Fang became politically prominent during the
pro-democracy student demonstrations of 1986-87. His speeches to
students at the University of Science and Technology in Hefei in
central China, where he was vice president, helped incite the
protests, party hard-liners said.
</P>
<P>
Fang was expelled from the Communist Party in 1957, when he said
Marxist theory on physics was obsolete. In 1987, he was fired from
his Hefei university posts. In between, in 1966, he was a victim of
the Cultural Revolution purges and was sent to a communal farm for
``re-education.''
After the June 4, 1989, military crackdown on the democracy
movement, Fang and Li obtained refuge in the U.S. Embassy.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA062290-0134
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
IRANIAN MEDIA LOW KEY IN REPORTING ON KILLER QUAKE 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
NICOSIA, Cyprus 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iranian news media reacted with little emotion Thursday to a killer earthquake 
that left an estimated 25,000 people dead in northern Iran. 
</P>
<P>
The country has endured several massive tragedies in recent years. An estimated 
1 million Iranians were killed or wounded in the eight-year war with Iraq that 
ended in 1988. And the Islamic revolution that in 1979 toppled the late Shah 
Mohammed Reza Pahlavi cost hundreds of thousands of lives. 
</P>
<P>
And devastating quakes are not new to the country. About 25,000 people died in 
eastern Iran in a 1978 earthquake. Roughly the same number died in a December, 
1988, quake in nearby Soviet Armenia. 
</P>
<P>
The Iranian media, monitored from Nicosia, was quick to report Thursday's 
earthquake. Within half an hour, the Islamic Republic News Agency reported that 
the tremor had been felt in Tehran, the capital. 
</P>
<P>
But subsequent reports, some a few minutes apart, said the damage must have 
been principally to crops, with brief mentions that many casualties were feared 
in Zanjan and Gilan provinces. 
</P>
<P>
The only detail reported for hours was that, when the quake hit, Tehran 
residents were either asleep or watching a World Cup soccer match between 
Brazil and Scotland. The report said that many people fled into the streets. 
</P>
<P>
In addition, the news agency's earliest reports dramatically underestimated the 
magnitude of the disaster. While IRNA reported 10,000 dead late Thursday, the 
Iranian ambassador to the United Nations said 25,000 people had died. 
</P>
<P>
Official radio was off the air when the earthquake struck, and although it came 
back on the air to report important news during the Iran-Iraq War, there was no 
such move Thursday. Iranian radio first reported the earthquake on the main 
newscast 6 1/2 hours later. 
</P>
<P>
The radio, like the agency, also kept listeners informed about the areas hit 
and the number of casualties. But again, the reporting lacked color and 
description for hours. 
</P>
<P>
The television's first shots from the stricken north were screened 12 hours 
after the quake with no comment from reporters. When the scenes were replayed 
during newscasts, the anchors appeared unshaken by chilling clips such as one 
showing a stuffed toy and a small shoe lying in a street carpeted with debris. 
</P>
<P>
Iranian President Hashemi Rafsanjani declared a three-day period of mourning 
for quake victims. But the television showed cartoons and an educational 
program for children and ended its programming with live transmission of a 
World Cup soccer match between Egypt and England. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA062290-0169
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
IRAN ACCEPTS U.S. HELP; 
EARTHQUAKE DEATH TOLL HITS 35,000 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iran said today that it would welcome relief offered by its bitter enemy, the 
United States, to help victims of the earthquake that has killed as many as 
35,000 people, the State Department said in Washington. 
</P>
<P>
The aid would be accepted through the American Red Cross and other U.S. 
humanitarian organizations, deputy spokesman Richard Boucher said. 
</P>
<P>
"We want to be helpful without regard for our political differences with Iran," 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
There have been only rare instances of U.S.-Iranian cooperation since the two 
countries broke diplomatic relations a decade ago. The United States holds Iran 
partly responsible for the continued detention of American hostages by 
pro-Iranian groups in Lebanon. 
</P>
<P>
Boucher said Iran told the U.S. government that private donor agencies should 
contact the Iranian Red Crescent, a humanitarian group that is the conduit for 
all outside assistance. 
</P>
<P>
The U.S. government routinely channels humanitarian assistance through the Red 
Cross and other donor groups. 
</P>
<P>
Boucher said the Iranian message to the United States presumably was delivered 
through a third party but added that he was uncertain. Messages between the two 
countries normally are handled by the Swiss Embassy in Tehran. 
</P>
<P>
Iranian authorities have told United Nations officials that about 35,000 people 
died in the earthquake. 
</P>
<P>
Iran reportedly said it would accept aid from all countries - including Iraq 
- but excluded Israel and South Africa. 
</P>
<P>
Rescuers in Iran today freed thousands of people from buildings flattened by 
the earthquake in northern Iran, which struck early Thursday and had a 
magnitude between 7.3 and 7.7. 
</P>
<P>
The Islamic Republic News Agency said 6,000 people were pulled from rubble and 
airlifted from the stricken Gilan and Zanjan provinces to hospitals. 
</P>
<P>
Iranian television showed scenes of devastation, including the remains of an 
entire row of hillside village houses that collapsed and slid down the hill. 
</P>
<P>
Rescuers scooped up rubble and used police dogs to find victims. They gently 
fed water to one man who was trapped in a mass of stones and earth, only his 
head protruding. 
</P>
<P>
The Iranian Red Crescent asked for help in providing shelter for 400,000 people 
left homeless by the earthquake. Offers of help came from across the globe. 
</P>
<P>
The death toll was higher than a quake that killed 25,000 people in nearby 
Soviet Armenia in December, 1988, and a quake in Iran in 1978 that also killed 
25,000. 
</P>
<P>
In scenes shown on television, masked rescuers in white aprons pulled 
dust-covered bodies from under concrete slabs. Corpses were laid on blocks of 
ice in open trucks. 
</P>
<P>
The state-run television interviewed one middle-aged man from Roodbar, a 
mountainside village in Gilan province, who said he was sleeping when the 
temblor struck. 
</P>
<P>
"It was so strong," he said. "I was thrown several meters, I ended up by the 
olive trees," outside his home. "Then a big boulder hit the house. The house 
collapsed. I lost all four of my children." 
</P>
<P>
* Photos of Iran's devastating earthquake. See Back Page 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA062390-0068
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
U.S. PUTS RANCOR ASIDE, AIDS QUAKE RELIEF EFFORT; 
ASSISTANCE: WASHINGTON GIVES $300,000 WORTH OF SUPPLIES TO THE AMERICAN RED 
CROSS FOR SHIPMENT TO IRAN. 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
WASHINGTON 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Setting aside years of animosity, the U.S. government joined with private 
humanitarian groups Friday to funnel medicine, tents, clothing, food and other 
relief materials to help earthquake-stricken Iran. 
</P>
<P>
State Department officials said the government gave $300,000 worth of supplies 
to the American Red Cross for shipment to Iran - including 1,000 hard hats, 
1,000 pairs of leather gloves, 10,000 face masks, 2,940 wool blankets and about 
500 tents. 
</P>
<P>
The U.S. military, which often is used to ferry relief supplies to countries in 
need, stood ready to offer transport planes and logistics support for any U.S. 
aid requested by Iran. However, a Pentagon official said it is unlikely that 
the State Department and the White House would authorize a military airlift of 
supplies. 
</P>
<P>
"It's pretty clear that the Iranians don't want us, and there are so many 
alternatives, such as private charters, it really isn't necessary," the 
officials said. "In a case like this, we would really be more of an irritant 
than a help." 
</P>
<P>
The quake, which rocked the northern region of Iran early Thursday, left nearly 
29,000 dead, by official count, and about 400,000 homeless. The death toll is 
expected to rise, however, as rescuers continue work. 
</P>
<P>
Late Thursday, the Iranian Red Crescent appealed for help from the Red Cross 
and Red Crescent Society, a Geneva-based umbrella for international 
humanitarian organizations. Iranian President Hashemi Rafsanjani, who toured 
the stricken region Friday, also appealed for international aid. 
</P>
<P>
Pat Davis, a spokesman for the American Red Cross in Washington, said Friday 
that although the Red Crescent is highly organized and well equipped, the large 
number of dead and suffering people has forced the Iranian agency to solicit 
international assistance. 
</P>
<P>
The American Red Cross responded by mobilizing its local offices to solicit 
money, informing its toll-free telephone operators to request earmarked 
donations for the earthquake victims and sending $50,000 in cash to the Red 
Crescent Society to be used to help needy Iranians. 
</P>
<P>
Some Jewish relief organizations found themselves in an uncomfortable position 
because of Iran's hostility toward the United States and Israel. Confronted 
with reports that Iran would not welcome assistance from Israel, the groups 
were uncertain whether they should offer any assistance. 
</P>
<P>
Andy Griffel, executive director of American Jewish World Service, said 
directors of the assistance organization participated in a conference call 
Friday morning to debate whether to collect money for the Iranian victims. 
</P>
<P>
After a spirited discussion, the group decided to help but to monitor the 
situation closely and to be prepared to change their decision. 
</P>
<P>
"We're a humanitarian organization . . . without regard to political 
considerations," Griffel said. "But if they are going politicize it, we will 
definitely reconsider our participation." 
</P>
<P>
Amir Zamani, a spokesman for the Iranian mission at the United Nations, 
welcomed the "many offers from many organizations" that his office has 
received. 
</P>
<P>
"Iran needs assistance, and such organizations are welcome to send it." 
</P>
<P>
Acknowledging Iran's strained relations with many nations, Zamani said his 
country is attempting to ease the antagonism to deal with the disaster in the 
country. As an example, he said "no formalities" will be required for relief 
planes flying into Iran. 
</P>
<P>
He added, however, that aid shipments will be coordinated by the government and 
routed through Tehran because there are no other airports in the country that 
can accommodate large transport planes. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, other U.S. groups were rushing to supply Iran with emergency goods. 
</P>
<P>
Dwain Schenck, a relief worker for AmeriCares Foundation, said the 
Connecticut-based relief group expects to send 80,000 pounds of medical 
supplies, two doctors, a nurse and about half a dozen relief workers to Iran 
today. 
</P>
<P>
"We hope to be there about four days or so," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Times staff writer Charles J. Hartley contributed to this report. 
</P>
<P>
WHERE TO SEND AID 
</P>
<P>
 Here are some of the agencies accepting donations for Iranian earthquake 
victims: 
</P>
<P>
Adventist Development and Relief Agency 
</P>
<P>
12501 Old Columbia Pike 
</P>
<P>
Silver Spring, Md. 20904 
</P>
<P>
(301) 680-6380 
</P>
<P>
American Jewish World Service 
</P>
<P>
1290 Avenue of the Americas, 11th Floor 
</P>
<P>
New York, N.Y. 10104 
</P>
<P>
American Red Cross 
</P>
<P>
Iran Earthquake Disaster 
</P>
<P>
P.O. Box 37243 
</P>
<P>
Washington, D.C. 20013 
</P>
<P>
(800) 842-2200 
</P>
<P>
American Red Cross (local) 
</P>
<P>
2700 Wilshire Blvd., 
</P>
<P>
Los Angeles, Calif. 90057 
</P>
<P>
AmeriCares 
</P>
<P>
161 Cherry St. 
</P>
<P>
New Canaan, Conn. 06840 
</P>
<P>
(800) 486-HELP 
</P>
<P>
Baptist World Alliance 
</P>
<P>
Iran Earthquake Fund 
</P>
<P>
6733 Curran St. 
</P>
<P>
McLean, Va. 22101 
</P>
<P>
Direct Relief International 
</P>
<P>
2801-B De La Vina St. 
</P>
<P>
Santa Barbara, Calif. 93105 
</P>
<P>
(805) 687-3694 
</P>
<P>
Bank Melli Iran 
</P>
<P>
Iran Quake Relief Assistance 
</P>
<P>
Account No. 5000 
</P>
<P>
628 Madison Ave. 
</P>
<P>
New York, N.Y. 10022 
</P>
<P>
Bank Melli Iran (local) 
</P>
<P>
818 Wilshire Blvd. 
</P>
<P>
Los Angeles, Calif. 90017) 
</P>
<P>
Lutheran World Relief 
</P>
<P>
390 Park Ave. S 
</P>
<P>
New York, N.Y. 10016 
</P>
<P>
U.S. Committee for UNICEF 
</P>
<P>
333 E. 38th St. 
</P>
<P>
New York, N.Y. 10016 
</P>
<P>
(212) 686-5522 
</P>
<P>
World Concern 
</P>
<P>
P.O. Box 33000 
</P>
<P>
Seattle, Wash. 98133 
</P>
<P>
World Vision 
</P>
<P>
919 W. Huntington Drive 
</P>
<P>
Monrovia, Calif. 91016 
</P>
<P>
(818) 357-7979 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
AMERICAN RED CROSS; RELIEF ORGANIZATIONS; UNITED STATES - FOREIGN RELATIONS - 
IRAN; CONTRIBUTIONS; EARTHQUAKES - IRAN; DISASTERS - IRAN; IRAN - RELIEF; 
DISASTER RELIEF 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA062590-0096
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>25
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
COUNTY'S IRANIANS OFFER AID IN QUAKE; 
RESCUE: MONEY, MEDICINE AND MEANS OF SHELTER ARE BEING COLLECTED FOR THE 
THOUSANDS OF INJURED AND HOMELESS BY PROFESSIONAL AND COMMUNITY GROUPS. 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
IRVINE 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Orange County's Iranian community launched an ambitious effort Sunday to 
collect half a million dollars in money, medicine, tents, blankets and sleeping 
bags for hundreds of thousands of injured and homeless people in 
earthquake-ravaged Iran. 
</P>
<P>
Representatives of 11 Iranian professional and community groups manned tables 
near William R. Mason Regional Park, where contributors dropped off supplies, 
pledged other aid or made financial contributions. 
</P>
<P>
Organizers said they hope to raise at least $500,000 in donations. 
</P>
<P>
"We'll do this as long as it takes," said organizer Bijan Kian. "We will be 
back here again next Sunday. I have been in contact with a group that raised 
$150,000 (Saturday) by telephoning from home to home. This is from their 
friends and relatives. I'm sure we can double and triple that." 
</P>
<P>
The 50 organizers Sunday wore black armbands expressing their grief for those 
killed, injured and left homeless in what they described as that country's 
worst earthquake of the century. 
</P>
<P>
In Iran, rescue efforts were hampered Sunday as the strongest aftershock yet 
jarred the already severely damaged rice-growing region of Rasht, 120 miles 
northwest of Tehran. The new shock, with a magnitude of 5.7, toppled the few 
still-standing structures and caused mudslides that temporarily closed the road 
linking Rasht with other destruction zones in Zanjan province. 
</P>
<P>
Estimates of the number killed in the devastating quake reached 50,000, with an 
additional 200,000 injured. 
</P>
<P>
Army mountaineers climbed rugged mountains Sunday in an effort to rescue 
villagers trapped in remote hamlets in the ravaged northern provinces. 
</P>
<P>
"They have no water or electricity," said Farrokh Shokooh, another organizer of 
the Sunday fund-raiser. "Everything is made that much more difficult because it 
is the rainy season." 
</P>
<P>
Shokooh said the effort to help the earthquake victims was put together hastily 
Friday afternoon. 
</P>
<P>
The group set up the collection point in front of William R. Mason Regional 
Park on property belonging to the City of Irvine. 
</P>
<P>
Irvine Police Sgt. Tom Hume, who is in charge of policing special events held 
in the city, said the group failed to obtain a permit from the city. But police 
accommodated the group, blocking off a bike lane on University Avenue so cars 
could pull in and unload supplies for the earthquake victims. The supplies were 
put into a large truck parked along the road. 
</P>
<P>
Hume said that two officers assigned to the event reported the crowd as small. 
</P>
<P>
Organizer Genia Panahi, 40, of Newport Beach, said the 150 Iranian doctors 
practicing in Orange County responded to calls for medicine, surgical gloves, 
disposable needles and blood bags. Organizers said between 60,000 and 80,000 
Iranians live in Orange County. 
</P>
<P>
"Medicine is in such a short supply over there," said Panahi, who along with 
her husband is a medical doctor. "Doctors are being asked to donate needles, 
gloves and antibiotics." 
</P>
<P>
Her 17-year-old son, Homan, and his friend Sepehr Khonsari worked throughout 
the day Saturday collecting medical supplies from doctors' offices throughout 
the county. 
</P>
<P>
The group - the Orange County Committee for Iran Earthquake Relief - has set 
up a special account at Capital Bank in Santa Ana. Checks can be made out to 
the Iran Earthquake Fund and mailed to the bank at 400 N. Tustin Ave. Blankets, 
tents and sleeping bags can be delivered to the Iranian Cultural Center at 8361 
Westminster Blvd., Suite 220, in Westminster. 
</P>
<P>
Kian said money sent to the special Capital Bank account will be turned over to 
the Red Cross for distribution in Iran. 
</P>
<P>
Red Cross representative Sylvia Stewart said the Red Cross will accept only 
monetary contributions because shipping supplies there is very expensive. She 
said sending money and allowing the supplies to be purchased there "helps 
stimulate the economy." She said the donations are sent to the national Red 
Cross and then to the international organization. 
</P>
<P>
The Iranian Student Assn. at California State Fullerton has set up a booth in 
Parking Lot C near State College Boulevard and Nutwood Avenue. The donations 
will be forwarded to the Red Cross or they may be sent directly to the Red 
Cross, P.O. Box 11364, Santa Ana, CA. 92711-1364. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
EARTHQUAKES - IRAN; IRAN - RELIEF; DISASTERS - IRAN; DISASTER RELIEF; 
IRANIANS - ORANGE COUNTY; CONTRIBUTIONS; RELIEF ORGANIZATIONS 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
