<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880808-0039
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>08
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Currents Hamper Recovery; Official Blames Overcrowding, Safety
Violations
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>KATIHAR, India (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Overcrowding and safety violations caused
an aging ferry to capsize in the Ganges River, killing as many as
400 people, a government report said. The ferry accident was said
to be India's worst ever.
</P>
<P>
Strong currents hampered efforts today to pull the two-decker
from the rising monsoon-swollen river. Hundreds of relatives stood
by watching.
</P>
<P>
A senior government official, discussing the confidential report
on condition of anonymity, said authorities believed at least 300
people on the lower deck died when the ferry overturned Saturday
morning.
</P>
<P>
About 200 people were on the upper deck, he said. Authorities
believe about 100 people swam to safety or were rescued by
villagers.
</P>
<P>
Only about a dozen bodies have been found, and most of the
missing were believed trapped inside the 35-year-old ferry.
``It was badly overcrowded. The situation was made more
dangerous by wheat bags loaded on the ferry. Many lives could have
been saved if the ferry had carried water safety equipment such as
life jackets,'' said the senior official.
</P>
<P>
Survivors said they protested when 150 bags of wheat were loaded
onto the ferry. The steam-powered vessel started wavering soon
after it left the banks and capsized about 100 yards from the shore.
</P>
<P>
Navy divers attempted to reach the submerged boat today, but the
river was too muddy and its current too swift, said H.S. Pathak,
head of the eight-member diving team.
``We are trying our best, but because of the current, we are not
able to go near the launch,'' Pathak said. ``The water is too
muddy. We can't see anything, so we just have to feel by our
hands.''
Authorities said the water was still rising and the submerged
boat was sinking in the river bed. The water depth was estimated at
12 to 30 feet.
</P>
<P>
Katihar Commissioner Madan Mohan Singh estimated the boat was
resting in about six feet of sand.
``We are planning to break the ferry. Only then will we be able
to get the bodies out,'' Singh said.
</P>
<P>
Katihar District Police Chief P.S. Natarajah said chances of
finding any survivors were ``very, very dim.''
He said the death toll may never be known because some bodies
probably were carried downstream 30 to 60 miles by the surging
water.
</P>
<P>
The ferry was designed to carry about 160 people, but was was
always overcrowded, he said. Jetty workers, who spoke on condition
of anonymity, said 535 tickets were sold for the trip.
</P>
<P>
Katihar Police Inspector N. Kumar said about 2,000 relatives and
residents were waiting along the rain-swollen river for the bodies
to be recovered.
``Police are trying to control the crowds and console them,'' he
said.
</P>
<P>
Family members railed against authorities as numerous officials
arrived to review recovery efforts.
``Give back our family members. We don't want (government)
ministers,'' they shouted.
</P>
<P>
One survivor, Chadrasekhar D. Tiwary, said he was standing on
the ferry's upper deck when it started wavering.
``As soon as the ferry tilted, I knew we were going down. I saw
three women crying for help. They probably drowned,'' the
50-year-old farmer said.
</P>
<P>
Ram Prasad Yadaw's wife and four other family members vanished
in the accident.
``The women and children suffered the worst. They had to sit on
the lower deck,'' he said. ``I am sure my wife is dead.''
It was the worst boat accident ever in India, according to the
United News of India. At least 150 people died on July 5, 1970,
when a boat capsized in Krishna River in eastern India.
</P>
<P>
The Navy divers came from New Delhi, the Indian capital about
650 miles west of Katihar.
</P>
<P>
Mangan Chand, a police officer, said only one body surfaced near
the ferry Sunday. Ten to 12 bodies were found Saturday, according
to Bihar state officials.
</P>
<P>
Chand said his father and uncle were aboard the ferry. He said
he was waiting for the bodies so he could cremate them according to
Hindu rites.
</P>
<P>
The boat trip is normally used by Hindu pilgrims going across
the river to worship at a shrine of Lord Shiva in Deoghar town.
</P>
<P>
Lord Shiva is the destroyer diety in the Hindu trinity.
</P>
<P>
Boat accidents are common during the annual monsoon rains when
major rivers overflow their banks.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP881027-0051
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>27
</DAY> 
<MONTH>10
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
100 Feared Drowned In Ferry Sinking, Pirates Attack Second Boat
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
More than 100 people were feared drowned
after an overcrowded ferry sank at a river junction in southern
Bangladesh, police said today.
</P>
<P>
Fifteen bodies were recovered and 94 people were reported missing
in the sinking Wednesday night where the Ilisha and Tetulia rivers
meet and join the Meghna, police and a district administrator said.
</P>
<P>
Another ferry was attacked by river pirates near Chandpur late
Tuesday, police said. Six passengers, including a pregnant woman,
were thrown overboard and have not been found, Chandpur police said.
</P>
<P>
About 200 passengers were wounded when the pirates fired rifles
and hurled homemade bombs before making off with about $83,000 in
local currency, police said.
</P>
<P>
The ferry that sank was carrying more than double its authorized
capacity of 100 passengers, police said. They said about 100 people
on the ferry's roof swam to safety but most of those in the hull
were unable to save themselves.
</P>
<P>
The ferry was traveling from Mehendiganj to the island town of
Bhola, about 68 miles southeast of Dhaka, when it sank in 22 feet of
water.
</P>
<P>
Police said six bodies were found in the hull of the ferry, the
M.L. Sonali, and nine others were found more than a mile downstream.
</P>
<P>
Two independent newspapers in Dhaka, Ittefaq and Sangbad, quoted
survivors as saying the ferry went out of control while trying to
negotiate a turn.
</P>
<P>
The pirate attack on the second ferry, the M.V. Sagar, also
occurred on the Meghna River. The Sagar was en route from Dhaka to
Barisal when about 50 pirates launched their attack near Chandpur,
34 miles southeast of Dhaka.
</P>
<P>
The pirates, who had boarded the ferry as passengers, opened fire
and exploded bombs shortly before midnight Tuesday as people were
bedding down for the night, Chandpur police said.
</P>
<P>
The attackers escaped in waiting boats, the police added. They
said 44 of the injured passengers were hospitalized, including four
in critical condition.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP881218-0007
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>18
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Overloaded Boat Sinks in South China, 55 Die and Seven Missing
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An overloaded ferry taking schoolchildren on a
field trip capsized and sank in southern China, killing 55 people
and leaving seven missing, the China News Service said in a dispatch
seen Sunday.
</P>
<P>
The 183 passengers and four crew members ``enormously exceeded''
the ferry's capacity and the ship capsized Wednesday before it had
sailed 200 yards, the report said. It did not say how many people
the boat was designed to hold.
</P>
<P>
It said that by Friday, 125 survivors had been rescued, 55 bodies
were found and seven people were missing. The accident occurred off
Hainan island, the report said.
</P>
<P>
The news service said the passengers were 183 students and
teachers from a high school and primary school in Qiongzhong County,
who were going to take the ferry to visit a hydroelectric power
station.
</P>
<P>
On September 22, another overloaded ferry sank in the Guangxi
Zhuang Autonomous Region bordering Vietnam, leaving 61 people dead
and one missing.
</P>
<P>
The Ministry of Communications, which is responsible for inland
water navigation, announced in August it had begun an investigation
into the safety of China's river vessels to determine if standards
should be tightened.
</P>
<P>
The move followed the July 21 capsizing of a ferry on the Min
River in Southwestern Sichuan province in which 133 people died, and
the July 25 sinking of a passenger boat on the Yangtze River in
which 71 people drowned.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890102-0076
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>02
</DAY> 
<MONTH>01
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
URGENT
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Guatemalan Ferry Sinks; 59 Dead, Six Missing
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: Updates with name of Spanish victim, other details. CORRECTS
spelling to Puerto Barrios. No pickup. Adds byline. 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A passenger ferry sank off the Caribbean
coast while being towed to port, and 59 people drowned and six are
missing, authorities and news reports said today.
</P>
<P>
Capt. Anibal Giron Arreola, a spokesman at the Puerto Barrios
naval base, said the ferry Justo Rufino Barrios II sank Sunday
afternoon in Amatique Bay. He said by telephone that 59 people died.
</P>
<P>
Juan Jose Gaytan, a reporter at Radio Portena in Puerto Barrios,
said the Justo Rufineo Barrios II ran out of fuel midway on a
regular 16-mile run from the town Livingston, across the bay, to
Puerto Barrios.
</P>
<P>
Gaytan said the boat sank while it was being towed by a tugboat.
</P>
<P>
The Spanish Embassy in Guatemala City confirmed the sinking and
said a 40-year-old Spanish citizen, Vicente Daudi, was among the
dead. The embassy reported his wife, Rosa Maria Arnal, and a son
survived the shipwreck, but two daughters were missing.
</P>
<P>
Daudi was working with a Spanish technical aid and economic
development mission in Guatemala, the embassy said.
</P>
<P>
An official at the Puerto Barrios morgue said 13 bodies have been
identified. Besides Daudi, the nationalities of the victims were not
immediately known.
</P>
<P>
Gaytan said navy patrol boats, fishing vessels and private craft
have been searching the bay for survivors and recovering bodies.
</P>
<P>
He said he had no other details on the shipwreck.
</P>
<P>
Puerto Barrios, 187 miles northeast of the capital, is
Guatemala's principal east coast port.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890103-0029
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>03
</DAY> 
<MONTH>01
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Captain Charged in Ferry Sinking that Left 67 Dead
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Authorities charged a 22-year-old ferry
captain with negligent homicide after the boat, overcrowded with New
Year's travelers, sank off the Caribbean coast. Sixty-seven people
drowned and 14 were missing.
</P>
<P>
Officials said 46 people survived the sinking of the ferry Justo
Rufino Barrios II in Amatique Bay on Guatemala's east coast Sunday.
</P>
<P>
Juan Pablo Ezquibel was arrested after authorities determined
that about 120 people were aboard the 30-ton ferry, which was
authorized to carry 90, said Capt. Anibal Giron Arreola,
second-in-command at the Puerto Barrios naval base.
</P>
<P>
He said by telephone that the ferry ran out of fuel midway on a
16-mile run across the bay from Livingston to Puerto Barrios and
sank after a naval patrol boat tried to tow it to port.
</P>
<P>
Officials had yet to determine the exact cause of the sinking,
but Giron Arreola said the ferry captain was slow to respond to
requests by the skipper of the naval patrol boat to take control of
the ferry's wheel once it was under tow. He said the patrol boat
captain believed the ferry's rudder was unmanned while under tow.
</P>
<P>
Esquibel radioed that he had taken the wheel just as the boat
began to capsize, Giron Arreola said.
</P>
<P>
Giron Arreola also said that passengers ran to one side of the
ferry while it was under tow just before the ferry sank.
``It appears the boat rode a wave and that as it was leaning the
people ran to one side out of fear,'' he said. Although seas were
only 1-to-1{ feet, passengers were not used to traveling by sea, he
said.
</P>
<P>
No Americans were on board, he said.
</P>
<P>
A morgue official said 13 bodies were identified.
</P>
<P>
Navy patrol boats, fishing vessels and other private craft
searched for the missing Monday.
</P>
<P>
Puerto Barrios, 187 miles northeast of Guatemala City, the
capital, is Guatemala's main east coast port. There are no roads to
Livingston and most travel along the coast is by boat.
</P>
<P>
The Rufino Barrios Maritime Transport firm owns the ferry and
operates two other ferries along the Livingston-Puerto Barrios route.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP901222-0078
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
American Sailors Recount Harrowing Escape
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Gulf Capsize, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>HAIFA, Israel (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Chief Petty Officer Lance Vickery recalls
waves tumbling into the stern of the bobbing ferry headed back to
the USS Saratoga and joking, ``Whoa, looks like we're flooding.''
Only minutes later, his words came true, turning a simple ride
back from Christmas shore leave into a harrowing fight to survive.
</P>
<P>
The Israeli ferry Tuvia capsized shortly after midnight on
Saturday, throwing more than 100 men into the cold waters of Haifa
Bay. At least 19 sailors drowned, and scores were injured. The
sailors were part of the multinational force arrayed against Iraq.
</P>
<P>
Vickery, 33, was among four American sailors interviewed at
Haifa's Rambam Hospital. He is from Jacksonville, Fla., is not far
from Mayport, the Saragota's home port.
</P>
<P>
Three of the sailors said the boat had been taking on water over
the stern in heavy seas, then capsized when it was hit by a big
wave.
</P>
<P>
Vickery said the fatal wave came about a minute after he had
cracked his joke.
``All of a sudden, I saw water just come flying in,'' he said.
``And it was maybe two seconds, and the boat rolled right over.''
The 13-year veteran sailor found himself trapped in the ferry's
cabin, frantically struggling to find a window as the ship sank.
``I started breathing in water and almost died,'' Vickery said.
``If I had been under the water maybe another 30 seconds, I
wouldn't be lying here right now. I'd be in one of those body bags
out there.''
When he made his way to the surface he found ``guys floating
everywhere, screaming and yelling like chaos.''
Despite his own predicament, he grabbed a struggling fellow
sailor by the collar and dragged him toward a floating, plastic
foam life ring. One rescue boat, already overloaded, passed by and
threw life preservers.
</P>
<P>
In what ``seemed like an hour,'' another boat came, also full.
``So they just dragged us through the water back to the
Saratoga, and I was a real happy person to see those guys snatching
me up,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
As Vickery was being treated for bleeding lungs caused by water
inhalation, his hospital roommate, Seaman Michael Benjamin, 19, of
San Antonio, Texas, was recovering from a neck injury suffered when
a rescue boat hit him while he was in the water.
</P>
<P>
Both were wearing blue hospital pajamas and, when they walked to
the visiting room's balcony could see the Saratoga anchored outside
the Haifa harbor.
</P>
<P>
Benjamin, who has been in the navy for just a year, said the
ferry had been jostled in heavy seas.
``As we were going on the waves, I just noticed one that was
bigger than normal and then another one that was bigger than
normal,'' he said. ``The next thing I know, all I saw coming in was
water,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Benjamin said he dove from the ferry, then had to swim
frantically to get away from the suction of the sinking boat.
</P>
<P>
Clinging to a foam plastic float, he was passed by one rescue
boat and hit by a second.
``I looked around and I see this big hull coming at me and we
were all yelling, but I guess the ship didn't see us,'' he said.
``I was trying to get out of the way, but I got hit by the ship.''
Dazed, Benjamin stripped off his jacket, shirt and shoes and
kept treading water until he found a piece of driftwood to cling
to.
``I was scared,'' he admitted. ``I was having a hard time
staying up in the water.''
A rescue ship picked him up, he estimated, about a half hour to
45 minutes later.
</P>
<P>
Two other men interviewed at Rambam Hospital identified
themselves as Technician John Richards, 31, of Twin Lake, Mich.,
and Airman Lamont Jones, 20, of Claremont, Va.
</P>
<P>
Both were breathing with difficulty despite gas masks.
</P>
<P>
Richards recalled seeing a large wave and feeling the ship
heeling to one side.
``All I can remember thinking is, `Oh my God, it's sinking,' and
then I was scrambling for my life,'' he said faintly.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06064099
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  AFRICA; BOAT; ACCIDENT; RESULT; MULTIPLE; DEATH  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  SOMALI REFUGEE BOAT SINKS; 130 ARE KILLED  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A boat carrying hundreds of Somali refugees struck a reef off Kenya and sank,
killing more than 130 people, newspapers reported.;    The accident involving
a vessel ferrying about 600 people occurred Friday near Malindi, a tourist
resort about 400 miles southeast of Nairobi.  
</P>
<P>
First accounts of the accident were reported Sunday in Kenyan newspapers.
</P>
<P>
Two English-language dailies said the accident occurred one mile off the
coast, but a third said it was six miles away.;    Police, navy divers,
tourists and local residents had recovered about 130 bodies by Saturday
afternoon, but 50 victims were believed still trapped in the sunken vessel,
according to the newspapers.;    Confirmation from local authorities of the
accounts was not immediately available.;    The boat with the refugees had set
sail from the Somali town of Kismayo, 250 miles north of Malindi, on Feb. 26.;
It was one of a stream of vessels that brought thousands of Somalis seeking
refuge to Kenya since rebels overthrew Somalian President Mohamed Siad Barre
in late January. The victory followed a month of heavy fighting in Mogadishu,
capital of the East African nation.;    The fighting appears largely to have
stopped since the rebel United Somali Congress established an interim
government, but refugees continue to arrive in Kenya.;    Abdi Mohammed Ali, a
survivor, was quoted as telling the Standard newspaper that most of those who
drowned were on the ship's lower deck.;    First word of the accident came
when two survivors staggered into the Jambo Club tourist hotel, manager Barney
Ngare was quoted as saying by the Sunday Nation.;    The hotel sent a small
boat to help save those still on the sinking vessel, but rescue workers had to
cut the lifeline when too many people grabbed hold, according to Ngare.;   
Another boat sent by the hotel ferried 15 people at a time to shore, said the
Nation.;    Eleven Somalis drowned when a boat capsized off Kenya near Lamu,
north of Malindi, on Feb. 1.  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Nairobi, Kenya  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>04
</DAY> 
<MONTH>03
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06351097
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  BOAT; DISASTER; MULTIPLE; DEATH; EGYPT; MISSING; PERSON; HUNT  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  EGYPTIAN FERRY SINKS - 471 LOST
U.S. AIRCRAFT JOIN THE SEARCH FOR SURVIVORS  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
U.S. Navy aircraft joined the search today for survivors of the ferry sinking
that left 471 people missing in shark-infested Red Sea waters but found
nothing but empty life rafts and debris.;   Investigators, meanwhile, were
looking into complaints from some of the 178 survivors that the crew of the
Salem Express abandoned ship without helping them into lifeboats or flotation
gear.  
</P>
<P>
They also want to know why the ferry strayed outside standard navigational
channels. The 1,105-ton ship went down Saturday night about six miles off the
Egyptian coast after ramming into a coral reef in stormy 10-foot seas.;   "We
are looking for both survivors and bodies," said Brig. Abdel-Karim el-Gazzar,
Egypt's deputy chief of port security. "We haven't lost all hope that there
may be some survivors, although the odds are against it.";   Prime Minister
Atef Sidki, who traveled to Safaga, said many passengers may have been on
lifeboats driven far from the wreck scene by strong winds.;   Ahmed Gamal
Sobhi, Safaga's city council chairman, said only four bodies were recovered by
Egyptian vessels and helicopters and the time nightfall and bad weather
stopped Sunday's search.;   The weather improved today as two helicopters from
the U.S. Navy frigate Aubrey Fitch, which joined in the rescue effort on
Sunday night, and a Navy P-3 submarine-chaser aircraft made their first
daylight search runs, said Lt. Cmdr. Rudolph Brewington, a Pentagon duty
officer.;   "They've observed lots of wreckage, empty life rafts, an oil slick
but no additional bodies and no survivors," he said.;   Survivors said that
after the ship struck the reef, crew members herded them to one side of the
listing boat to keep it from heeling over, then pushed passengers aside to get
to the lifeboats.;   "They went off in a boat," passenger Abdel-A'ati Hassan,
31, said from his hospital bed in Safaga. "They left us with women and kids,
who died.";   The Salem Express was near the end of a 36-hour trip from
Jiddah, Saudi Arabia, to Safaga, about 290 miles south of Cairo. Many of the
passengers were Muslims returning from off-season pilgrimages to Mecca and
others were returning to Egypt after stints as guest workers in Saudi Arabia.;
Outside the harbor, scores of relatives of passengers squatted on a sidewalk
or huddled in taxis, awaiting word about their kin.;   Hassan Al-Aghouri,
Egypt's chief of port security, said the Egyptian-registered ferry
inexplicably left standard navigational channels and investigators were
seeking to question surviving crew about the course change.;   The
investigation also will try to determine whether the ferry was carrying enough
lifeboats.;   Al-Ahram, a leading Cairo newspaper, said in an unattributed
report today that the vessel left the charted navigation channel to take a
shortcut. It said naval authorities warned the skipper back on course to avoid
the area's abundant coral reefs.;   But strong winds sent the boat out of
control, the newspaper said.;   The boat's first mate, Mahmoud Soleiman
Rizake, said a "terrible explosion" from the collision awoke him in his
cabin.;   "Water flooded the ship in 10 minutes, causing it to sink," he said,
adding that he jumped overboard and swam until a rescue boat picked him up.;  
The temperature of the water was not immediately known, but the air
temperature was about 50 degrees and many of the survivors were treated for
exposure. At least 118 of the survivors were hospitalized.;   El-Gazzar, the
deputy port security chief, said all but 10 of the passengers were Egyptians.  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Safaga, Egypt  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>SJMN91-06351209
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> SJMN 
</SOURCE>
<KEYWORDS>  BOAT; DISASTER; MULTIPLE; DEATH; EGYPT; MISSING; PERSON; HUNT  
</KEYWORDS>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
  EGYPTIAN FERRY SINKS - 462 LOST
SURVIVORS SAY CREW MEMBERS ABANDONED THEM  
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The engineer of a ferry that sank off this Red Sea port, leaving more than 400
people missing, today denied accusations of widespread negligence on the part
of the ship's crew.;   Mahmoud Moharram, engineer of the Salem Express,
acknowledged misconduct by some crew members but said the survival of only
about 10 of the 71-member crew indicated negligence was not widespread.  
</P>
<P>
Investigators were looking into complaints from some survivors that the
crew abandoned the ferry without helping passengers and that some crew members
pushed aside passengers to get to lifeboats.;   Moharram said he helped 17
passengers put on life jackets. He said the ferry sank quickly Saturday night
after being tossed into a coral reef by stormy seas. Moharram said the coral
cut a hole in the ship's side, and water also entered through the boarding
doors.;   Only seven bodies have been recovered since the ferry went down,
leaving 462 people missing. Today, the deputy security chief for Egypt's ports
said searchers have not given up.;   "We are looking for both survivors and
bodies," said Brig. Gen. Abdel-Karim el-Gazzar. "We haven't lost all hope that
there may be some survivors, although the odds are against it. But you never
can tell.";   Survivors said that after the ferry hit the reef, crew members
herded them to one side of the listing boat, then pushed passengers aside to
get to lifeboats.;   "They went off in a boat," passenger Abdel-A'ati Hassan,
31, said from his hospital bed. "They left us with women and kids, who died.";
Hassan said the ship sank within 15 minutes of hitting the reef. During that
time, he said, he saw no crew members helping passengers.;   "The crew told us
to stand on one side. They wore life preservers and left us and even pushed us
aside to escape," he said. "They could have had time to help.";   Many
survivors spent hours in shark-infested waters or in lifeboats before being
picked up. Egypt's director of port security, Hassan al-Aghouri, said the
rescue was delayed by the storm.;   At Safaga Central Hospital, Mustafa Ahmed,
38, said he pulled 13 people into a lifeboat.;   "I found a rope and clung to
it, and then I found a capsized lifeboat," Ahmed said. "I managed to get 13
people who were around me in the sea onto the boat. We waited until a ship
rescued us at around noon.";   Prime Minister Atef Sidki, who traveled to
Safaga, said many passengers may have been on lifeboats driven far from the
wreckage by strong winds.;   However, many bodies were expected to be found in
the hull of the ferry. Efforts to lift it began today.;   U.S. Navy helicopter
crews reported "lots of wreckage including life preservers, rafts and floating
material" where the ferry went down. They said the 1,105-ton ferry lay on its
starboard - or right-hand - side, with its port side protruding from the
water.;   Lt. Gen. Salah Halaby, chief of staff of Egypt's armed forces, said
30 Egyptian navy divers were searching for victims or, less likely,
survivors.;   The Salem Express sank after a trip from Jiddah, Saudi Arabia,
to Safaga, 290 miles south of Cairo. Many passengers - all but 10 of the 649
people aboard were Egyptians - were Muslims returning from pilgrimages to
Mecca, and others were coming home after working in Saudi Arabia.;   Ahmed
Gamal Sobhi, Safaga's city council chairman, said four bodies were recovered
by Egyptian vessels and helicopters by nightfall, and bad weather stopped the
search Sunday.  
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY>  USA  
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_CITY>  Safaga, Egypt  
</DATELINE_CITY>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>91
</YEAR> 
</DATE> 
<DATELINE_REGION>  WEST  
</DATELINE_REGION>
<DATELINE_STATE>  CA  
</DATELINE_STATE>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
