<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890426-0123
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>04
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Career Highlights Of Lucille Ball
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Obit-Ball Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here are highlights of Lucille Ball's career:
1911 _ Born Aug. 6, 1911, in Jamestown N.Y., the daughter of an
electrician and concert pianist Desiree Ball.
1926 _ Begins career in show business in New York as a chorus
girl.
1933 _ Goes to Hollywood as movie showgirl for RKO, later
becoming a successful actress appearing in more than 75 films.
1940 _ Marries Desi Arnaz, a Cuban percussionist and bandleader
when both were making the movie ``Too Many Girls.''
1951 _ They form Desilu Productions with $5,000 and ``I Love
Lucy'' begins its historic six-year domination of television
comedy. Earlier in the year, they have their first child.
1953 _ ``I Love Lucy'' episode in which Lucy Ricardo gives birth
to Little Ricky is telecast the same day that Lucille Ball, in real
life, gives birth to second child, Desi Jr.
1957 _ Desilu purchases RKO studios and begins producing other
programs.
1960 _ The Arnazes divorce, with Desi selling his share of the
studio to Lucy for $3 million.
1961 _ Miss Ball marries night-club comic Gary Morton, who
becomes her executive producer.
1962 _ Miss Ball goes solo, returning to the airwaves in ``The
Lucy Show.''
1967 _ Miss Ball sells company to Gulf 
</P>
<P>
amp;
</P>
<P>
Western for $18 million.
1968 _ ``The Lucy Show'' is redesigned and becomes ``Here's
Lucy.'' It runs until 1974.
1974 _ Miss Ball plays the title role in the movie version of
``Mame.''
1985 _ In her first serious dramatic role in years, Miss Ball
plays a New York bag lady in the CBS-TV movie ``Stone Pillow.'' She
is hospitalized for dehydration following strenuous work on the
film.
1986 _ Miss Ball returns to sitcom television in ABC's ``Life
With Lucy.'' The show is canceled within months.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890426-0126
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>04
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Little Ricky, Now 38, Remembers Lucy as Surrogate Mom
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Obit-Ball, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhoto JX2
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>JACKSON, Miss. (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The actor who played Little Ricky on the
``I Love Lucy'' show said Wednesday he spent more time with Lucille
Ball than he did with his own family in the five years he played
the comedian's TV son.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball died of a ruptured aorta at Cedars-Sinai Medical
Center in Los Angeles Wednesday morning, hospital officials said.
</P>
<P>
She was 77.
``She was old and, of course, I knew about the heart attack, so
I was not shocked by her death,'' said Keith Thibodeaux, who at age
6 began playing Miss Ball's drum-playing son on the comedy series
that continues in syndication around the world. ``I'm sure all this
is going to hit me a little later on.''
Thibodeaux grew up on the set, playing Little Ricky from 1956
until 1961 under Miss Ball's watchful eye.
``I think the thing I remember most about Lucy was that she was
very much in control of everything,'' said Thibodeaux, who began
playing the drums at age 2, was a professional drummer at age 4 and
is now drummer with David and the Giants, a Christian rock group.
</P>
<P>
He lives in Jackson with his wife, Kathy, a ballerina.
</P>
<P>
Thibodeaux, 38, said he got his break in show business when big
band leader Horace Heidt persuaded his father to bring him from
Lafayette, La., to California for the ``Swift Premium Hour,'' a
traveling radio show that led to a string of one-night stands
across the country.
</P>
<P>
That led to an audition for the ``I Love Lucy'' role in
Hollywood.
``I remember Lucy saying, `that's him,' and from that time I was
Little Ricky,'' said Thibodeaux, who then used the name Richard
Keith. ``I signed a seven-year contract with the studio in 1956 and
the first episode I was in was aired that December with Bob Hope _
I just turned 6.''
Thibodeaux said that during the series' run he spent as much
time with Miss Ball as with his own family in Lafayette.
``And I spent more time with her off the set at her home than at
the studio,'' he said. ``I remember her as very strict but with a
lot of love. She had her ways but despite all, she was a great
person, very, very talented.
``I know everybody remembers her as zany and wacky but that was
only on the show. Actually, she was just the opposite and was very
serious. ... That's what made her a great actress.''
He said Miss Ball often gave him gifts and that he remembers
spending at least one Christmas at her home.
``I remember she once gave me an Indian tepee, then my own
dressing room,'' he said. ``She gave me bicycles and an identical
set of drums.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890426-0160
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>04
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Lucille Ball Remembered In Her Hometown
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Obit-Ball, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>JAMESTOWN, N.Y. (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Lucille Ball was mourned Wednesday by the
western New York hometown she left for Hollywood more than half a
century ago.
``It is a sad day for all of us. But I'm sure that feeling is
shared by many people around the world,'' said Nelson Garifi,
organizer of a homecoming for Miss Ball that was to have been held
next month.
``She was always so full of life,'' said Pauline Lopus, who went
to school with Miss Ball and had kept in touch with her. ``It
seemed like she would just go on forever.''
The 77-year-old comedian died of a ruptured aorta, the main
heart artery, at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center in Los Angeles, where
she was recovering from emergency heart surgery last week.
</P>
<P>
The American Heart Association's Jamestown office was deluged
with calls from Miss Ball's fans who wanted to make a memorial
donation, officials said.
``We just can't process as many memorials as we've received,''
said office manager Nathan Lax.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball was born Aug. 6, 1911, in this city of 40,000 people
about 60 miles south of Buffalo, the daughter of an electrician and
a concert pianist. She grew up in nearby Celoron, a rural hamlet on
Chautauqua Lake.
</P>
<P>
Friends said some of the characteristics of her most famous role
_ the zany, excitable star of television's ``I Love Lucy'' _ were
evident during her childhood.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Lopus said Miss Ball dreamed of fame, either as a dramatic
actress in New York City or as a dancing girl in musicals.
</P>
<P>
At age 15, she worked as a barker at a local amusement park,
screaming pitches for popcorn and hot dogs until she lost her voice.
</P>
<P>
In high school, she starred in high school plays and made her
first appearance before a large audience at the now-defunct Palace
Theater here. As a model, she caught Hollywood's eye and in 1933,
she was off to Hollywood.
</P>
<P>
Although the comedian hadn't visited Jamestown since 1956 and
had no family there, she regularly donated money to charities,
civic events and Jamestown Community College, said Mayor Steven
Carlson.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball was to have received an honorary degree from the
college at the homecoming scheduled for May 20.
</P>
<P>
Residents had hung posters saying ``Jamestown Loves Lucy'' in
storefronts and house windows.
</P>
<P>
After she fell ill last week, residents signed the posters and
sent them to her as a get-well greeting. They sent more than 150
posters with 10,000 signatures.
</P>
<P>
The honorary degree will be awarded posthumously, said Garifi,
who is community relations director at the college.
</P>
<P>
Celoron had planned to rename a street in Miss Ball's honor
during her visit, and still plans to rename it as Lucy Lane, said
John Goodell of Celoron's Historical Society.
</P>
<P>
Goodell said that when the group was formed about a year ago,
``We sent an invitation to Lucille Ball to be a member, and she
sent back a check for $500 for a life membership.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890426-0185
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>04
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Actress-Comedian Lucille Ball Dies at 77
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 9th, `I and ..., to UPDATE with comment
from President Bush; picks up 10th graf: ``Her red ...
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhotos LA4, NY28, 36, 38, 40, LaserColor NY31
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Lucille Ball, the daffy comedian whose
harebrained schemes drove her television family crazy but delighted
viewers for four decades, died Wednesday of a ruptured abdominal
artery. She was 77.
</P>
<P>
The actress, star of the hugely popular ``I Love Lucy'' and
related situation comedies seen in more than 80 countries, had
undergone major heart surgery April 18.
</P>
<P>
She had been recovering steadily, getting out of bed and joking
with the staff, but shortly before dawn Wednesday, she went into
cardiac arrest due to internal bleeding and could not be revived,
said Cedars-Sinai Medical Center spokesman Ronald Wise.
</P>
<P>
She suffered a complete heart failure at 5 a.m. and 47 minutes
of resuscitation efforts proved fruitless, Wise said. ``There was
nothing to indicate this would happen,'' Wise said. ``The heart
itself apparently was not involved in Miss Ball's sudden death.''
In the 6{-hour surgery at Cedars-Sinai, doctors replaced her
aorta and aortic valve. Although the replaced portion of Miss
Ball's aorta did not apparently fail, the entire artery was in poor
condition when she was operated upon, said Dr. Robert Kass.
</P>
<P>
Kass, who performed the operation, said at the time the tearing
in Miss Ball's aorta ``progressed all the way down into her
abdomen.''
Miss Ball, with her fire-engine red hair and siren wail, was
considered the queen of situation comedy and a pioneer of the
sitcom format.
``I and 100 million others will miss her,'' said comedian George
Burns. ``But we haven't lost Lucille Ball because she's still with
us on television and we can see her on and on.''
``Lucille Ball possessed the gift of laughter. But she also
embodied an even greater treasure _ the gift of love,'' President
Bush said in a statement. ``She appealed to the gentler impulses of
the human spirit. She was not merely an actress or comedienne. She
was Lucy and she was loved.''
``Her red hair, her antics on the screen, her timing and her
zest for life made her an American institution,'' former President
and Nancy Reagan said in a statement. ``Just the mention of her
name brings a smile. ... We love Lucy and will miss her deeply.''
``It's a shock after working very closely with her and loving
her for over 35 years,'' said Miss Ball's frequent sidekick, Gale
Gordon, who was in Edmonton, Alberta.
</P>
<P>
While in the hospital, the comedian was deluged with thousands
of cards, letters, flowers and phone calls from fans as far away as
Australia and Europe.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball and her late former husband, Desi Arnaz, starred in
``I Love Lucy'' from 1951 to 1957 and have been seen since in
widely syndicated reruns. The late Vivian Vance and William Frawley
played their neighbors, Fred and Ethel Mertz.
</P>
<P>
Her split-second timing, wide-mouthed wails and exaggerated
pratfalls made the ``I Love Lucy'' show one of the most popular in
television history.
</P>
<P>
Bridge clubs and bowling teams changed their meeting nights to
watch Lucy and Ethel cook up still another ridiculous scheme that
would push their long-suffering husbands to exasperation.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball's real, onscreen pregnancy marked a milestone in
television, and an estimated 44 million viewers _ more than for the
inauguration of President Eisenhower _ tuned in on Jan. 19, 1953,
to watch Lucy Ricardo have Little Ricky. The real birth occurred
just four hours before the previously-filmed show was broadcast.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball's singularity as a comedian was matched by her talent
as a show-business entrepreneur. She and Arnaz established one of
TV's first major independent studios.
</P>
<P>
Desilu, as their production company was called, made some of the
top comedy shows of the 1950s and '60s, including ``December
Bride,'' ``Our Miss Brooks'' and ``Make Room for Daddy.''
As testament to their value as prime-time stars, Miss Ball and
Arnaz signed an $8 million, no-cancellation, two-year contract with
CBS in 1953 _ the largest in television history at the time and a
figure scarcely any TV star can touch today.
</P>
<P>
The couple stopped making weekly ``I Love Lucy'' shows in 1957.
</P>
<P>
Despite riches and two children, Lucie and Desi Jr., their marriage
foundered, and the couple divorced in 1960.
</P>
<P>
In 1961, Miss Ball married nightclub comic Gary Morton, who
became her executive producer, and remained on TV for 12 more years
in the weekly ``Here's Lucy'' and ``The Lucy Show.''
Miss Ball was born Aug. 6, 1911, in Jamestown, N.Y., the
daughter of an electrician and a concert pianist.
</P>
<P>
Young Lucy, a brunette, was dazzled by the stage, but her
ambitions were discouraged by an acting school _ ``They sent my
mother a letter saying she was wasting her money,'' Miss Ball once
said _ and she turned to modeling under the name Diane Belmont.
</P>
<P>
Her ads for Chesterfield cigarettes caught Hollywood's eye, and
in 1933 she went to California. As a blonde, she appeared with the
Marx Brothers in ``Room Service,'' with Fred Astaire in ``Follow
the Fleet'' and with Katharine Hepburn and Ginger Rogers in ``Stage
Door.''
In all, she appeared in more than 75 movies.
</P>
<P>
In 1940, her tresses colored the fiery trademark red, Miss Ball
met Arnaz, a rumba star. They married within six months.
</P>
<P>
In 1951, when CBS decided to move her radio series, ``My
Favorite Husband,'' to television, Miss Ball insisted that Arnaz be
her co-star. But the network wasn't sure Arnaz would be a hit with
the American public.
</P>
<P>
The couple went on a nationwide vaudeville tour and proved
audiences would watch a leggy, blue-eyed comedian and a Cuban-born
band leader with a heavy accent. They also produced their own pilot
episode on borrowed money.
</P>
<P>
CBS relented, and ``I Love Lucy'' was an immediate success.
</P>
<P>
The show revolutionized television sitcom production in the days
before videotape. It was filmed in advance before a live audience,
employing three cameras instead of the traditional one used for
motion pictures.
</P>
<P>
The actress was last seen at the 61st Academy Awards ceremony
March 29, where the svelte actress received a standing ovation and
laughed freely throughout her brief bit with Bob Hope.
</P>
<P>
Her last series _ ``Life with Lucy,'' once again co-starring
Gordon _ was carried by ABC at the start of the 1986 season. But
the show, her first series in 12 years, was canceled after less
than two months when it drew spectacularly low ratings. She ``felt
terrible. ... It really devastated her,'' daughter Lucie Arnaz said
at the time.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball also played a bag lady in the 1985 TV movie ``Stone
Pillow,'' considered one of the most challenging roles of her
career. She was hospitalized for dehydration when it was over, but
the movie was a minor critical and ratings success.
</P>
<P>
Just this month, Miss Ball had signed a deal for a reported
$750,000 with Putnam to publish her autobiography.
</P>
<P>
Said CBS Chairman William Paley: ``Lucille Ball will always be
the first lady of CBS. ... Lucy's extraordinary ability to light up
the screen and brighten our lives is a legacy that will last
forever.''
Funeral arrangements were pending.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890426-0204
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>04
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Longtime Sidekick Remembers Lucy Back When
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Obit-Ball, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>EDMONTON, Alberta (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Actor Gale Gordon, a sidekick of
Lucille Ball from radio days who appeared with her in three
television series, recalled on Wednesday how the comedian never
thought of herself as particularly funny.
``Oh, but when she told a story or recalled an event that
happened she always illustrated it with her body and her face,''
the 83-year-old Gordon said in a telephone interview. ``She never
saw it, but she was extremely amusing.''
Gordon, who is appearing in a play in Edmonton, spent the day in
an Edmonton hotel room, mourning the death of Lucille Ball in a Los
Angeles hospital Wednesday at age 77 and quietly remembering his
funny friend.
``The world will miss her greatly,'' the actor said. ``I
personally will remember her as the best talent of her kind in the
world ... a wonderful, warm friend and a bit of a genius _ the only
one I've ever really known.''
In his first television series alongside Miss Ball, Gordon was
the flustered banker Mr. Mooney in ``The Lucy Show'' from 1962-68.
</P>
<P>
The next six years saw him as Harrison Carter on ``Here's Lucy.''
They were reunited briefly in 1986 for the short-lived ``Life
With Lucy.''
Gordon first met Miss Ball in 1947 on the radio program ``My
Favorite Husband,'' which later became ``I Love Lucy'' on
television.
``I thought she was a very good-looking young woman, and very
talented,'' he recalled. ``She was very pleasant to work with. None
of us knew what was going to happen _ television was very young
then and it wasn't taken too seriously. We never dreamed it would
ever become the power it was ... and the great stars it would
produce.''
Gordon last spoke to Miss Ball from Edmonton on his birthday,
Feb. 20, when ``she called to wish me a happy birthday as she has
done for years and years.''
Gordon has done regular stints for years at a chain of
Edmonton-based dinner theatres called Stage West. He is currently
appearing with that company's Mayfair Dinner Theatre as a priest in
the play ``Mass Appeal.''
The play has another month to run and Gordon says that means he
won't be able to attend Miss Ball's funeral.
``I couldn't do that because it would put people out of work,''
he said. ``She would be the first one to scream her head off if I
did that.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890427-0014
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>27
</DAY> 
<MONTH>04
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Lucy Always Credited Others And Never Knew How Great She Was
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Obit-Ball, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: Also in Thursday AMs report.
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Bob Thomas has covered Hollywood for The
Associated Press for 45 years.
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
She never knew how great she was.
</P>
<P>
Amid the blimp-size egos of the entertainment world, Lucille
Ball stood out like an orange beacon. She never bragged. She never
exercised her considerable power. She always seemed astonished,
even embarrassed, when honors inevitably came her way.
</P>
<P>
When she was to receive a humanitarian award from Variety Clubs
on a CBS special five years ago, she told me: ``There comes a time
in your life when you get a lot of plaques. It's very flattering
and I'll go along with it, especially if it benefits children.''
Whenever she was praised for ``I Love Lucy,'' she invariably
replied: ``Well, all of the credit should go to (writers) Madelyn
Pugh and Bob Carroll Jr.'' Or, ``Desi was a genius: He was
responsible for the show's success.'' Or she cited co-stars Desi,
Vivian Vance and Bill Frawley.
</P>
<P>
Yes, the writing and producing and casting of ``I Love Lucy''
were marvelous, but Lucy's performance added the quantum force. Her
inspired pantomime could be written by no one: the growing panic as
the chocolate assembly line speeded up; her catalog of pained
expressions after tasting the patent medicine she was demonstrating.
</P>
<P>
Unlike many stars, Lucille Ball rarely indulged in
self-analysis. But on one occasion she revealed why her feelings
about the ``I Love Lucy'' triumph might have been ambivalent:
Living through the last five years of the show, she said, ``took
the edge off any enjoyment I might have had. Desi's drinking and
carousing were a terrible embarrassment, bad for a woman's
self-esteem. The talk around town was `poor Lucy.' Because I
couldn't face people, I became a recluse for more than 5{ years.
``I never demonstrated my unhappiness at the studio, and
actually, working together was a blessing. Desi had everything so
well organized that it was easy to do the work.''
Lucy was late in reaching her comedy potential. She was 40 when
``I Love Lucy'' started on CBS and revolutionized television. And
although she spent many years in Hollywood, ``none of the studios
ever designed comedies for me the way MGM did for Red Skelton,
Paramount did for Bob Hope and Sam Goldwyn did for Danny Kaye,''
she once said.
``Television was the medium for me, the medium for anyone who
wanted to be well known a lot faster than waiting a year and a half
for a movie to come out,'' she said in an interview late in life.
``Television is an instant barometer, especially the way we did it.
``It was all new. Nobody knew anything about television. Nobody
was there to say, `No, don't do that, it's wrong!' We never knew
what was wrong and what was right. We were all feeling our way.
</P>
<P>
Desi was very innovative and very showmanship-conscious and was
very intent on going ahead and doing it: `That sounds all right,
let's go!' So we went.''
Always the credit to someone else. But millions upon millions of
television watchers know otherwise.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890427-0052
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>27
</DAY> 
<MONTH>04
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Lucille Ball Remembered In Her Hometown
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Obit-Ball, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>JAMESTOWN, N.Y. (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As a young girl in western New York,
Lucille Ball hawked hot dogs and popcorn at an amusement park as
she dreamed of starring in movies, hometown friends recalled.
``She always talked about being a star,'' said Pauline Lopus,
who went to school with Miss Ball and had kept in touch with her.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball, born 60 miles south of Buffalo in Jamestown on Aug.
6, 1911, grew up in nearby Celoron, a rural hamlet on Chautauqua
Lake.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Lopus remembered the sitcom star on Wednesday as ``daring
in many ways.''
``She tried to get me to run off (to Broadway),'' Mrs. Lopus
added. ``But I didn't have the nerve.''
At 15, Miss Ball worked as a barker at the amusement park,
screaming for people to buy popcorn and hot dogs until she lost her
voice.
</P>
<P>
Later, she starred in high school plays and got her start in
front of a large audience on the vaudeville stage at the defunct
Palace Theater in Jamestown.
</P>
<P>
Although Miss Ball hadn't visited Jamestown since 1956 and had
no family there, she stayed in touch with friends.
``Even though she was a big star, she was still just Lucy to
us,'' said Irene Rosseti of Celoron.
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Rosseti said Miss Ball recently sent her and her husband a
letter on their 50th wedding anniversary.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball regularly donated money to charities, civic events and
Jamestown Community College, said Jamestown Mayor Steven Carlson.
</P>
<P>
On May 20, Miss Ball was to receive an honorary degree from the
college and had planned to return to Jamestown, now a city of about
40,000.
</P>
<P>
Residents had put up posters saying ``Jamestown Loves Lucy'' in
storefronts and home windows. After Miss Ball suffered a heart
attack last week, residents decided to sign the posters and send
them to her as a get-well greeting. More than 150 posters were sent
with 10,000 signatures.
</P>
<P>
The 77-year-old comedian died Wednesday of a ruptured aorta, the
main heart artery, at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center in Los Angeles,
where she was recovering from last week's emergency heart surgery.
``It is a sad day for all of us,'' said Nelson Garifi, an
organizer of the welcoming event. ``But I'm sure that feeling is
shared by many people around the world.''
Garifi, community relations director for the community college,
said the honorary degree will be awarded posthumously.
</P>
<P>
Future generations in Celoron will have a reminder of their
famous resident every time they drive or walk down the street where
she grew up _ it will be renamed Lucy Lane.
</P>
<P>
Village officials had planned formal ceremonies renaming the
street when she was due in the area next month.
``But it will happen anyway,'' John Goodell of the village's
historical society said Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
When the society was formed about a year ago, Goodell said: ``We
sent an invitation to Lucille Ball to be a member, and she sent
back a check for $500 for a life membership.
``It was a check written in a very bold hand with a signature
about a half inch high.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890427-0098
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>27
</DAY> 
<MONTH>04
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Lucy's Legacy Will Be Eternal
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: INSERTS one graf after 24th graf, `Admirers included...' to
add Reagan statement.
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhoto NY8
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An outpouring of sympathy from presidents to
childhood neighbors followed the death of Lucille Ball, but many
said the queen mother of comedy will live on through television
reruns and her influence on comedy.
</P>
<P>
The daffy, redheaded comedian whose harebrained schemes drove
her television family crazy and delighted viewers for four decades
died Wednesday of a ruptured abdominal artery at Cedars-Sinai
Medical Center. She was 77 and died eight days after emergency
heart surgery.
</P>
<P>
A private burial was planned, reportedly with no funeral
services in accordance with Miss Ball's wishes.
``God has her now, and, thanks to television, we'll have her
forever,'' said comedian and longtime friend Bob Hope.
</P>
<P>
Hospital switchboards were swamped with condolence calls and
thousands of cards after Miss Ball's death, spokesman Ron Wise
said. Miss Ball's family requested that any flowers sent to the
Medical Center in her memory be distributed to other patients.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball maintained her sense of humor even when she was
critically ill. Following her operation last week, her first words
to her daughter, Lucie, were: ``Wouldn't you know _ this is the day
I was going to get my hair done.''
Miss Ball had been improving steadily from the heart surgery, so
her death came as a shock.
``She had been walking, her spirits were up. Her family was with
her,'' Wise said. ``She responded as well as anyone could respond
to that kind of surgery.''
He said she woke up early Wednesday complaining about a sudden
pain in her back, and in a matter of seconds went into a full
cardiac arrest that was caused by a ruptured aorta.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball and her late former husband, Desi Arnaz, starred in
``I Love Lucy'' from 1951 to 1957. In the ground-breaking show,
still seen in syndication worldwide, the late Vivian Vance and
William Frawley played their neighbors, Fred and Ethel Mertz.
``Probably a lot of what she did rubbed off on what I do,'' said
actress-comedian Jane Curtin, star of the sitcom ``Kate and
Allie.'' ``But it couldn't be helped, because I memorized her
shows.''
The show, one of the most popular in television history, was
distinguished by Miss Ball's faultless timing, rubber-faced
expressions, wide-mouthed wails and extravagant pratfalls.
``Working with Lucy was like receiving an M.A. or a Ph.D. in
comedy,'' recalled Joan Rivers. ``What she forgot about comic
timing and delivery is more than most of us will ever learn in a
lifetime.''
Comedian Whoopi Goldberg said: ``Lucy was great because she
represented every person. She showed us human foibles and gave us a
chance to laugh at ourselves.''
Miss Goldberg said her favorite episode involved a visit by the
``I Love Lucy'' characters to Hollywood, where Lucy and Ethel
spotted actor William Holden in a restaurant.
``That was how we would all react to seeing a movie star in a
restaurant,'' Miss Goldberg said. ``She was looking at him in a
compact mirror, and trying to look at him surreptitiously. And
that's just an example of how everyone can identify with Lucy.''
Bob Rosati, who lives down the street from the Beverly Hills
home Miss Ball shared with husband Gary Morton, said he was
watching a rerun of ``I Love Lucy'' on Wednesday morning when the
screen went black and the words ``In Memory of Lucille Ball,
1911-1989'' appeared.
``I felt I had lost someone in my family. I couldn't believe
it,'' said Rosati, 40. ``I was watching Lucy like I do every
morning. She's one of the most-admired ladies in this town.''
He was among a group of fans who stood reverently outside Miss
Ball's home on Roxbury Drive as florists delivered baskets of
flowers to the house. Tour vans passed by in a non-stop procession.
</P>
<P>
On Hollywood Boulevard's Walk of Fame, flower arrangements were
placed on Miss Ball's two stars _ one for her film work, one for
television.
</P>
<P>
Budd Friedman, owner of the Improvisation comedy clubs, said,
``The world of comedy has lost its first lady. Her death is an
irreparable loss ... to our industry.''
Actor Danny DeVito recalled getting a personal congratulation
from Miss Ball in 1981 when he won an Emmy for the TV series
``Taxi.''
``It made it like it had been blessed,'' he recalled.
</P>
<P>
Admirers included President Bush, in Southern California at the
time of Miss Ball's passing, and former President Reagan.
``Her red hair, her antics on the screen, her timing and her
zest for life made her an American institution,'' the former
president and Nancy Reagan said in a statement. ``Just the mention
of her name brings a smile. ... We love Lucy and will miss her
deeply.''
``Lucille Ball possessed the gift of laughter,'' Bush said.
``But she also embodied an even greater treasure _ the gift of
love. She appealed to the gentler impulses of the human spirit. She
was not merely an actress or comedienne. She was Lucy and she was
loved.''
``To baby boomers, a happy chunk of our childhood is missing,''
said ``Saturday Night Live'' comedian Victoria Jackson, who was
born two years after ``I Love Lucy'' went off the air as a regular
series. ``She didn't make me laugh out loud, I remember, she just
made me happy about life.''
Said comic Tim Conway: ``We're going to miss this lady, but not
really, because she's still here. All those wonderful things they
did together ... those wonderful TV shows ... are still available.''
Although Miss Ball hadn't visited her hometown of Jamestown,
N.Y, since 1956 and had no family there, she had stayed in touch
with friends.
</P>
<P>
Irene Rosseti, who now lives in Celoron, N.Y., said Miss Ball
recently had sent her and her husband a letter on their 50th
wedding anniversary.
``Even though she was a big star, she was still just Lucy to
us,'' she recalled.
</P>
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
<P>
Hospital spokesman Wise said that the family has
asked that donations be sent to the Lucille Ball Foundation, in
care of Irella-Manella, 1800 Ave. of the Stars, Suite 900, Los
Angeles, Ca. 90067.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890509-0040
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>09
</DAY> 
<MONTH>05
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Lucille Ball Memorials: Fans Shed Tears for Woman Who Made Them Laugh
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Thousands of Lucille Ball's fans shed tears
for the woman who made them laugh, as three cities held memorial
services in which the redheaded comedian was remembered with
prayers and applause.
``She was a whole package. There never will be another one like
her. I love her,'' said a tearful Carol Burnett following a
memorial Mass in suburban Santa Monica.
</P>
<P>
More than a thousand people who packed the St. Monica's Catholic
Church rose to their feet and clapped for several minutes after
television minister the Rev. Robert Schuller asked them to
``applaud the Lord for Lucille Ball.''
About 1,000 people also crowded a church in New York and 200
gathered in a Chicago church. All three memorial Masses began at 8
p.m. Monday, the time Miss Ball's three most popular programs were
often broadcast.
</P>
<P>
The 77-year-old comedian who starred in one of television's
biggest all-time hits, ``I Love Lucy,'' died here April 26 of a
ruptured aorta, a major blood vessel, eight days after emergency
open-heart surgery.
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball, known for her honed comedic timing, wide-mouthed
expressions and wacky antics, was popular among generations of fans
who watched ``I Love Lucy'' as a first-run show in the '50s and in
three decades of reruns.
``She showed her love in the only way she knew how, by making
you laugh,'' the Rev. James Fox told those gathered for the Roman
Catholic Mass at St. Ignatius Loyola in New York.
</P>
<P>
Broadcaster Diane Sawyer told the crowd that the death of Miss
Ball may have settled a longstanding theological debate over
whether there is laughter in heaven.
``A God who would have created her would never let her laughter
be far from Him,'' said Ms. Sawyer.
</P>
<P>
In Chicago, the Rev. Jack Wall told people at Old St. Patrick
Church that God gave the world talents like Miss Ball ``to show us
life is not a tragedy, but a comedy with a happy ending.''
``She taught us that if we could love Lucy, we could love
ourselves,'' Wall said.
</P>
<P>
In announcing the services, Miss Ball's family said: ``Monday
night was the time when most of the nation was used to being with
Lucy.''
Two of the three long-running comedy shows in which Miss Ball
starred, ``The Lucy Show'' and ``Here's Lucy,'' aired Monday
nights. ``I Love Lucy'' had starting times on Mondays and other
days.
``Lucille Ball gave the gift of humor which produced
happiness,'' said Schuller at the Santa Monica service. ``Only God
knows how many husbands and wives weren't speaking _ and then
Monday night rolled around.''
Fans lined up to get in the Santa Monica church as much as four
hours early. Florists delivered arrangements including a 3-foot
heart of red carnations with the words ``I Love Lucy'' written
across.
</P>
<P>
Hundreds of people came forward during Holy Communion to receive
blessings from three priests, including a woman wearing an ``I Love
Lucy'' T-shirt.
``I think she would have loved it very much, and she lived her
life for the people who were in that room tonight,'' said Lucie
Arnaz, daughter of Miss Ball and the late Desi Arnaz.
</P>
<P>
Gary Morton, Miss Ball's husband for more than two decades,
attended a private service for his wife last month. The actress'
remains were buried at Forest Lawn Memorial Park in Hollywood Hills.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890913-0253
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>13
</DAY> 
<MONTH>09
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
$adv22
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
$adv23
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
For Release Weekend Editions, Sept. 22-23, and thereafter
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Bob Hope Remembers Moments With Lucy in NBC Special
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhoto LA1 of Sept. 11
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Bob Hope keeps voluminous files, including the
jokes he delivered and people he has performed with, and his first
entry under Lucille Ball is an appearance with Hope in 1945 on a
show called ``G.I. Journal.''
``I really can't remember many details about it,'' said Hope, who
pays tribute to his frequent co-star in an NBC special Saturday
night. It's called ``Bob Hope's Love Affair With Lucille Ball.'' She
died in April of this year.
</P>
<P>
That first time together was followed by four movies, frequent
visits by Hope on ``I Love Lucy'' and regular appearances by Lucy on
his television shows.
``Lucy was a very funny woman,'' Hope said. ``Even in private she
could get off a great ad lib. But it's hard to compare her with
other funny women. It's like asking who's the best golfer. You have
to go to the records. I don't think anyone ever had the success she
had. She certainly holds the most records.''
A secretary dug the details of that first joint appearance out of
one of two vaults where Hope keeps everything pertaining to his long
comic career. There are written records of all his shows, copies of
all the scripts, monologues and comic routines, audio tapes of his
radio shows and thousands of other mementos.
``G.I. Journal'' was on May 4, 1945. Hope's file reads: ``Spot:
Lucille Ball ... English play ... For Charity Bazaar.''
Hope and Ball had actually known each other before they began
working together. In fact, the late Desi Arnaz, her then husband,
worked for Hope first.
</P>
<P>
He said Ball asked him nearly 50 years ago to find a place on his
popular radio show for band leader Arnaz.
``Stan Kenton was leaving as my orchestra leader,'' Hope said.
``I gave Desi a spot on my show. We also gave him some lines to
speak. Every time he walked up to the microphone he dropped an
enchilada. He could hardly talk, let alone get a laugh. When they
started `I Love Lucy,' I said, `What's going on? This man is
funny.'''
``The night before she died I performed at the Music Center,'' he
said. ``Lucy was in the hospital and I saw her daughter, Lucie
Arnaz, and said, `Isn't it wonderful she's doing better.' They
called me the next day and said she had died. I said, `God has her
now, but we'll have her forever.' We'll be watching her performances
for a long, long time.''
``Bob Hope's Love Affair With Lucy'' will include clips from
their movies and TV appearances, plus such guest stars as Betty
White, George Burns and Danny Thomas.
``I'm going through everything myself picking out the clips,''
Hope said. ``The last time she was on my show was my birthday show
two years ago. We sang `I Remember It Well.' Our last time together
in public was at the Academy Awards in March. I think I'll do my
tribute to her over a shot of that in the background. I think
everyone remembers that.''
She was on his radio show on May 27, 1947, at Detroit. The
program notes say, ``Lucille Ball: New York, clothes, cars,
pictures.''
``I could do a fashion show with her walking on stage,'' Hope
said of the show clips he had been watching in preparing the
special. ``She had great gowns and hairdos. When she performed she
would use different styles. She'd change the way she read a line.
</P>
<P>
She'd throw a line away one time, then she'd turn around and milk a
line for laughs.''
Hope recalled his funny co-star in a sunny alcove in the living
room of his Los Angeles home. It overlooks the one-hole golf course
in the back yard, and he was attired in golfing clothes.
</P>
<P>
Occasionally, he called his office in another building on the
grounds to check on a piece of information. Soon after the
interview, he was aboard a plane for a series of personal
appearances around the country.
</P>
<P>
Ball made 22 appearances on Hope's specials and he was on her
shows 10 or 12 times, he said.
</P>
<P>
In their first movie, ``Sorrowful Jones'' in 1949, Hope played a
racetrack bookie who's forced to become the foster father of a young
girl whose real father was killed by gangsters in a racehorse fix.
</P>
<P>
Ball was a nightclub singer who helps him look after the girl. It
was a remake of ``Little Miss Marker,'' which starred Shirley Temple
in 1934.
</P>
<P>
Next was ``Fancy Pants'' in 1950, a remake of ``Ruggles of Red
Gap.'' Ball played a rich rancher who acquires an English butler,
played by Hope. ``Facts of Life'' was in 1960, with Hope and Ball as
married lovers who have a tryst. Their last film was ``Critic's
Choice'' in 1963, in which Hope is a Broadway critic who has to
review a play written by his wife, played by Ball.
``Someone reminded me the other night of a bus tour we did of
movie theaters in New York to promote one our of pictures,'' he
said. ``I think it was `Critic's Choice.' I found her very
cooperative, very wonderful. We always had a lot of fun together.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA042689-0146
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>4
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LUCILLE BALL DIES AT 77; 
THE WHOLE WORLD LOVED LUCY DURING TV'S GOLDEN AGE; 
SUFFERS AORTA RUPTURE AFTER HEART SURGERY 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Lucille Ball, the leggy showgirl, model and B-grade movie queen whose 
pumpkin-colored hair and genius for comedy made her an icon of television's 
early years, died early today, a week after undergoing emergency heart surgery. 
She was 77. 
</P>
<P>
The high-spirited star of "I Love Lucy," a show that the nation took to its 
heart as no other and that continues in syndication around the world, died of a 
ruptured abdominal aorta at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, hospital spokesman 
Ronald Wise said. 
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball, who had a heart attack and had throat surgery in 1988, underwent 
surgery at Cedars-Sinai on April 18 to replace her aorta and aortic valve and 
had been getting out of bed, eating and even walking around the room in recent 
days. 
</P>
<P>
Her recovery had seemed so certain that her husband, comedian Gary Morton, had 
been exchanging jokes with his wife. She had been asking about their white 
poodle, Tinker. 
</P>
<P>
Wise said the rupture occurred in a portion of the aorta, the main heart 
artery, far from where the operation was performed. 
</P>
<P>
Since the surgery fans had flooded the hospital with hundreds of cards, 
telegrams and even facsimile machine messages. Hospital officials said it was 
the largest outpouring they had ever seen. 
</P>
<P>
'Name Brings a Smile' 
</P>
<P>
Tributes were plentiful and immediate: 
</P>
<P>
"Her red hair, her antics on the screen, her timing and her zest for life made 
her an American institution," former President and Nancy Reagan said in a 
statement. "Just the mention of her name brings a smile. . . . We love Lucy and 
will miss her deeply." 
</P>
<P>
"Oh, what a blow. What a shame," said fellow TV clown Dick Van Dyke. "She 
didn't deal in jokes, she dealt in human behavior. She was a great physical 
mime with all the instincts of a Chaplin." 
</P>
<P>
William S. Paley, chairman of CBS Inc., said from New York: "Lucille Ball will 
always be the first lady of CBS. With 'I Love Lucy' she helped establish 
television as the nation's leading entertainment medium. Lucy's extraordinary 
ability to light up the screen and brighten our lives is a legacy that will 
last forever." 
</P>
<P>
That legacy involved Miss Ball and her late former husband, Cuban band leader 
Desi Arnaz. They starred regularly from 1951 to 1957 as Lucy and Ricky Ricardo 
in "I Love Lucy." The late Vivian Vance and William Frawley played their 
neighbors, Fred and Ethel Mertz. 
</P>
<P>
The series continued irregularly into the early 1960s. 
</P>
<P>
Talent as Entrepreneur 
</P>
<P>
Her singularity as a comedian was matched by her talent as a show-business 
entrepreneur. She and Arnaz established one of TV's first major independent 
studios. 
</P>
<P>
Desilu, as their production company was called, made some of the top comedy 
shows of the 1950s and '60s, including "December Bride," "Our Miss Brooks" and 
"Make Room for Daddy." 
</P>
<P>
As testament to their value as prime-time stars, Miss Ball and Arnaz signed an 
$8-million, no-cancellation, two-year contract with CBS in 1953 - the largest 
in television history at the time and a figure scarcely any TV star can touch 
36 years later. 
</P>
<P>
The actress was last seen introducing the "Young Hollywood" production number 
with Bob Hope at the 61st Academy Awards ceremony March 29, receiving a 
standing ovation. Looking svelte for her years in a fashionable slit skirt, she 
seemed to be in good health and laughed freely throughout a brief routine with 
Hope. 
</P>
<P>
Her last series - "Life With Lucy," co-starring frequent sidekick Gale Gordon 
- was carried by ABC at the start of the 1986 season. But the show, Miss 
Ball's first series in 12 years, was canceled after less than two months when 
it drew spectacularly low ratings. Miss Ball also played a bag lady in the 1985 
TV movie "Stone Pillow," considered one of the most challenging roles of her 
career. Her timing, wails and pratfalls had made the "I Love Lucy" show one of 
the most popular in television history. 
</P>
<P>
Bridge clubs and bowling teams changed their meeting nights to watch Lucy 
Ricardo and Ethel Mertz come up with yet another harebrained scheme to drive 
their long-suffering husbands, Ricky and Fred, to desperation. 
</P>
<P>
On-Screen Pregnancy 
</P>
<P>
A Chicago department store changed the night it stayed open because shoppers 
were staying home to watch television. 
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball's real, on-screen pregnancy marked a milestone in television, and an 
estimated 44 million viewers - more than watched the inauguration of President 
Dwight D. Eisenhower - tuned in on Jan. 19, 1953, the night Lucy Ricardo 
delivered Little Ricky. Her real son was born just four hours before the 
previously filmed show was broadcast. 
</P>
<P>
Lucille Ball was born in Jamestown, N.Y., the daughter of an electrician and a 
concert pianist. 
</P>
<P>
Young Lucy, a natural brunette, was dazzled by the stage, but her ambitions 
were discouraged by an acting school - "They sent my mother a letter saying 
she was wasting her money" - and she turned to modeling under the name Diane 
Belmont. 
</P>
<P>
Her ads for Chesterfield cigarettes caught the attention of Hollywood, and in 
1933 she was off to California. As a blonde, she appeared with the Marx 
Brothers in "Room Service," with Fred Astaire in "Follow the Fleet" and with 
Katharine Hepburn and Ginger Rogers in "Stage Door." 
</P>
<P>
In all, she appeared in more than 75 movies. 
</P>
<P>
CBS Wary of Arnaz 
</P>
<P>
In 1940, her tresses now the fiery trademark red, Miss Ball met Arnaz, a rumba 
star. They married within six months. 
</P>
<P>
In 1951, when CBS decided to move her radio series, "My Favorite Husband," to 
television, Miss Ball insisted that Arnaz be her co-star. But the network 
wasn't sure that Arnaz would be a hit with the American public. 
</P>
<P>
The couple went on a nationwide vaudeville tour and proved that audiences would 
sit still to watch a leggy, blue-eyed comedian and a Cuban-born band leader 
with a heavy accent. CBS relented and her antics became comedy classics: Lucy 
putting too much yeast in the bread, which quickly fills up her kitchen and 
pins her against the wall; Lucy fighting with a fellow grape-presser in a giant 
wine-making vat; Lucy rehearsing a commercial for a health tonic and becoming 
drunk from its alcohol content. 
</P>
<P>
The show also revolutionized television sitcom production in the days before 
videotape. It was filmed in advance before a live audience, employing three 
cameras instead of the traditional one used for motion pictures. 
</P>
<P>
Filming the shows also made them marketable as reruns, and they continue to be 
seen in more than 80 countries. 
</P>
<P>
Despite riches and two children, Lucie and Desi Jr., both of whom became 
actors, the marriage foundered, and the couple divorced in 1960. 
</P>
<P>
Arnaz died in 1986, Miss Vance in 1979 and Frawley in 1966. 
</P>
<P>
Photos of Miss Ball's family and television show on Page 2. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA042789-0025
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>27
</DAY> 
<MONTH>4
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LUCILLE BALL DIES; TV'S COMIC GENIUS WAS 77; 
DEATH CAUSED BY RUPTURED ABDOMINAL AORTA AS SHE APPEARED TO BE RECOVERING FROM 
SURGERY 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Lucille Ball, the leggy showgirl, model and B-grade movie queen whose pumpkin 
hair and genius for comedy made her an icon of television, died early 
Wednesday, a week after undergoing emergency heart surgery. 
</P>
<P>
The co-creator and star of "I Love Lucy," a product of TV's Golden Age that 
continues via syndication to be viewed by millions around the world, was 77 and 
died at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center of a ruptured abdominal aorta. 
</P>
<P>
Known simply as "Lucy" to four decades of smitten television fans, she had 
undergone surgery at Cedars-Sinai on April 18 to replace part of her aorta and 
aortic valve and had recovered from the 6 1/2-hour operation to a point where 
she was eating and even walking around her hospital room. 
</P>
<P>
Hospital spokesman Ronald Wise said the rupture occurred in a portion of the 
aorta, the main heart artery, far from where the operation was performed. 
</P>
<P>
She suffered a complete heart failure at 5 a.m., and 47 minutes of 
resuscitation efforts proved fruitless, Wise said. "There was nothing to 
indicate this would happen," Wise said. "The heart itself apparently was not 
involved in Miss Ball's sudden death." 
</P>
<P>
Since last week's surgery, fans had flooded the hospital with thousands of 
get-well cards, sent via telegram and even facsimile machine. Hospital 
officials said it was the largest outpouring they had ever seen. 
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball was a tough-talking woman who had used her stardom and show business 
savvy to become, with her then-husband, the late Desi Arnaz, head of one of 
Hollywood's major studios, Desilu. 
</P>
<P>
Despite her business acumen, she remained the unquestioned queen of television 
comedy. From her star-struck childhood through her struggles as a wisecracking 
movie actress in the 1930s and '40s to the television career that made her a 
legend, Miss Ball's life was in the best show business tradition of rags to 
riches. 
</P>
<P>
Almost humbly, she liked to say she owed her enormous success, not so much to 
talent, but to a magical combination of guts and good supporting players. Her 
greatest achievements, she always would add, were not any milestones in her 
career but ranked somewhere under the birth of her two children, Lucie in 1951 
and Desi Jr., two years later. 
</P>
<P>
"I am not funny," Ball told an interviewer for Rolling Stone magazine in 1983. 
"My writers were funny. My directors were funny. The situations were funny. . . 
. What I am is brave. I have never been scared. Not when I did movies, 
certainly not when I was a model and not when I did "I Love Lucy." 
</P>
<P>
It was "I Love Lucy," which premiered on CBS on Oct. 15, 1951, that earned Miss 
Ball her niche in television history. The 30-minute comedy starred Miss Ball 
and the Cuban-born Arnaz as the wacky Lucy Ricardo and her conga-playing 
husband Ricky. The show was a weekly dash into absurdity that boasted the 
biggest television audience of its time - of almost any time. 
</P>
<P>
Stopped the Nation 
</P>
<P>
In creating the show, Miss Ball and Arnaz - who died in 1986 - set a pattern 
of television that was to be repeated in decades to come. They filmed the 
programs in front of a live audience and in doing so, invented the popular and 
financially rewarding rerun. 
</P>
<P>
The show was so popular during the 1950s that it literally stopped the nation 
every Monday night from 9 p.m. to 9:30 p.m. In fact, nighttime shoppers became 
so scarce in Chicago that the mammoth Marshall Field department store posted a 
sign that read: "We Love Lucy, too, so from now on we will be open Thursday 
night instead of Monday." When presidential candidate Adlai E. Stevenson 
interrupted the show once for a political message, he was flooded with angry 
mail. 
</P>
<P>
Even a charge that Miss Ball was a Communist, made by the House Un-American 
Activities Committee in 1952, failed to dent her popularity. The charges, based 
on her registering to vote as a Communist in 1936, were dropped when Miss Ball 
explained she had done so only to please her ailing grandfather. Millions of 
sympathetic fans and a pragmatic CBS understood. 
</P>
<P>
A phenomenal 40 million viewers watched the antics each week as Lucy would 
always try to outwit Ricky. With their best friends and landlords, Fred and 
Ethel Mertz, played by veterans William Frawley and Vivian Vance as the perfect 
foils, the Ricardos found themselves mired in situations that frequently were 
rowdy and always ridiculous. 
</P>
<P>
A generation of Americans grew to recap their favorite Lucy episodes, plot 
twist by crazy twist. 
</P>
<P>
There was the time Lucy schemed her way onto Ricky's television show to do a 
commercial for a vegetable drink with a high alcoholic content and got 
hilariously tipsy during the many retakes. 
</P>
<P>
Then there was the time she threw in two packages of yeast while baking 
homemade bread and ended up pinned against the wall of her Manhattan kitchen by 
a monster loaf. 
</P>
<P>
And there was the time Lucy and Ethel, trying to impress their New York friends 
with the ultimate souvenir from a trip to Hollywood, pried loose the cement 
block containing John Wayne's footprints from in front of Grauman's Chinese 
Theater. Of course, the block broke. 
</P>
<P>
Week after week, Lucy would find herself trapped in a vat of laundry starch, 
locked in a meat freezer, or lost on a subway with a loving cup stuck on her 
head. Her turmoils permanently positioned her in the hearts of most Americans, 
including the critics. 
</P>
<P>
"An extraordinary discipline and intuitive understanding of farce give 'I Love 
Lucy' an engaging lilt," wrote New York Times critic Jack Gould. In its Lucy 
cover story, Time magazine said: "This is the sort of cheerful rowdiness that 
has been rare. . . . Lucille submits enthusiastically to being hit with pies; 
falls over furniture. . . . Tricked out as a ballerina or a Hindu maharani or a 
toothless hillbilly, she takes her assorted lumps and pratfalls with unflagging 
zest and good humor." 
</P>
<P>
In a 1981 interview in The Times, even Miss Ball admitted, "I love Lucy." 
</P>
<P>
"There were two key qualities to her," the comedienne said. "She was always in 
financial trouble - if she wanted a fur collar, a ratty little fur collar, she 
had to figure out a way to make some extra money to get it. . . . God, that's 
universal. And she always had a domineering figure over her. . . . Lucy was 
forever knocking somebody's top hat off." 
</P>
<P>
Miss Ball's personal favorite episodes were filmed when she was pregnant with 
Desi Jr. An amazing 44 million viewers, 90% of the television audience, 
gleefully watched on Jan. 19, 1953, when she gave birth on film to the show's 
little Ricky. To the unabashed delight of a nation, it was the same night she 
had given birth in real life. 
</P>
<P>
"I was so damned happy - just floating on a cloud - and I think the way I 
felt came across on the film," she said. "I loved doing all those pregnant 
shows." 
</P>
<P>
Astoundingly, or so it seems in retrospect, early reviews of Miss Ball's 
talents gave little hint of what was to come. In fact, when she was a plucky 
15-year-old looking for that first break on Broadway, Miss Ball was told by a 
drama teacher to give up. Luckily, the turquoise-eyed teen-ager ignored the 
advice. 
</P>
<P>
Born to an electrician father and pianist mother on Aug. 6, 1911, in a suburb 
of Jamestown, N.Y., Miss Ball had set her sights on stardom almost from the 
first. By 5, the brown-haired little girl was taking music lessons. Each spring 
that followed she would head toward New York City, walking until someone found 
her and returned her to her home. 
</P>
<P>
Leaving school at 15, Miss Ball finally made it to New York and the John Murray 
Anderson dramatic school. There was a brief stint in a Ziegfeld Follies road 
show and some short-lived appearances in a handful of Broadway chorus lines. 
</P>
<P>
Changing her name to Diane Belmont ("I always loved the name Diane and I was 
driving past the Belmont race track, and the names seemed to fit together") she 
turned to modeling. At various times a dress model and a hat model, Miss Ball, 
with long legs peeking out the bottom of a oversized cigarette pack, ultimately 
became a "Chesterfield girl." America grew to know her on billboards, magazine 
ads and on posters in its drugstore windows. 
</P>
<P>
Then in 1933, she headed to Hollywood. Her curly hair bleached a Jean Harlow 
platinum, Miss Ball was hired to work for six weeks in the chorus of Samuel 
Goldwyn's "Roman Scandals." Bit part after bit part stretched her stay to six 
months and she became a Hollywood fixture, taking second billing in the years 
that followed to everyone from The Three Stooges and Buster Keaton to Katharine 
Hepburn and Spencer Tracy. Along the way, she dyed her hair a fiery red and was 
given the unofficial title of "Queen of the Bs." 
</P>
<P>
Reviewers noted her "pert presence" and talent for "rubber-faced slapstick 
clowning." She was described in one newspaper as a "slangy, breezy wisecracking 
gal with a bebop rhythm to her walk." Said another, "Pretty Lucille Ball . . . 
was born for the parts Ginger Rogers sweats over." 
</P>
<P>
Playing the ingenue lead in the 1940 musical "Too Many Girls," Miss Ball met 
rumba singer Arnaz, cast as a Cuban football player. She later told an 
interviewer, "It was, at least for me, true love from the start." 
</P>
<P>
Exchanging vows seven months later, the pair began what was for the most part a 
troubled marriage. All but three of their first 11 years of marriage were spent 
apart. With Arnaz traveling the country with his band and Miss Ball committed 
to Hollywood sound stages, the pair spent almost $30,000 on telegrams and 
long-distance telephone calls. 
</P>
<P>
"We would end up talking on the phone - no, fighting on the phone," Miss Ball 
told interviewers. "You can't have a marriage over the phone. You can't have 
children over the phone. It became obvious that something had to be done." 
</P>
<P>
What was done to salvage the marriage was "I Love Lucy." 
</P>
<P>
Since CBS was stubbornly opposed to the idea of the heavily accented Arnaz 
playing the husband, the determined Arnazes created their own Desilu company 
and took a stage version of their show on the road to gauge public opinion. It 
was a smash, and television executives reluctantly gave "I Love Lucy" a time 
slot. 
</P>
<P>
"I wanted our characters to have problems," Miss Ball said of her concept for 
the show. "I wanted to be an average housewife. A very nosy but very average 
housewife. And I wanted my husband to love me. 
</P>
<P>
"CBS thought we were out of our minds to want to do it on film." 
</P>
<P>
The episodes were filmed before a live audience by Academy Award-winning 
cinematographer Karl Freund, famous for his work on such films as "The Good 
Earth" and Garbo's "Camille." When the Arnazes negotiated to keep the films "to 
show our kids someday," few in the industry predicted what would happen. 
</P>
<P>
"I remember (someone) saying, 'These films may be worth something someday,' " 
Miss Ball told The Times. "You should hang onto them. If Desi had that in mind, 
I never knew it. Maybe he knew he was creating the rerun but he never told me 
about it. All I knew was I was 40 years old and was having my first baby and I 
didn't want to do these shows and let them disappear into the air. I felt we 
could save the films for home movies. . . ." 
</P>
<P>
Instead, in the years since the original 153 "I Love Lucy" episodes were 
telecast, they have been shown and reshown in virtually every country around 
the globe, earning an estimated $50 million to $100 million. Miss Ball's face 
was one of the most recognized on Earth. 
</P>
<P>
But all of it was not enough to save her troubled marriage. To the horror of 
their television fans, Miss Ball and Arnaz were divorced in 1960. 
</P>
<P>
"He (Arnaz) was like Jekyll and Hyde," she said years later. "He drank and he 
gambled and he went around with other women. It was always the same: booze and 
broads." 
</P>
<P>
Breaking with the past, Miss Ball left Hollywood for New York and a starring 
role in the musical "Wildcat." The 1960 production floundered after only a few 
performances but during her stay in the East, she met stand-up comedian Gary 
Morton. They married in 1961. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, Arnaz and Miss Ball had sold their "I Love Lucy" films to CBS for $6 
million and she bought her ex-husband's interest in Desilu, becoming in effect, 
the first woman to head a major studio. It was by then home to 18 shows, 
including such hits as "The Untouchables" and "The Ann Sothern Show." Friend 
Bob Hope called her business sense "startling." 
</P>
<P>
"I never wanted to be an executive, but when my marriage to Desi broke up after 
19 years, I couldn't just walk away from my obligations and say 'forget it,' " 
Miss Ball explained. "We were an institution. Life takes guts. If you don't 
take chances, you'll never bathe again because you might get dirty again." 
</P>
<P>
Husband Morton said Miss Ball was blessed with an "innate business sense." 
</P>
<P>
"When she was running Desilu," he said, "she made decisions affecting the 
future of the company that often amazed board members, not because they were 
coming from a woman but because time usually proved her judgment to be 
correct." 
</P>
<P>
Among the shows Miss Ball tutored to success was her own "The Lucy Show," a 
series without Arnaz but with the same madcap clowning that kept her fans 
delighted. Among the guest stars attracted by the madness were Elizabeth Taylor 
and Richard Burton, the most glittering couple of the day. 
</P>
<P>
amp; Western Industries bought the property for a 
reported $17 million. 
</P>
<P>
In place of Desilu, Miss Ball, along with Morton, launched the much smaller 
Lucille Ball Productions Inc. and in 1968, began filming "Here's Lucy," a 
series featuring Desi Jr. and Lucie. 
</P>
<P>
"My life started when my children were born," Miss Ball said at the time. "I 
couldn't wait to work with them. . . . Even when they moved out of the house, 
they were still home at the studio. I liked that." 
</P>
<P>
The series aired through 1974. With her children's careers off the launching 
pad, the comedienne, then 63, decided it was time to retire her legendary 
character. "The Lucy character is too old to run around like an idiot," she 
said in explanation. 
</P>
<P>
That same year, she filmed her final motion picture, "Mame," a version of the 
Broadway musical. Although by now the world's best-known television star, as a 
movie star Miss Ball again received mixed reviews. Times critic Charles 
Champlin wrote, "The shame about 'Mame' is that it managed to deny us a Lucy to 
love." 
</P>
<P>
With those final starring credits to her name, she settled into co-producing 
shows, making occasional television appearances and accepting one after another 
of a continual barrage of awards and tributes. 
</P>
<P>
In addition to her 13 Emmy nominations (she won four), Miss Ball was feted in 
1976 with a nostalgic television tribute saluting the 25th anniversary of "I 
Love Lucy." Danny Kaye was among those who gave testimonials during the two 
hours of reminiscing. "Calling Lucille Ball just a comedienne is like calling 
Margot Fonteyn just a dancer," Kaye said. 
</P>
<P>
In 1984, when she was named one of seven initial inductees in the Television 
Hall of Fame, she credited the many "talented and creative people" around her 
for making her a legend. "I have been absolutely blessed," Miss Ball said. 
</P>
<P>
Role as Bag Lady 
</P>
<P>
The following year she took on one of the most challenging roles of her career: 
a bag lady in the television movie "Stone Pillow." She was hospitalized for 
dehydration when it was over, but it was a critical and ratings success. 
</P>
<P>
Her last flirtation with television came with her ill-fated and short-lived 
1986 series, "Life With Lucy," in which she again teamed with longtime sidekick 
Gale Gordon. It was quickly pulled by the network because of abysmal ratings. 
</P>
<P>
Her final public appearance proved to be during the 61st annual Academy Awards 
ceremony on March 29 when she joined her old friend Hope as a presenter. 
</P>
<P>
She had signed a contract with Putnam to publish her autobiography but died 
before she could begin work on it. 
</P>
<P>
Tearfully sentimental when it came to her husband and family, she reveled in 
life as a grandmother and glowed whenever she talked of her children. Their 
struggles and early failed marriages seemed not to matter. While she always 
spoke fondly of Arnaz, Miss Ball claimed that she had found the perfect mate in 
Morton. 
</P>
<P>
"He (Morton) takes care of me like I was his mother," she told an interviewer 
in 1981. "Gary gives me protection." On a scale of 1 to 10, Miss Ball said, "I 
rate my marriage to Gary a 12." 
</P>
<P>
But to her countless television fans - from the postwar babies who adored her 
during the '50s to their children and children's children who roared at her 
antics through decades of reruns - it was always Lucy and Ricky. More than a 
quarter-century of marriage to Morton could not erase that. There was always 
the hilarious image of the redhead and "that Cuban bongo player," as Miss Ball 
affectionately called him. 
</P>
<P>
Even years after the Lucy shows ended, the comedienne openly admitted to 
missing the characterization. 
</P>
<P>
"After Lucy ended, I thought, 'I'll live a few more years and then I'll die," 
she said in 1983. "I didn't plan on living this long. . . . Now I miss her. . . 
." 
</P>
<P>
Related Stories: Page 3 and Calendar, Page 1 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
BALL, LUCILLE; ACTRESSES; COMEDIANS 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA042789-0032
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>27
</DAY> 
<MONTH>4
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
FANS AND FAMOUS - ALL LOVED LUCY 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Presidents, famous actors, television executives, neighbors and tourists all 
had their memories. Some had known her; most had not. 
</P>
<P>
In form their sentiments ranged from flowers to telegrams to hand-lettered 
signs. Through them all ran a single, constant thread. 
</P>
<P>
They all said they loved Lucy, and they'll miss her. 
</P>
<P>
From former President and Mrs. Ronald Reagan: "Lucille Ball was a gifted 
comedienne who brought laughter to millions the world over. Her red hair, her 
antics on the screen, her timing and her zest for life made her an American 
institution." 
</P>
<P>
Reagan's successor extended his "deepest sympathy" to Miss Ball's family and 
called her a "legendary figure." "We too loved Lucy. So did the world," 
President Bush said in a statement. 
</P>
<P>
Lucille Ball had last appeared in public in March at the Academy Awards 
ceremony. Her co-presenter was Bob Hope, who a few hours after her death said 
simply, "God has her now, but thanks to television, we'll have her forever." 
</P>
<P>
The scene on North Roxbury Drive in Beverly Hills where Miss Ball spent her 
last and what she said were her happiest years was one of curiousity coupled 
with genuine mourning. About 20 people gathered on the sidewalk, some snapping 
photographs of the home and of the dozen television crews standing outside. 
</P>
<P>
Andy Stern, a neighbor, said that the large white house surrounded by 
snapdragons and bougainvillea was the most popular of all the homes on the 
Hollywood Stars' tours: "They (the buses) stop at her house more than any 
other." 
</P>
<P>
Another neighbor, Bob Rosati, said he was watching a rerun of "I Love Lucy" 
when the screen went black and the words "In Memory of Lucille Ball, 1911-1989" 
appeared. "I felt I had lost someone in my family," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Karen Pope, who described herself as an aspiring actress, drove from her Los 
Angeles home with a little container of flowers and a sign that read: "Lucy is 
seen in the smile of everyone's eyes." 
</P>
<P>
She left them with a guard at Miss Ball's home, turned away and said quietly: 
"She's touched all of us. She's not gone. She's just playing to a larger 
audience." 
</P>
<P>
Many of the people outside the house were like Karen Mestichelli from 
Philadelphia, a tourist who had purchased a map to the neighborhoods where many 
of the entertainment greats live. "This is the first house we stopped at," she 
said. "I loved her. She was good." 
</P>
<P>
In Paris, entertainer Sammy Davis Jr. called Miss Ball a "great artist - one 
of the world's greatest clowns." 
</P>
<P>
In Boston, comedian Lily Tomlin said: "It's a sad day for me. She was a great 
role model for me and a great funny woman." 
</P>
<P>
Comedian George Burns, another friend of many years, said, "As long as the 
world goes on, Lucy will be seen." 
</P>
<P>
Burns likened Miss Ball's death to that of his wife, Gracie Allen. "When Gracie 
died, it was a shock to me," he said. "This is a shock. Lucy and Gracie had one 
quality exactly alike. They both dressed like ladies and were very feminine." 
</P>
<P>
Television and film actor Danny DeVito recalled getting a personal 
congratulation from Miss Ball in 1981 when he won an Emmy for his work on the 
TV series "Taxi." 
</P>
<P>
"It made it like it had been blessed," he recalled. 
</P>
<P>
"To baby boomers, a happy chunk of our childhood is missing," said "Saturday 
Night Live" comedian Victoria Jackson, who was born two years after the "I Love 
Lucy" show went off the air as a regular series. "She didn't make me laugh out 
loud, I remember, she just made me happy about life." 
</P>
<P>
From William S. Paley, chairman of CBS Inc., where "I Loved Lucy" reigned for 
all those years: "Lucille Ball will always be the first lady of CBS. With 'I 
Love Lucy,' she helped establish television as the nation's leading 
entertainment medium. Lucy's extraordinary ability to light up the screen and 
brighten our lives is a legacy that will last forever." 
</P>
<P>
And then there were those at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center where she died. They 
had admired her as a celebrity for years but known her as a person for only 
days. 
</P>
<P>
A bouquet of red roses had been left in front of the center's north tower and 
calls were coming in from all over the world. 
</P>
<P>
"The telephone is ringing off the hook. People crying on the phone," said 
hospital spokeswoman Paula Correia. "It's a massive outpouring of grief from 
all ages." 
</P>
<P>
Maureen LaMour, a hospital admittance representative, said she heard the news 
of Miss Ball's death on her way to work. 
</P>
<P>
"We (the staff) always kept in touch with how she was doing and kept up with 
all the gifts and cards she received, because it was like they were for a 
family member," she said. 
</P>
<P>
"Everyone has grown up with her. Our children have grown up with her. She's a 
legend. It's like losing a friend, a family member, instead of a celebrity." 
</P>
<P>
Staff writer Burt A. Folkart contributed to this article. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
BALL, LUCILLE; FANS; MEMORIALS; HONORS 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA042789-0068
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>27
</DAY> 
<MONTH>4
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
EVERYBODY LOVED LUCY; 
LUCILLE BALL MADE IT ALL LOOK SPONTANEOUS 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Lucille Ball, whose death Wednesday morning at the age of 77 will be the most 
widely and deeply felt show-business loss in recent memory, was the movies' 
greatest gift to television. 
</P>
<P>
It turned out to be one of Sam Goldwyn's finest and most prophetic hours when 
he signed her as one of his Goldwyn Girls to appear in "Roman Scandals" with 
Eddie Cantor in 1933. She had had bit parts in two earlier films but "Roman 
Scandals" was the one that gave her a firmer foothold on the slippery slopes of 
a Hollywood career. 
</P>
<P>
The movies prepared her for television. She perfected her matchless craft as a 
comedienne in dozens of films, including three of Fred Astaire's and one of the 
Marx Brothers ("Room Service"). 
</P>
<P>
A lot of the other films caused few ripples on the wide surface of film 
history. But in those years Lucy was refining her enduring, endearing public 
image as a perky, saucy woman who was likelier (at least in the early days) to 
end up with the hero's funny pal than with the hero himself. 
</P>
<P>
Yet as often happened with supporting performers, her verve, an engagingly 
sharp tongue and a rather salty view of the world made her more interesting 
than the square-cut principals, and led to leading roles. 
</P>
<P>
To look at the "I Love Lucy" reruns today, as everybody does, again and again, 
is to realize how superbly professional they are. Today many sitcoms still use 
the three-camera technique, shooting in front of live audiences, that Desi 
Arnaz pioneered. 
</P>
<P>
The idea now seems as inevitable as the wheel or pre-sliced muffins, and yet 
you wonder if it would have worked nearly as well or caught on at all without 
Lucy's sheer expertise as a physical as well as a verbal comedienne. 
</P>
<P>
She made it all - even the wildest, craziest capers - look as if it were 
happening now - spontaneous, unrehearsed, accidental, the inevitable 
consequences of the screen Lucy's scatterbrained and lovable personality. Her 
foils - Desi himself, Vivian Vance and William Frawley - were superb farceurs 
themselves, but Lucy was the dynamo that made it all work. 
</P>
<P>
The craft was invisible, the skills so perfected they concealed themselves 
totally. It was a brilliant illusion, generating a charm that hid the hard work 
and the artful writing and editing as well as the performing. 
</P>
<P>
The result was probably the finest and certainly the most durable single series 
in television's history thus far. The appeal of the Lucy shows was also the 
most universal that American television has yet provided. 
</P>
<P>
They were wholly, prototypically American, and that is central to their 
popularity abroad. Yet they have been embraced as the kind of middle-class 
goings-on that might possibly arise almost anywhere there is a middle class. 
Lucy was all-American but, equally, a citizen of the world. 
</P>
<P>
Her successful career in films, in which she ultimately earned star billing if 
not superstar status, gave her an invaluable identification when "I Love Lucy" 
began. The irony is that, created by the movies, she was to achieve fame and 
fortune in television on a scale that had eluded her in the movies. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, when Lucy began to commandeer our hearts on "I Love Lucy" in 1951, the 
movies were already in considerable trouble, their audiences staying home in 
large numbers to watch the likes of Lucy in their living rooms. As always, her 
timing was impeccable. 
</P>
<P>
Lucille Ball was not Lucy, of course. She had come a hard road from Jamestown, 
N.Y., in a line of work in which you did not survive by being scatterbrained. 
She was smart, hard-working and a perfectionist who knew that whatever else it 
was, comedy was not accidental. 
</P>
<P>
Then again, the cameras, television or film, have X-ray properties, and the 
millions who saw and loved her were not wrong to think they perceived a 
generous and loving woman, as well as a glorious clown who knew the world was 
better off laughing. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
BALL, LUCILLE; HUMOR; COMEDIANS; TELEVISION - HISTORY 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
