<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900621-0186
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>21
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Iran Earthquake Caught Victims Asleep in Fragile Homes
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The earthquake that devastated Iran early
Thursday took tens of thousands of lives because people were asleep
in fragile homes built on flood plains, an earthquake expert said.
``Most casualties from earthquakes are caused by something
falling on top of you,'' said Russ Needham, a geophysist with the
U.S. Geological Survey that monitors ground motion around the world.
</P>
<P>
The quake hit at 12:30 a.m. in Iran, when most of the people
were in their homes, Needham said Thursday in a telephone interview
from Golden, Colo.
</P>
<P>
At least 25,000 people died and thousands were injured in the
quake, which demolished scores of villages and buried thousands of
people in the rubble of their homes, Iranian officials said.
</P>
<P>
Needham said most structures in that area are built of a
ceramic-type brick or adobe that collapses easily.
``It's very similar to what we had in Armenia,'' he said of the
Dec. 7, 1988, earthquake that killed about 25,000 people.
</P>
<P>
A Soviet parliamentary report later blamed the high number of
fatalities on shoddily built buildings.
</P>
<P>
The Armenian quake was measured at 6.9 on the Richter scale, but
Thursday's earthquake shook the earth with a magnitude of 7.7.
</P>
<P>
The shock wave traveled through the mountainous section of
coastal Iran where most of the buildings are built on a flood plain
of loosely deposited soil that shifts in an earthquake and allows
structures to collapse, he said.
</P>
<P>
The 7.7-magnitude quake was the largest ever recorded in that
area, where two major plates of the earth's crust meet, Needhams
said.
``Iran is in a very active seismic region,'' he said, and that
there have been many smaller quakes.
</P>
<P>
Twelve earthquakes greater than magnitude 7 have occurred in
Iran during the last 30 years, Needhams said.
</P>
<P>
A quake of magnitude 7 is considered a major earthquake, capable
of widespread, heavy damage in populated areas.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900622-0025
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Iran Earthquake Caught Victims Asleep in Fragile Homes
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The earthquake that struck northern Iran brought
reminders of another quake that devastated Soviet Armenia in 1988.
</P>
<P>
Like Thursday's earthquake in Iran, the Dec. 7, 1988, earthquake
in Armenia killed about 25,000 people. Most died in structures that
collapsed when the quake hit.
``It's very similar to what we had in Armenia,'' said Russ
Needham, a geophysicist with the U.S. Geological Survey.
</P>
<P>
The Armenian quake was measured at 6.9 on the Richter scale, but
Thursday's earthquake shook the earth with a magnitude of 7.7
according to the U.S. Geological Survey.
</P>
<P>
In the Iranian quake, the casualty count was pushed up by the
fact that people were indoors and asleep at the time, just after
midnight. Many of the victims lived in fragile homes built of a
ceramic-type brick or adobe that collapses easily.
</P>
<P>
In the Armenian quake, a Soviet parliamentary report later
blamed the high number of fatalities on shoddily built buildings.
``Most casualties from earthquakes are caused by something
falling on top of you,'' said Needham in a telephone interview from
Golden, Colo.
</P>
<P>
The quake struck an area of Iran where most of the buildings are
built on a flood plain of loosely deposited soil that shifts in an
earthquake and allows structures to collapse, Needham said.
</P>
<P>
The 7.7-magnitude quake was the largest ever recorded in that
area, where two major plates of the earth's crust meet, he said.
``Iran is in a very active seismic region,'' he said, and that
there have been many smaller quakes.
</P>
<P>
Twelve earthquakes greater than magnitude 7 have occurred in
Iran during the last 30 years, Needham said.
</P>
<P>
A quake of magnitude 7 is considered a major earthquake, capable
of widespread, heavy damage in populated areas.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900623-0022
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Group Claims Iran Underreporting Earthquake Casualties
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iran-Quake
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhoto WX21 of June 22
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iran is deliberately underreporting the number
of casualties from Thursday's massive earthquake out of fear of a
political backlash, leaders of a group seeking to overthrow the
country's Islamic leadership say.
``The regime is very much fearful of public outrage,'' said
Shahin Gobadi, spokesman for the People's Mojahedin of Iran.
``They're very much afraid of the political aftershocks.''
As Gobadi spoke Friday, members of the organization denounced
Iran's government at a noisy rally held in a park across the street
from the White House.
</P>
<P>
Northern Iran was stuck Thursday by an earthquake measuring
between 7.3 and 7.7 on the Richter Scale. Iran has told the United
Nations that the death toll is at least 36,000, but Gobadi said his
organization has received estimates closer to 100,000.
</P>
<P>
Gobadi said the country cannot properly assist earthquake
victims because its treasury has been spent in a war with
neighboring Iraq and against internal opposition.
``They have been very late in assisting the people,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Sympathy for the earthquake victims was a secondary issue for
the chanting, flag-waving rally participants, who also carried
signs criticizing their native country.
</P>
<P>
Planning for the event began three weeks before the earthquake,
but part of the Friday's activities focused on Iran's stricken
residents.
</P>
<P>
Gobadi said shoddy housing in which the government forced people
to live was the cause for the widespread loss of life.
``This regime has brought them nothing but devastation and
misery. This regime has devoted all of its resources to a senseless
war with Iraq and to oppression of the people at home,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
A U.N.-sponsored cease-fire was declared last year after eight
years of the Iran-Iraq war.
</P>
<P>
Iran's Islamic republic was established in 1979 after Shah
Mohammad Reza Pahlavi was deposed by Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini
and militants seized the U.S. Embassy in Tehran, taking 66
Americans hostage.
</P>
<P>
The United States broke diplomatic relations with Iran in April
1980. The shah died in exile in July 1980, U.S. hostages were freed
six months later and Khomeini died last June.
</P>
<P>
Gobadi said his 25-year-old group had helped depose the shah but
had no part in organizing the Islamic republic.
``Even in this tragedy for which we grieve we cannot trust the
regime in Iran,'' Rep. Mervyn Dymally, D-Calif., told an estimated
3,000 people attending the rally.
``There were many, many victims before this tragedy and there
are victims now whose needs need to be addressed by the people of
the United States,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Dymally, a member of the House Foreign Affairs Committee,
praised President Bush's offer of humanitarian aid to Iran but said
Bush must make sure the assistance is channeled through
non-government groups.
</P>
<P>
The State Department said Friday that Iran was willing to accept
earthquake relief from the American Red Cross and other U.S.
humanitarian organizations.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900623-0119
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Friendly, Hostile Countries Send Aid To Iran
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iran Quake,Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Countries worldwide, both friendly and hostile to Tehran's
Islamic government, sent supplies, medical personnel and
condolences to Iran, where about 40,000 people have died in an
earthquake.
</P>
<P>
Iran's deadliest earthquake since 1976 jolted the northern part
of the country Thursday, devastating towns and injuring at least
100,000 people.
</P>
<P>
The United States sent a message of condolence and expressed its
willingness to provide humanitarian aid.
</P>
<P>
Iran, which has had no diplomatic ties with the United States
since the 1979 seizure of hostages at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran,
said it would welcome relief from the American Red Cross and other
U.S. humanitarian groups.
</P>
<P>
Moderate Arab countries with which Iran has had prickly
relations _ Egypt, Saudi Arabia and Jordan _ also offered their
support.
</P>
<P>
An official statement distributed late Friday by the Saudi Press
Agency said the kingdom followed with ``deep sorrow'' the news of
the tragedy.
``The kingdom of Saudi Arabia ... declares its readiness to help
in extending assistance to those harmed by the tragedy, wishing to
help ease the pain of the afflicted from among the sons of the
Iranian Moslem nation,'' it said.
</P>
<P>
Jordan announced Saturday it was sending medical aid to Iran,
but details were not immediately clear.
</P>
<P>
King Hussein sent condolences to Iranian President Hashemi
Rafsanjani on Friday in what is believed to be the first direct
contact between Jordanian and Iranian heads of state in almost a
decade.
</P>
<P>
Jordan backed Iraq in the eight-year Iran-Iraq war, which ended
with a cease-fire in August 1988, and at one point sent hundreds of
Jordanian volunteers to fight alongside Iraqi soldiers.
</P>
<P>
Egypt was sending two military planes with supplies, the Middle
East News Agency reported. President Hosni Mubarak offered the aid
``in the framework of Egypt's concern to provide help for brothers
and friends, especially at times of natural disasters.''
The official Soviet news agency Tass reported that a
professional lifesaving team from the Armenian capital of Yerevan
flew Saturday to Iran. The team gained experience in the
devastating 1988 earthquake in Armenia that killed 25,000 people.
</P>
<P>
Thousands of residents in the predominantly Moslem Soviet
republic of Azerbaijan, which borders Iran, donated tons of flour,
rice and tea, and contributed more than $500,000 to a special
earthquake fund, Tass said.
</P>
<P>
The Italian Red Cross sent a plane to Iran Saturday with relief
supplies, including tents, blankets and medicine.
</P>
<P>
In Paris, the French government, which already has sent a
200-member civil defense team _ including rescuers, medical
personnel and search dogs _ said Saturday it would send an entire
mobile hospital unit if Iran wanted it.
</P>
<P>
In West Germany, the Foreign Ministry said that it was sending
tents, blankets, hospital equipment and cooking equipment to Iran.
</P>
<P>
Eight tons was being shipped Saturday and the government has
chartered a jumbo jet to transport 100 tons of equipment Monday.
</P>
<P>
At the Vatican, Pope John Paul II sent aid to earthquake victims
and a message of condolence to Iranian leaders.
</P>
<P>
The Vatican said in a statement that the donation of an
unspecified amount was to ``provide for the most immediate needs of
the population hurt by this huge earthquake.''
John Paul also sent a telegram to the papal nuncio, or
diplomatic representative, in Tehran saying the pope ``is praying
fervently for the wounded and the families of the victims.''
The Indian government said it would donate medicine, blankets
and other relief supplies worth more than $500,000.
</P>
<P>
China's Red Cross said it was sending $106,000 worth of relief
supplies, state-run television said Saturday.
</P>
<P>
The Polish government was sending 5 tons of powdered milk, a ton
of bed sheets, a ton of medicine and 3 tons of blankets and
clothing, according to Polish media reports.
</P>
<P>
Malaysia was providing more than $90,000 in relief aid. Foreign
Ministry Secretary-General Ahmad Kamil Jaafar told reporters
Saturday the money would be used to buy medicine, food, powdered
milk, tents and other essential items.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900624-0011
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>24
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Radical Paper Blames U.S., In Part, For Quake Damage
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>TEHRAN, Iran (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An anti-American newspaper in Iran said
Sunday the United States is partly to blame for the death of tens
of thousands of people in last week's earthquake.
</P>
<P>
The ``criminal role of America in Iran's past became evident
once again in the recent earthquake,'' the Jomhuri Islami said in
an editorial reported by the official Islamic Republic News Agency.
``Our people, even under the rubble, chant `Death to America'
and pray to God to cut off the hands of the United States ... even
those hands stretched out to help,'' it said.
</P>
<P>
It argued that by ``plundering Iran's oil and other resources''
for 25 years, the United States had prevented the use of even a
small part of the national wealth for urban development projects
and ``advanced (anti-seismic) building construction systems.''
``Even after its expulsion from Iran, the U.S. government by
imposing economic sanctions and launching several other plots,
halted the renovation of the country,'' the editorial added.
</P>
<P>
The newspaper was implying that with these actions the United
States had blocked the diversion of funds to earthquake safety
measures.
``If the United States has real humanitarian objectives and
intended to help the Iranian nation, it should do only one thing,
stop hatching plots,'' the newspaper said.
</P>
<P>
It called on Iranians to reject relief offers by the United
States and ``other governments whose hands are stained with the
blood of the Iranian people.''
Iran, at odds with the United States since the 1979 seizure of
hostages at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran, has said it would welcome
relief from the American Red Cross and other U.S. humanitarian
groups. The two nations have no diplomatic ties.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900625-0153
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>25
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Five Decades of Major Earthquakes Worldwide
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iran-Quake, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The estimated 50,000 dead in the Iran earthquake make it the
world's fourth deadliest quake in the past half-century. Here is a
list of the major quakes of the past 50 years. The location is
followed by the Richter scale magnitude and the number of dead.
</P>
<P>
Iran, June 21, 1990, 7.3 to 7.7 on the Richter scale, 50,000
dead (estimated).
</P>
<P>
Soviet Armenia, Dec. 7, 1988, 6.9, 25,000.
</P>
<P>
Iran, Sept. 16, 1978, 7.7, 25,000.
</P>
<P>
China, July 28, 1976, 8.2, 200,000 officially, 800,000
unofficially.
</P>
<P>
Guatemala, Feb. 4, 1976, 7.5, 22,778.
</P>
<P>
Peru, May 31, 1970, 7.7, 66,794.
</P>
<P>
Iran, Aug. 31, 1968, 7.4, 12,000.
</P>
<P>
Iran, Sept. 1, 1962, 7.1, 12,230.
</P>
<P>
Morocco, Feb. 29, 1960, 5.8, 12,000.
</P>
<P>
Soviet Turkmenia, Oct. 5, 1948, (no Richter reading available),
110,000.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA062290-0169
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
IRAN ACCEPTS U.S. HELP; 
EARTHQUAKE DEATH TOLL HITS 35,000 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iran said today that it would welcome relief offered by its bitter enemy, the 
United States, to help victims of the earthquake that has killed as many as 
35,000 people, the State Department said in Washington. 
</P>
<P>
The aid would be accepted through the American Red Cross and other U.S. 
humanitarian organizations, deputy spokesman Richard Boucher said. 
</P>
<P>
"We want to be helpful without regard for our political differences with Iran," 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
There have been only rare instances of U.S.-Iranian cooperation since the two 
countries broke diplomatic relations a decade ago. The United States holds Iran 
partly responsible for the continued detention of American hostages by 
pro-Iranian groups in Lebanon. 
</P>
<P>
Boucher said Iran told the U.S. government that private donor agencies should 
contact the Iranian Red Crescent, a humanitarian group that is the conduit for 
all outside assistance. 
</P>
<P>
The U.S. government routinely channels humanitarian assistance through the Red 
Cross and other donor groups. 
</P>
<P>
Boucher said the Iranian message to the United States presumably was delivered 
through a third party but added that he was uncertain. Messages between the two 
countries normally are handled by the Swiss Embassy in Tehran. 
</P>
<P>
Iranian authorities have told United Nations officials that about 35,000 people 
died in the earthquake. 
</P>
<P>
Iran reportedly said it would accept aid from all countries - including Iraq 
- but excluded Israel and South Africa. 
</P>
<P>
Rescuers in Iran today freed thousands of people from buildings flattened by 
the earthquake in northern Iran, which struck early Thursday and had a 
magnitude between 7.3 and 7.7. 
</P>
<P>
The Islamic Republic News Agency said 6,000 people were pulled from rubble and 
airlifted from the stricken Gilan and Zanjan provinces to hospitals. 
</P>
<P>
Iranian television showed scenes of devastation, including the remains of an 
entire row of hillside village houses that collapsed and slid down the hill. 
</P>
<P>
Rescuers scooped up rubble and used police dogs to find victims. They gently 
fed water to one man who was trapped in a mass of stones and earth, only his 
head protruding. 
</P>
<P>
The Iranian Red Crescent asked for help in providing shelter for 400,000 people 
left homeless by the earthquake. Offers of help came from across the globe. 
</P>
<P>
The death toll was higher than a quake that killed 25,000 people in nearby 
Soviet Armenia in December, 1988, and a quake in Iran in 1978 that also killed 
25,000. 
</P>
<P>
In scenes shown on television, masked rescuers in white aprons pulled 
dust-covered bodies from under concrete slabs. Corpses were laid on blocks of 
ice in open trucks. 
</P>
<P>
The state-run television interviewed one middle-aged man from Roodbar, a 
mountainside village in Gilan province, who said he was sleeping when the 
temblor struck. 
</P>
<P>
"It was so strong," he said. "I was thrown several meters, I ended up by the 
olive trees," outside his home. "Then a big boulder hit the house. The house 
collapsed. I lost all four of my children." 
</P>
<P>
* Photos of Iran's devastating earthquake. See Back Page 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA062390-0001
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
SAN DIEGANS AWAIT WORD ON IRAN RELATIVES 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Shortly after 2 p.m. Wednesday, San Diego resident Mohammad Nyakoui got a call 
from his wife, who is spending the summer in the Caspian Sea coastal city of 
Rasht, Iran, with her family. 
</P>
<P>
"I asked her what she was doing, and she said she was watching the World Cup," 
Nyakoui recalls. 
</P>
<P>
About 15 minutes after she hung up, Rasht and other cities in Iran's northern 
region were rocked by an earthquake that killed thousands. 
</P>
<P>
Back home in San Diego, it was several hours before Nyakoui even heard news of 
the quake. When he did, some quick time-zone arithmetic showed that he had 
talked to his wife just minutes before the quake happened. 
</P>
<P>
"I was very worried," Nyakoui said. "I tried through the Red Cross to call 
Iran, but they told us they couldn't do anything before 48 hours passed." 
</P>
<P>
One of about 25,000 San Diego Iranians in the same anxious state, Nyakoui was 
luckier than most: His wife managed to call him a second time that day, about 
eight hours after the quake, to tell him she and their two children were safe. 
</P>
<P>
Phone lines remained jammed Friday, other Iranian-Americans in San Diego said. 
</P>
<P>
"There's a sense of panic. It's just impossible to get through," said Houshang 
Ghashghai, who teaches political science at San Diego State University. 
</P>
<P>
Already though, some of the worried immigrants were turning their fear into 
action by mobilizing relief efforts for Iran. 
</P>
<P>
Hamid Biglari, a theoretical physicist at UC San Diego, was among those who 
organized a local group to gather contributions for the United Nations Fund for 
the Iran Earthquake. 
</P>
<P>
The group has set up two offices and phone lines. They are collecting medicine, 
food and a variety of living supplies, including blankets, light clothing and 
flashlights. The supplies will be transported by the United Nations, Biglari 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Another group gathering medical supplies is Southwest Medical Teams, an 
organization whose last major international effort was sending volunteers and 
medical supplies to Armenia after the 1988 quake there. 
</P>
<P>
Southwest Medical Teams won't be sending any volunteers this time, said 
director Barry La Forgia. 
</P>
<P>
"That's at the advice of the State Department. They couldn't ensure our safety 
over there, and we don't want to endanger any of our volunteers," La Forgia 
said. 
</P>
<P>
WHERE TO SEND AID 
</P>
<P>
Donations for Iranian earthquake relief are being taken in San Diego by two 
groups: 
</P>
<P>
 United Nations Fund for the Iran Earthquake (467-1120 or 456-4000) - 
Collecting antibiotic and analgesic drugs, collapsible plastic water 
containers, plastic sheeting, 220-volt portable generators of less than 10 
kilowatts, tents, blankets, dry food, light clothing, flashlights and lighting 
equipment. Bring items or mail checks to 4540 Kearny Villa Road, Suite 214, San 
Diego 92123; or to 7509 Girard Ave., Suite A, La Jolla 92037. Checks should be 
made out to the U.N. Fund for the Iran Earthquake. 
</P>
<P>
Southwest Medical Teams (284-7979) - Through Thursday, collecting sutures, 
surgical gloves, antibiotics, analgesics (including aspirin), vitamins, 
ophthalmic solutions and empty blood collection bags. Shipment will be sent 
July 2. Cash donations will be used to pay to fly the supplies to Iran. Mail 
checks to 3547 Camino del Rio South, Suite C, San Diego 92108, noting that 
donation is for Iranian Earthquake Relief Fund. 
</P>
<P>
 Other agencies accepting donations for Iranian earthquake victims: 
</P>
<P>
Adventist Development and Relief Agency 
</P>
<P>
12501 Old Columbia Pike 
</P>
<P>
Silver Spring, Md. 20904 
</P>
<P>
(301) 680-6380 
</P>
<P>
American Red Cross 
</P>
<P>
Iran Earthquake Disaster 
</P>
<P>
P.O. Box 37243 
</P>
<P>
Washington, D.C. 20013 
</P>
<P>
(800) 842-2200 
</P>
<P>
Bank Melli Iran 
</P>
<P>
Iran Quake Relief Assistance 
</P>
<P>
Account No. 5000 
</P>
<P>
628 Madison Ave. 
</P>
<P>
New York, N.Y. 10022 
</P>
<P>
U.S. Committee for UNICEF 
</P>
<P>
333 E. 38th St. 
</P>
<P>
New York, N.Y. 10016 
</P>
<P>
(212) 686-5522 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA062490-0172
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>24
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
SOVIET TRUCKS CARRY QUAKE AID TO IRAN; 
NEIGHBORS: GORBACHEV SENDS CONDOLENCES, RESCUE CREWS, SUPPLIES. AZERBAIJAN 
DECLARES DAY OF MOURNING. 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
MOSCOW 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Trucks carried aid into earthquake-stricken Iran on Saturday from Soviet 
Azerbaijan, which observed a day of mourning for victims, the official Tass 
news agency said. 
</P>
<P>
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev sent his condolences to the Iranian leadership, 
and the Soviet Red Cross dispatched a plane carrying rescue workers and aid. 
</P>
<P>
In his message to Iranian President Hashemi Rafsanjani, Gorbachev expressed his 
"deep condolences to the families and friends of those who lost their lives in 
the earthquake." 
</P>
<P>
A report by Tass from the Azerbaijan capital of Baku said an official day of 
mourning was declared in the mainly Muslim republic and that black ribbons hung 
from public buildings in the city. 
</P>
<P>
A column of trucks carrying 100 doctors, 10,000 tons of food, clothing and 
equipment such as welding gear left the town of Nakhicheva near the border. 
</P>
<P>
Tass said people in Azerbaijan, many of whom are Shiite Muslims who feel a 
kinship with people of their faith in Iran, poured money into a public fund for 
earthquake victims. Other volunteers donated blood, it said. 
</P>
<P>
A Soviet Red Cross official said a plane left Moscow carrying relief aid, nine 
doctors and rescue workers. 
</P>
<P>
In December, 1988, a powerful earthquake killed 25,000 people in Soviet 
Armenia, which borders Azerbaijan. 
</P>
<P>
Also on Saturday, aid continued to pour into Iran from other parts of the 
world. 
</P>
<P>
A 205-member French relief team arrived Friday night, according to Iran's 
official Islamic Republic News Agency (IRNA). West Germany said it was sending 
200 tents and 3,200 blankets, to be followed by 100 tons of similar supplies. 
Jordan and Kuwait also said they are sending planeloads of relief aid. 
</P>
<P>
The European Community has granted $1.2 million in emergency aid, and Japan is 
reportedly sending between $500,000 and $1 million in cash as well as a 
22-member medical and rescue squad. 
</P>
<P>
The United States on Friday sent $300,000 worth of relief supplies through the 
American Red Cross and is planning more aid, State Department officials said. 
</P>
<P>
Pope John Paul II was "very saddened" by the earthquake and has donated 
personal funds to help victims of the disaster, the Vatican said. 
</P>
<P>
Spokesman Joaquin Navarro did not specify the amount, but in the past the Pope 
has sent as much as $100,000 for disaster relief from his personal funds. 
</P>
<P>
Other assistance reportedly was due from Holland, Turkey, Greece, Pakistan, 
Belgium, Finland, India, Bangladesh, Yugoslavia, Sri Lanka, Kuwait and several 
other nations. 
</P>
<P>
Iranian officials have said they would welcome aid from all countries except 
Israel and South Africa. 
</P>
<P>
However, Egyptian officials in Cairo said Iran rejected an Egyptian offer to 
send a planeload of medical supplies. A source at the Foreign Ministry said 
Iran rejected the supplies, saying it needed heavy equipment. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
EARTHQUAKES - RELIEF; IRAN - RELIEF; DISASTERS - RELIEF; RELIEF 
ORGANIZATIONS; DISASTER RELIEF; GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S; IRAN - FOREIGN RELATIONS 
- USSR 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA062690-0155
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
WORLD; 
RUSHDIE DONATES QUAKE AID; IRAN SAYS HE'S STILL DOOMED 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
LONDON 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Writer Salman Rushdie, who has been sentenced to die by Iranian zealots, has 
donated $8,600 to victims of last week's devastating earthquake in Iran. Iran 
said today his death order still stands. 
</P>
<P>
Rushdie donated the money to the Independent Iranian Earthquake Appeal, 
organized by the Independent newspaper to help survivors of the earthquake that 
Iranian officials said left at least 50,000 people dead. 
</P>
<P>
"I wanted to join the Independent and the hostage families and many other 
people in their appeal for contributions toward the needs of the Iranian 
earthquake victims," Rushdie said in a message delivered from his hiding place. 
</P>
<P>
"It's quite clear that at the moment, we should be thinking only of the 
humanitarian issue, which transcends all other discussion," said Rushdie, 42. 
</P>
<P>
The Indian-born writer has been out of public view since Feb. 14, 1989, when 
the late Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini sentenced him to death for writing "The 
Satanic Verses," a novel many Muslims regard as blasphemous. 
</P>
<P>
"The foreign media seems to think that by publishing news of aid from Salman 
Rushdie to earthquake victims, we will compromise on Rushdie's fatwa (edict)," 
Ayatollah Sadeq Khalkhali, known as the "Hanging Judge," said in Tehran. He 
indicated they would not. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
