<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890603-0103
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>03
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
URGENT
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Death Toll at 32 as Troops Storm Tiananmen Square
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with armored personal carriers entering
square; U.S. reaction; no pickup
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Chinese troops stormed Tiananmen Square early
Sunday, shooting and beating their way through crowds of
pro-democracy protesters in clashes that witnesses and doctors said
killed at least 32 people. Hundreds were wounded.
</P>
<P>
The troops cut a violent swath through the heart of Beijing to
get to the the square, rolling through barricades and surging
masses on the surrounding streets.
</P>
<P>
By 3:30 a.m., soldiers and riot police had surrounded Tiananmen,
boxing off several thousand students and supporters concentrated
around a monument to revolutionary heroes in the center.
</P>
<P>
A half hour later, lights were turned out. The square was in
darkness.
``You have to give up all hope,'' students said over their
loudspeaker at the monument. ``You have to give your life to the
movement.''
Students sang the ``Internationale,'' the communist anthem.
</P>
<P>
At 4:30 a.m., armored personnel carriers entered the square and
troops began moving slowly toward several thousand students
clustered around a monument to revolutionary heroes in the center.
</P>
<P>
Sporadic gunfire could still be heard on the outskirts of the
square as troops shot at crowds of thousands. The death and
casualty toll was believed to be mounting rapidly. Ambulances and
bicycle pedicabs went back and forth hauling away the wounded.
</P>
<P>
One man was seen shot in the back, another in the head.
</P>
<P>
An official loudspeaker on the square announced that the troops
were moving in to clear the area as soldiers prepared to advance
from all four sides.
</P>
<P>
Ho Te-chien, a Taiwanese singer who defected to China in 1983
and has been active in the student movement, urged the students to
leave. ``We're not afraid to die, but we've already lost too much
blood,'' he said over a student loudspeaker.
</P>
<P>
A 33-foot-high replica of the Statue of Liberty, set up by
students last week, remained standing.
</P>
<P>
The main streets leading to the Tiananmen, China's symbolic
political center, were sealed. Thousands fled from the square,
where hundreds of thousands of people had gathered to support
students in the third week of a sit-in.
</P>
<P>
The assault came two weeks after Premier Li Peng declared
martial law in Beijing and sent troops to the city. Hundreds of
thousands of residents responded by blocking roads with trucks and
their bodies.
</P>
<P>
In Washington, Secretary of State James A. Baker III said
Saturday the situation in China had become ``ugly and chaotic.
``This will disturb the United States government, and will
disturb the American people, considerably,'' he said. The secretary
hinted that there could be repercussions to the Chinese
government's use of violence.
</P>
<P>
The standoff between troops and protesters had been tense but
largely peaceful for weeks, with soldiers seemingly reluctant or
unable to move against the crowds until the first widespread
violence broke out Saturday afternoon.
</P>
<P>
A doctor from the Fuxing Hospital in western Beijing, where
troops began firing on street people, said the hospital had taken
in 15 dead and so many wounded they had to be put in garages.
</P>
<P>
A doctor from another hospital said 12 people died there.
</P>
<P>
One soldier was killed when he was run over by an armored
personnel carrier rushing toward the square, and another man was
reported shot to death in a street clash elsewhere.
</P>
<P>
A Swedish visitor, Tom Hansson, said he saw three people shot to
death in clashes south of the square.
``The government is fascist! How can they do this to me? How can
they do this to the people?'' cried a 28-year-old man who was shot
in the leg.
</P>
<P>
Most of those shot on the square were hurling rocks at the
troops and people close to their front lines.
</P>
<P>
A government loudspeaker on the square charged the students with
``counterrevolutionary turmoil'' and said the military was taking
necessary means to end their rebellion.
</P>
<P>
Sporadic clashes and dozens of injuries were reported on
Saturday as soldiers made several attempts to reach the square.
</P>
<P>
They retreated momentarily under barrages of rocks, shoes and
other objects, then resumed their most violent push at about 8 p.m.
</P>
<P>
Saturday, firing weapons and using tear gas and clubs as they moved
toward Tiananmen.
</P>
<P>
Thousands of troops armed with rifles marched up the east side
of the square, beating people who got in their way. Students threw
Molotov cocktails and other objects at them.
</P>
<P>
One armored personnel carrier rammed into a burning bus on
Changan Avenue, the main street running along the square, and was
torched by students. Two people inside were dragged out by the
crowds and beaten severely.
</P>
<P>
Other armored personnel carriers drove up and down the avenue
smashing down lane dividers and other barriers set up by citizens
to block the army's way.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890603-0108
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>03
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Chronology of Events in China
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Eds: UPDATES with latest developments, includes events between May
26 and June 2
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here is a look at key events in the student
pro-democracy movement that led to Sunday's assault by soldiers on
protesters in Tiananmen Square:
April 15 _ Former Communist Party chief Hu Yaobang dies. Beijing
University students put up posters praising him and indirectly
criticizing opponents who forced his resignation after student
demonstrations in 1986-87.
</P>
<P>
April 17 _ Thousands of students march in Beijing and Shanghai,
shouting ``Long live Hu Yaobang! Long live democracy!''
April 27 _ More than 150,000 students, with wide support from
people on the street, surge past police lines and fill Tiananmen
Square, chanting slogans for democracy and freedom.
</P>
<P>
April 29 _ Officials meet with student leaders, but independent
student groups are not satisfied and continue a class boycott at 41
universities.
</P>
<P>
April 30 _ Beijing's Communist Party chief, Zhao Ziyang, meets
with student representatives.
</P>
<P>
May 4 _ About 100,000 students and supporters march on Tiananmen
Square to celebrate the 70th anniversary of China's first student
movement. Demonstrations are held in Shanghai, Nanjing and other
cities. About 300 journalists protest outside the official Xinhua
News Agency.
</P>
<P>
May 9 _ Journalists petition the government for press freedom.
</P>
<P>
May 10 _ Thousands of students bicycle to major media offices in
a press freedom demonstration. Another protest is held in the
provincial capital of Taiyuan.
</P>
<P>
May 13 _ About 2,000 students begin a hunger strike in Tiananmen
Square.
</P>
<P>
May 14 _ Thousands flock to the square to back the students. The
number fasting rises to 3,000.
</P>
<P>
May 15 _ The government deadline for students to leave the
square passes. Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's welcoming
ceremony planned near the square must be moved to the airport.
</P>
<P>
May 16 _ Hundreds of thousands occupy the square. Journalists
and intellectuals join the protest.
</P>
<P>
May 17 _ Zhao pleas for students to leave. Students reject his
appeal and hold marches that generate 1 million supporters in
Beijing.
</P>
<P>
May 18 _ About 1 million people, including many workers, again
take to the streets to show their support for the hunger strikers.
</P>
<P>
Li Peng issues a stern lecture to student leaders and refuses to
discuss their demands.
</P>
<P>
May 19 _ A tearful Zhao visits weakened hunger strikers. Li also
visits the students briefly. The students later decide to end the
hunger strike.
</P>
<P>
May 20 _ Martial law is declared in parts of Beijing. Zhao
reportedly resigns after failing to persuade Li and other
hardliners to compromise. Students resume their hunger strike, then
abandon it, saying they will need their strength for the struggle
ahead.
</P>
<P>
May 21 _ Students claim to reject an order by Li Peng to leave
the Tiananman Square or face military action. Defying martial law,
hundreds of thousands of people remain in the square or block
intersections to prevent troops from reaching it.
</P>
<P>
May 22 _ Hundreds of thousands of people again block major roads
and senior military leaders say they are resisting orders to order
their troops on the protesters. At least one military convoy is
reported to withdraw.
</P>
<P>
May 23 _ One million people take to the streets to demonstrate
for democracy.
</P>
<P>
May 25 _ Li makes his first appearance since declaring martial
law. State- run radio says 27 of 29 provinces support martial law,
and military units announce they support martial law.
</P>
<P>
May 26 _ Sources say Zhao and another leading liberal, Wan Li,
head of the legislature, are under house arrest.
</P>
<P>
May 27 _ Beijing student leaders propose students end their
occupation of Tiananmen Square. Non-Beijing students resist and the
sit-in continues.
</P>
<P>
May 28 _ About 80,000 people, many students from outside the
capital, stage a demonstration, but unlike in past rallies few
workers participate.
</P>
<P>
May 30 _ Students unveil their ``Goddess of Democracy,'' a
replica of the Statue of Liberty, on the square. The government
calls it an insult to the nation. Students rally outside police
headquarters to protest the detention of three members of an
independent labor union.
</P>
<P>
May 31 _ The first of several pro-government rallies is staged
by farmers and workers in Beijing suburbs. The participants,
ordered to show up, show little enthusiasm.
</P>
<P>
June 1 _ The Beijing Municipal Government warns foreign
journalists that under martial law they must receive approval for
all press coverage. Coverage of the demonstrations is banned.
</P>
<P>
June 2 _ More than 1,000 troops appear outside the railway
station in a show of force.
</P>
<P>
June 3-4 _ Tens of thousands of troops make several attempts to
move on the square but are driven back by crowds of hundreds of
thousands of people supporting the students. Riot squads beat and
fire tear gas at demonstrators. A final push is made the evening of
June 3, and soldiers begin firing on crowds. Troops surround and
enter the square June 4 in the early morning hours and thousands of
protesters flee. Hundreds are wounded and many dead.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890603-0122
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>03
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Chronology of Violence Around Tiananmen Square
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-China, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here is a chronology of events that began
Saturday in Tiananmen Square:
1 a.m. Saturday (12 noon EDT Friday) _ Tens of thousands of
troops enter Beijing from the east marching toward Tiananmen
Square, China's symbolic political heart. Military units also seen
approaching from the west and the north.
2 a.m. _ The main body of troops is stopped several hundred
yards east of the vast square by thousands of people.
2 a.m. to 9 a.m. _ Troops straggle away from their positions
near the square, walking in small groups followed by watchful
residents.
12 noon _ Two truckloads of People's Armed Police attack crowds
outside Beijing Hotel east of the square and up to 30 people
injured.
2 p.m. _ About 5,000 troops emerge from Great Hall of the People
on the western side of the square and are surrounded by crowds.
</P>
<P>
People's Armed Police fire tear gas and use clubs to beat
protesters west of the square in a 30-minute attack.
4:30 p.m. _ Stone- and bottle-throwing demonstrators skirmish
with troops outside the Great Hall. Troops swinging belts attack
crowds. Some soldiers injured by flying debris.
6 p.m. _ Thousands of residents surround two troop convoys on a
main highway in northeastern Beijing.
7 p.m. _ National television repeats martial law regulations and
warns people to stay off the streets and away from Tiananmen Square.
8:30 p.m. _ Troops retreat into the Great Hall.
9 p.m. _ More than 20,000 people block a 26-truck convoy about
2{ miles east of the square and thousands of others converge on the
square to protect students demanding demoncratic reforms.
</P>
<P>
Crowds throw rocks at troop contingent 4{ miles west of
Tiananmen.
9 p.m.-10 p.m. _ Troops hurl tear gas then open fire on the
crowds.
12 midnight _ Armored vehicles break through barricades and
about 40 trucks carrying military personnel slowly advance toward
the square from the west.
1 a.m. Sunday. Troops dash through flames caused by a
burning-bus barricade at the major intersection of Xidan west of
the square. More people shot as troops fire at crowds.
</P>
<P>
A smaller group of about 1,000 military personnel enters the
square from the east and shooting erupts.
2 a.m. _ Thousands of troops arrive at the west side of the
square and some of the riflemen open fire.
3:30 a.m. _ Military units surround the square, trapping several
thousand students inside.
4:30 a.m. _ Armored personnel carriers enter the square.
</P>
<P>
Students are told by loudspeaker that troops will move in and clear
the area.
5 a.m. _ Demonstrators, many walking hand-in-hand, begin leaving
the square, ending their three-week occupation.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890603-0126
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>03
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Tiananmen Square Resembles Battlefield in Assault on Students
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-China, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Dawn broke Sunday over a battle-scarred Tiananmen
Square with tanks and rifle-toting troops ruling the vast expanse
occupied the day before by students seeking a freer society from
their communist rulers.
</P>
<P>
A low cloud of smoke covered much of the 100-acre square as
bonfires set during the night's confrontation continued to smolder.
</P>
<P>
Hundreds of helmeted troops were deployed on the monument to
revolutionary heroes in the square's center and thousands more at
important intersections nearby. Tanks moved into place on what had
hours earlier been a rag-tag squatter's camp of tents for the
pro-democracy students.
</P>
<P>
The battle for Tiananmen was primarily fought in the streets
leading to the square, where scores of people fell trying to
prevent columns of troops and armored military vehicles from moving
on the students.
</P>
<P>
Gunfire could be heard from several sides, and tracers zipped
through the sky above Mao Tse-tung's mausoleum, one of the main
monuments to Chinese communism in the square. Torched buses and
army vehicles on the streets around Tiananmen billowed acrid smoke.
</P>
<P>
Troops first entered the square from the south, when a column
trotted toward the student encampment about 1 a.m. (noon EDT
Saturday). They took up positions to the east after a brief
skirmish involving clubs and sticks with students.
</P>
<P>
More soldiers were deployed in front of the Great Hall of the
People to the west, and a huge convoy with armored vehicles rolled
down Changan Avenue to the north side.
</P>
<P>
The few thousand students remaining in the square stayed calm as
they quietly gathered on the steps of the heroes' monument. ``I'm
not afraid,'' several said as the heavily armed troops encircled.
</P>
<P>
Hundreds of supporters continued to mill around the square, many
dressed more for a summer outing than a military battle.
</P>
<P>
Loudspeakers blaring government and student announcements
engaged in a noisy propaganda battle throughout the night.
``The government is corrupt, you've been tricked,'' the students
roared. The state-run speaker warned that troops would use every
means at their disposal to clear the square and that remaining
students would bear responsibility for the consequences.
</P>
<P>
At 4 a.m., the lamposts that dot the square went ominously dark,
and the student loudspeaker played the Internationale, the
socialist anthem. A Taiwan singer staging a hunger strike for
democracy took the microphone and proclaimed: ``We've achieved a
big victory. ... We're not afraid to die, but we've already lost
too much blood.''
After the lights went back on a half hour later, a voice vote by
the students showed most wanted to leave the square to avoid
further bloodshed.
</P>
<P>
They quickly filed out under the banners of their schools,
carrying the quilts and padded jackets that offered warmth during
the 22-day sit-in. Neither the students nor the Beijing residents
who arrived to show support could control their tears.
``Go with us,'' they told their supporters, who applauded the
students as they retreated. As they sobbed, many students defiantly
shouted: ``We shall return!'' and flashed V-for-victory signs.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890606-0116
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>06
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Chronology of Beijing Spring
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-China Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here is a look at key events in the student pro-democracy
movement, the government crackdown and the fighting between rival
army factions:
</P>
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
<P>
April 15 _ Former Communist Party chief Hu Yaobang dies. Beijing
University students put up posters praising him and indirectly
criticizing opponents who forced his resignation after student
demonstrations in 1986-87.
</P>
<P>
April 18 _ Thousands of students march in Beijing and Shanghai,
expressing dissatisfaction with the government and shouting ``Long
live Hu Yaobang! Long live democracy!'' About 1,000 stage a sit-in
at the Great Hall of the People to demand greater democracy, a free
press, and more money for education.
</P>
<P>
April 24 _ Students begin boycott of university classes.
</P>
<P>
April 27 _ In the largest to date of a continuing series of
protests, more than 150,000 students, with wide support from people
on the street, surge past police lines and fill Tiananmen Square,
chanting slogans for democracy and freedom.
</P>
<P>
April 29 _ Officials meet with student leaders, but independent
student groups are not satisfied and continue a class boycott at 41
universities.
</P>
<P>
May 4 _ About 100,000 students and supporters march on Tiananmen
Square to celebrate the 70th anniversary of China's first student
movement. Demonstrations are held in Shanghai, Nanjing and other
cities. About 300 journalists protest outside the official Xinhua
News Agency.
</P>
<P>
May 13 _ About 2,000 students begin a hunger strike in Tiananmen
Square.
</P>
<P>
May 14 _ Thousands flock to the square to back the students. The
number fasting rises to 3,000.
</P>
<P>
May 15 _ The government deadline for students to leave the square
passes. Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's welcoming ceremony
planned near the square must be moved to the airport.
</P>
<P>
May 16 _ Hundreds of thousands occupy the square. Journalists and
intellectuals join the protest.
</P>
<P>
May 17 _ Zhao pleas for students to leave. Students reject his
appeal and hold marches that generate 1 million supporters in
Beijing.
</P>
<P>
May 18 _ About 1 million people, including many workers, again
take to the streets to show their support for the hunger strikers.
</P>
<P>
Li Peng issues a stern lecture to student leaders and refuses to
discuss their demands.
</P>
<P>
May 19 _ A tearful Zhao visits weakened hunger strikers. Li also
visits the students briefly. The students later decide to end the
hunger strike.
</P>
<P>
May 20 _ Martial law is declared in parts of Beijing. Zhao
reportedly resigns after failing to persuade Li and other hardliners
to compromise. Students resume their hunger strike, then abandon it,
saying they will need their strength for the struggle ahead.
</P>
<P>
May 21 _ Students claim to reject an order by Li Peng to leave
Tiananman Square or face military action. Defying martial law,
hundreds of thousands of people remain in the square or block
intersections to prevent troops from reaching it.
</P>
<P>
May 22 _ Hundreds of thousands of people again block major roads
and senior military leaders say they are resisting orders to order
their troops on the protesters. At least one military convoy is
reported to withdraw.
</P>
<P>
May 23 _ One million people take to the streets to demonstrate
for democracy.
</P>
<P>
May 25 _ Li makes his first appearance since declaring martial
law. State-run radio says 27 of 29 provinces support martial law,
and military units announce they support martial law.
</P>
<P>
May 26 _ Sources say Zhao and another leading liberal, Wan Li,
head of the legislature, are under house arrest.
</P>
<P>
May 27 _ Beijing student leaders propose students end their
occupation of Tiananmen Square. Non-Beijing students resist and the
sit-in continues.
</P>
<P>
May 28 _ About 80,000 people, many students from outside the
capital, stage a demonstration, but unlike in past rallies few
workers participate.
</P>
<P>
May 30 _ Students unveil their ``Goddess of Democracy,'' a
replica of the Statue of Liberty, on the square. The government
calls it an insult to the nation. Students rally outside police
headquarters to protest the detention of three members of an
independent labor union.
</P>
<P>
May 31 _ The first of several pro-government rallies is staged by
farmers and workers in Beijing suburbs. The participants, ordered to
show up, show little enthusiasm.
</P>
<P>
June 1 _ The Beijing Municipal Government warns foreign
journalists that under martial law they must receive approval for
all press coverage. Coverage of the demonstrations is banned.
</P>
<P>
June 2 _ More than 1,000 troops appear outside the railway
station in a show of force.
</P>
<P>
June 3-4 _ Tens of thousands of troops make several attempts to
move on the square but are driven back by crowds of hundreds of
thousands of people supporting the students. Riot squads beat and
fire tear gas at demonstrators. A final push is made the evening of
June 3, and soldiers begin firing on crowds. Troops surround and
enter the square June 4 in the early morning hours and thousands of
protesters flee. Hundreds are killed and thousands wounded.
</P>
<P>
June 5 _ Soldiers in Beijing randomly shoot at unarmed civilians.
</P>
<P>
Army reinforces positions in city center. Reports spread of a split
in the army and a battle between military factions. Demonstraters in
Shanghai, Nanjing and other major Chinese cities protest the
slaughter in Beijing. U.S. announces suspension of all military
sales and visits of Chinese military leaders, but stops short of
severing diplomatic ties.
</P>
<P>
June 6 _ Armies loyal to rival factions trade fire. Soldiers
continue firing into crowds around Beijing. Anti-government
demonstrations spread to Shanghai, Nanjing, Chengdu, Shenyang and
other cities. Other nations urge their citizens to leave Beijing.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890607-0067
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>07
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Reports Vary on Number of Casualties
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-China, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Chinese government says that 300 soldiers,
``thugs,'' bystanders and students have been killed during the
martial law occupation of Beijing.
</P>
<P>
But most other estimates of casualties are far higher.
</P>
<P>
State Council spokesman Yuan Mu said on Tuesday that 7,000
people, including 5,000 soldiers, have been injured and 400 other
soldiers are missing and may be dead or wounded.
</P>
<P>
Non-official sources say Yuan's figures on civilian casualties
are far too low, but most have different estimates on the number of
victims. They range from 500 to 12,000 people slain.
</P>
<P>
In Washington, U.S. intelligence reports indicate 3,000 people
probably were killed, according to a U.S. official who spoke on
condition of anonymity. He said estimates of the number of dead
could go higher.
</P>
<P>
Nearly all of the deaths and injuries occurred Saturday night and
early Sunday when troops, firing randomly into large crowds, smashed
through barricades to reach Tiananmen square and attack
demonstrators demanding democratic reforms.
</P>
<P>
One doctor said Sunday that a quick check of 10 hospitals placed
the death toll at 500.
</P>
<P>
Other sources, compiling various reports and surveys, estimated
more than 1,000 people had been killed.
</P>
<P>
That number has increased with additional details and rumors of
killings.
</P>
<P>
Some officials of China's Red Cross said 2,600 people were killed
but Beijing's Red Cross office has refused to provide any figures.
</P>
<P>
One Hong Kong newspaper reported 5,000 deaths and 30,000 injured.
</P>
<P>
An Eastern European diplomat, whose country has good relations
with China, insisted that 12,000 people were slain by soldiers as
they attacked protesters in Tiananmen Square.
</P>
<P>
That figure is certainly high. Probably fewer than 10,000 people
were in the square when the troops moved in and most were able to
escape unharmed.
</P>
<P>
But students who had joined the Tiananmen occupation said
hundreds of colleagues from the Academy of Fine Arts who were
huddled around their ``Goddess of Democracy'' statue in the square
were shot or crushed by tanks. Beijing University students said 150
of their fellow students who were in the square are missing.
</P>
<P>
There were rumors that after the square was cleared troops burned
many corpses in large bonfires and other bodies were removed by
helicopters and garbage trucks to minimize the death count.
</P>
<P>
Yuan's statement said only 23 of the 300 people fatally injured
were students.
</P>
<P>
The exact number of people killed may never be known.
</P>
<P>
Victims were taken to dozens of hospitals, clinics and homes, and
there is no indication the government will reveal many details of
the tragedy.
</P>
<P>
And the death toll mounts. Troops manning checkpoints in central
Beijing continue to fire on unfriendly crowds and victims fall.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890608-0094
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>08
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Chronology of Beijing Spring
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here is a look at key events in the student pro-democracy
movement and at events since Sunday's assault by soldiers on
protesters in Tiananmen Square:
</P>
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
<P>
April 15 _ Former Communist Party chief Hu Yaobang dies. Beijing
University students put up posters praising him and indirectly
criticizing opponents who forced his resignation after student
demonstrations in 1986-87.
</P>
<P>
April 18 _ Thousands of students march in Beijing and Shanghai,
expressing dissatisfaction with the government and shouting ``Long
live Hu Yaobang! Long live democracy!'' About 1,000 stage a sit-in
at the Great Hall of the People to demand greater democracy, a free
press, and more money for education.
</P>
<P>
April 24 _ Students begin boycott of university classes.
</P>
<P>
April 27 _ In the largest to date of a continuing series of
protests, more than 150,000 students, with wide support from people
on the street, surge past police lines and fill Tiananmen Square,
chanting slogans for democracy and freedom.
</P>
<P>
April 29 _ Officials meet with student leaders, but independent
student groups are not satisfied and continue a class boycott at 41
universities.
</P>
<P>
May 4 _ About 100,000 students and supporters march on Tiananmen
Square to celebrate the 70th anniversary of China's first student
movement. Demonstrations are held in Shanghai, Nanjing and other
cities. About 300 journalists protest outside the official Xinhua
News Agency.
</P>
<P>
May 13 _ About 2,000 students begin a hunger strike in Tiananmen
Square.
</P>
<P>
May 14 _ Thousands flock to the square to back the students. The
number fasting rises to 3,000.
</P>
<P>
May 15 _ The government deadline for students to leave the square
passes. Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's welcoming ceremony
planned near the square must be moved to the airport.
</P>
<P>
May 16 _ Hundreds of thousands occupy the square. Journalists and
intellectuals join the protest.
</P>
<P>
May 17 _ Zhao pleads for students to leave. Students reject his
appeal and hold marches that generate 1 million supporters in
Beijing.
</P>
<P>
May 18 _ About 1 million people, including many workers, again
take to the streets to show their support for the hunger strikers.
</P>
<P>
Li Peng issues a stern lecture to student leaders and refuses to
discuss their demands.
</P>
<P>
May 19 _ A tearful Zhao visits weakened hunger strikers. Li also
visits the students briefly. The students later decide to end the
hunger strike.
</P>
<P>
May 20 _ Martial law is declared in parts of Beijing. Zhao
reportedly resigns after failing to persuade Li and other hardliners
to compromise. Students resume their hunger strike, then abandon it,
saying they will need their strength for the struggle ahead.
</P>
<P>
May 21 _ Students claim to reject an order by Li Peng to leave
Tiananman Square or face military action. Defying martial law,
hundreds of thousands of people remain in the square or block
intersections to prevent troops from reaching it.
</P>
<P>
May 22 _ Hundreds of thousands of people again block major roads
and senior military leaders say they are resisting orders to order
their troops on the protesters. At least one military convoy is
reported to withdraw.
</P>
<P>
May 23 _ One million people take to the streets to demonstrate
for democracy.
</P>
<P>
May 25 _ Li makes his first appearance since declaring martial
law. State-run radio says 27 of 29 provinces support martial law,
and military units announce they support martial law.
</P>
<P>
May 26 _ Sources say Zhao and another leading liberal, Wan Li,
head of the legislature, are under house arrest.
</P>
<P>
May 27 _ Beijing student leaders propose students end their
occupation of Tiananmen Square. Non-Beijing students resist and the
sit-in continues.
</P>
<P>
May 28 _ About 80,000 people, many students from outside the
capital, stage a demonstration, but unlike in past rallies few
workers participate.
</P>
<P>
May 30 _ Students unveil their ``Goddess of Democracy,'' a
replica of the Statue of Liberty, on the square. The government
calls it an insult to the nation. Students rally outside police
headquarters to protest the detention of three members of an
independent labor union.
</P>
<P>
May 31 _ The first of several pro-government rallies is staged by
farmers and workers in Beijing suburbs. The participants, ordered to
show up, show little enthusiasm.
</P>
<P>
June 1 _ The Beijing Municipal Government warns foreign
journalists that under martial law they must receive approval for
all press coverage. Coverage of the demonstrations is banned.
</P>
<P>
June 2 _ More than 1,000 troops appear outside the railway
station in a show of force.
</P>
<P>
June 3-4 _ Tens of thousands of troops make several attempts to
move on the square but are driven back by crowds of hundreds of
thousands of people supporting the students. Riot squads beat and
fire tear gas at demonstrators. A final push is made the evening of
June 3, and soldiers begin firing on crowds. Troops surround and
enter the square June 4 in the early morning hours and thousands of
protesters flee. Hundreds are killed and thousands wounded.
</P>
<P>
June 5 _ Soldiers terrorize Beijing with random shooting of
unarmed civilians. Army reinforces positions in city center. Reports
spread of a split in the army and a battle between military
factions. Demonstrations in Shanghai, Nanjing and other major
Chinese cities to protest the slaughter in Beijing. Chorus of
condemnation from around the world. U.S. announces suspension of all
military sales and visits of Chinese military leaders, but stops
short of severing diplomatic ties.
</P>
<P>
June 6 _ Armies loyal to rival factions are reported to be
clashing. Soldiers continue firing into crowds around Beijing.
</P>
<P>
Anti-government demonstrations spread to Shanghai, Nanjing, Chengdu,
Shenyang and other cities. Other nations urge their citizens to
leave Beijing.
</P>
<P>
June 7 _ Soldiers sprayed a diplomatic compound with bullets and
foreign embassies ordered their nationals to leave Beijing. Hundreds
of foreigners leave the country. The U.S. government called the
situation ``increasingly dangerous.''
June 8 _ Premier Li Peng makes his first public appearance since
May 25 and praises the soldiers who crushed the demonstrations. The
government issued new martial law orders demanding that student
leaders surrender.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890609-0036
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>09
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Freedom Signs Gone, Tiananmen Square is Now an Armed Camp
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Six Days in China, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
An AP Extra
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Gone from Tiananmen Square are the pro-democracy
banners and the tents of China's freedom movement, replaced by
tanks, armed guards and the chants of drilling soldiers.
</P>
<P>
The army on Thursday allowed the people of Beijing their first
glance of the 100-acre expanse since the military swept into the
capital six days ago, leaving hundreds dead and crushing a movement
for political change.
</P>
<P>
Troops moved back their barricades, making it possible for city
residents to walk to the edge of the square, which for seven weeks
stood at the heart of the movement. Buses and bicyclists today were
allowed to pass by Changan Avenue, which borders the north edge of
the square.
</P>
<P>
The spot once occupied by the Goddess of Democracy, a
33-foot-high replica of the Statue of Liberty, was taken by a
tread-wheeled armored personnel carrier. When students built the
statue last week, for a few days it became a symbol of the movement
for democratic reforms and an end to official corruption. On Sunday
morning, a tank crushed it.
</P>
<P>
In all, 80 tanks and 40 armored personnel carriers lined the
northern part of the square.
</P>
<P>
The Monument to Revolutionary Martyrs, where the students took a
final stand early Sunday, was swept clean. Poems and posters calling
for a more open China have disappeared from its sides.
</P>
<P>
Chinese Red Cross officials estimate 3,600 people were killed and
60,000 injured over the weekend, citing a Chinese students'
organization, the Union of Chinese Students in West Germany. The
government says nearly 300 people, mostly soldiers, were killed;
diplomats and Chinese say up to 3,000 died.
</P>
<P>
Soldiers drilled in Tiananmen's center, their cadenced shouting
echoing around the vast expanse. A crowd of officials stood on the
roof of the Great Hall of the People, overlooking the square. From
this same roof five days earlier officials watched as a jubilant
mass of demonstrators enveloped 5,000 troops and blocked their entry
to the square.
</P>
<P>
Inside the square, soldiers could be seen shuffling about, their
uniformed jackets stripped off, wash basins in hand. There was a
relaxed air of the inside of an army barracks as unarmed troops
carried food and walked slowly together, talking and laughing in
groups.
</P>
<P>
The area once housing students' tents has become a holding area
for a huge fleet of troop trucks.
</P>
<P>
On the southern perimeter, a single line of tanks and a cordon of
soldiers blocked the square from the thousands of bicylists who
pedaled slowly by, peering into Tiananmen.
</P>
<P>
Near the square, troops placed barbed wire in front of one
street. Soldiers were billeted in a construction site, their
laundered fatigues drying on the scaffolding. Next door, troops,
their assault rifles slung nonchalantly over their shoulders, stood
and chatted outside a discotheque.
``They look like they ,'' said one local resident. ``I hope they
know that we still don't want them here.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890609-0094
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>09
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
5,000 Turn Out for Tiananmen Square Memorial In NYC's Chinatown
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-China, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
More than 5,000 people chanting ``Freedom will
survive!'' packed a Chinatown park this morning in a memorial
service for students slain by soldiers in Tiananmen Square. They
then marched through the streets in a funeral procession.
``The gods are crying for what's happening in China today. It's a
great tragedy,'' said Harry Zinn of International Ladies Garment
Workers Union Local 2325, addressing the crowd through a steady
rain. ``Our hearts go out to the people of China.''
The crowd, which stood respectfully and silently during a
traditional funeral ceremony, waved banners and wore buttons
honoring ``the martyrs of Tiananmen Square'' and calling for
democracy in China.
</P>
<P>
After the service and several speeches, the crowd marched through
the streets of Chinatown, led by a casket and a traditional Chinese
funeral bier containing fruit and incense. As they headed up
Mulberry Street, a major street in Chinatown, they walked beneath a
30-foot black banner strung across the road.
``This has united the Chinese people for one cause _ to overthrow
the government and establish democracy,'' said Peter Lee, one of the
student organizers of the service. ``We must never allow them to
crush another body.''
The funeral procession stretched for blocks through Chinatown,
tying up traffic. Demonstrators planned another rally later in the
day outside the United Nations.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
