<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880729-0155
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>29
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Gorbachev Proposes Tougher Legislation to Punish Promoters of
Nationalism
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Mikhail S. Gorbachev on Friday proposed tougher
legislation to punish Soviets who seek to kindle ethnic unrest,
saying ``nationalist passions'' benefit opponents of his reforms.
</P>
<P>
The Soviet leader told a meeting of the Communist Party
leadership that inter-ethnic relations were worsening in some
regions of the country, due in part to ``active resistance put up
to perestroika by corrupt groups.''
``Perestroika,'' or restructuring, is Gorbachev's program for
widespread economic and social change.
</P>
<P>
State-run media also indicated Friday that a crackdown had begun
on people in Armenia who continue to agitate for annexation of a
mostly Armenian enclave in the neighboring republic of Azerbaijan.
</P>
<P>
The six-month conflict between the two republics over control of
the Nagorno-Karabakh district has led to mass rallies, strikes and
ethnic violence since February.
</P>
<P>
The Supreme Soviet Presidium, the government's top executive
body, intervened July 18. It rejected any change in
Nagorno-Karabakh's status but called for measures to develop the
region's economy and culture.
</P>
<P>
The conflict over Nagorno-Karabakh is one of the most rancorous
domestic disputes faced by Gorbachev since he became Communist
Party chief in March 1985. He indicated Friday he wants to defuse
tensions between ethnic groups, but also to punish those who
transform the tensions into a political crisis.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev spoke before a plenary meeting of the Central
Committee, the party's policy-making body. A summary of his remarks
was distributed by the official Tass news agency.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev outlined the reasons for a ``current aggravation'' of
tensions between ethnic groups in some regions of the Soviet Union,
Tass said.
</P>
<P>
Among the causes, Gorbachev listed ``a lack of concern for many
years for the specific requirements of peoples and ethnic groups,
inadequate control by the masses over the activities of executive
personnel, and active resistance put up to perestroika by corrupt
groups.''
Tass said that after Gorbachev noted that ``nationalist passions
benefit all anti-perestroika forces,'' he suggested increasing
accountability in Soviet laws for kindling ethnic strife.
</P>
<P>
Tass did not give details of Gorbachev's suggestion. At the July
18 Presidium meeting, the Soviet leader accused corrupt
conservatives who oppose his reforms of hiding behind the
Nagorno-Karabakh annexation drive.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev said the grounds for tougher legislation come directly
from Article 36 of the 1977 Soviet Constitution, which says the law
can punish ``any advocacy of racial or national exclusiveness,
hostility or contempt.''
Tass said Gorbachev made other proposals on how to resolve
ethnic tensions, including an increase in power for each of the
country's 15 republics, a law on ``equal use'' of the more than 100
languages spoken in the Soviet Union and some economic autonomy for
the country's republics and regions.
</P>
<P>
In particular, the Baltic republics of Lithuania, Latvia and
Estonia, forcibly incorporated into the Soviet Union in 1940, have
demanded more say in their own economic and government affairs.
</P>
<P>
The labor newspaper Trud said 44 people in Yerevan, Armenia's
capital, will face criminal charges following an incident in which
activists seeking the annexation of Nagorno-Karabakh attached
slogans to their cars and drove around the city. The paper did not
give the date or size of the mobile demonstration, but said 155
drivers have had their licenses revoked and 310 were fined.
</P>
<P>
In its July 18th decision, the Presidium also ordered local law
enforcement agencies to ensure order was restored in the Caucasus
Mountain region. Tass reported Friday that the situation was
stabilizing in Armenia, but said that at the ``urging of
instigators,'' some strikes and protests were continuing.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891213-0164
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>13
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
German, Crimean Tatars to Get Own Soviet Regions _ Eventually
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The government has decided to give ethnic Germans
and Crimean Tatars who were expelled from their homelands by Josef
Stalin their own autonomous regions but it will take years, Tass
reported Wednesday.
``The ice has been broken. A start has been made. We're working
on creating such autonomy,'' said Rafik Nishanov, chairman of a
chamber of the Soviet legislature, in remarks carried by the
official news agency.
</P>
<P>
However, he said, the nuts and bolts of how to create the
regions still had to be worked out. ``For example, a 10-year
program on resettlement. People can't just be expelled from the
area for others to move in.''
The Tatars of the Crimea and the ethnic Germans who lived on the
Volga River were forcibly resettled during World War II, when Josef
Stalin kicked peoples out of their homelands on the grounds they
could not be trusted to occupy strategic areas.
</P>
<P>
The Tatars and Germans, among others, long have been agitating
to return from Siberia and Central Asia to their traditional lands,
and last month the Supreme Soviet legislature declared that all
peoples exiled under Stalin should be considered politically
rehabilitated.
</P>
<P>
But other people now occupy the lands and houses that belonged
to the exiles, and re-establishing their dominion in their home
regions will not be so simple.
</P>
<P>
The Supreme Soviet took the basic decision that the two
autonmous regions should be created on Nov. 28 but kept it quiet,
apparently fearing explosive reactions from the populations now
living in the regions. It was also a potentially dangerous
precedent: The Soviet Union is a patchwork of well over 100 ethnic
groups, and many of them have outstanding territorial claims.
</P>
<P>
Trouble already has been reported between ethnic Germans and
Russians in several cities on the Volga. Residents of the Saratov
and Volgograd regions have protested the prospect of seeing many of
the nation's estimated 2 million Germans descending on them.
</P>
<P>
Ethnographers estimate there are some 500,000 Crimean Tatars in
the Soviet Union, and another 1 million in Turkey. Their protests
near the Kremlin in 1987 demanding to be allowed to return to their
homeland were among the first tests of President Mikhail S.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev's promises of greater democracy.
</P>
<P>
Several thousand Tatars have been filtering back to the Crimea
each year despite the lack of wholesale permission to return.
</P>
<P>
A wave of some 100,000 ethnic Germans emigrated to West Germany
this year, but many would probably stay if they could be assured of
their own republic, said Irina Ostroukh, a researcher at the Soviet
Institute of Ethnography who studies ethnic Germans.
</P>
<P>
The Nov. 28 plan approved by the Supreme Soviet recommended
excluding from the German region areas where resistance to German
resettlement was strongest in order to avoid ethnic conflicts.
</P>
<P>
The explosive conflict between Armenians and Azerbaijanis over
the Nagorno-Karabakh region has led to 200 deaths and hundreds of
thousands of refugees in the last two years. Both sides claim
control over the mountainous enclave.
</P>
<P>
The Supreme Soviet charged the government with creating a
commmission to determine how to create the regions for the Germans
and Crimean Tatars.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900613-0195
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>13
</DAY> 
<MONTH>06
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Soviets Say 148 Died in Kirghizia Unrest
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Ethnic violence killed 148 people and wounded 885
this month in the Central Asian republic of Kirghizia, the official
news agency Tass said Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
Tass said 748 of the injured had to be hospitalized and said a
search was continuing for a police officer who vanished June 7.
</P>
<P>
No new outbreaks were reported in the region near the border
city of Osh in western Kirghizia, where clashes arising from a land
dispute began on June 2 between ethnic Kirghiz and Uzbeks, both
Sunni Moslems.
</P>
<P>
The argument involves allocation of land in a densly populated
region where housing is scarce. It was the latest in a series of
bloody civil conflicts to trouble President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's
government.
</P>
<P>
Maj. Gen. Alexander Grienko, chief of the Interior Ministry's
Political Department, said that in two years of civil strife _
mainly ethnic clashes _ in the Soviet Union, about 24,000 people
have been arrested.
</P>
<P>
He said in Moscow on Tuesday that ministry troops had to be used
in 13 regions of the Soviet Union because of such outbreaks, Tass
said.
</P>
<P>
Grienko said 16 ministry soldiers were killed, four were
reported missing and more than 1,000 wounded. Tass did not quote
Grienko on how civilians casualties.
</P>
<P>
The general was quoted as saying these conflicts ``were often
accompanied by riots and pogroms, arson and massacre of innocent
people, (and) complete or partial destabilization of the
situation.''
Besides unrest this month in Kirghizia and Uzbekistan, ethnic
violence also has been reported in recent years in Georgia,
Armenia, Azerbaijan, Kazakhstan and Tadzhikistan.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP901230-0022
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>30
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Moldavian Parliament Agrees to Gorbachev's Measures
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Moldavia, acting to defuse one of the Soviet
Union's most explosive ethnic conflicts, agreed Sunday to comply
with a Kremlin order to reconsider its law making Moldavian the
republic's official language.
</P>
<P>
The republic's parliament acted in response to a decree issued
on Dec. 22 by President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the official news
agency Tass reported.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev also gave the republic 10 days to dissolve a new
national guard and to come up with measures guaranteeing equal
rights for all ethnic groups within its borders.
</P>
<P>
Tass said the Moldavan parliament agreed to disband the nationalguard
and to revise a law that Gorbachev said restricted the rights
of minorities.
</P>
<P>
Ethnic tension has gripped Moldavia, a largely agricultural
republic bordering Romania, during its push for independence from
the Soviet Union this year. The unrest turned violent last month,
when government troops clashed with activists, leaving four dead.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev said the conflicts had reached ``critical levels,''
and he put part of the blame on the Moldavian Supreme Soviet for
enacting laws that discriminate against minorities.
</P>
<P>
Alarmed by rising Moldavian nationalism, two of the republic's
minority groups have begun their own separatist movements.
</P>
<P>
The Gagauz, a group of about 150,000 Turkish Christians,
declared a new republic in southern Moldavia. In the eastern part
of Moldavia, more than 300,000 ethnic Russians and Ukrainians have
joined in declaring a new republic along the Dneister River.
</P>
<P>
All three groups claim discrimination by Moldavians. In
particular, they resent a new law making Moldavian the official
language and requiring people in dozens of jobs ranging from
doctors to hairdressers to pass Moldavian language tests by 1995.
</P>
<P>
Tass did not say how the Moldavian parliament would modify the
law.
</P>
<P>
Moldavian is identical to Romanian except for the Cyrillic
script Josef Stalin imposed on the republic. It is spoken by
two-thirds of the republic's residents.
</P>
<P>
Soviet hard-liners want Gorbachev to impose a state of emergency
and presidential rule in troubled zones throughout the ethnically
and geographically diverse country.
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev said the declaration of the Gagauz and Dniester
republics was illegal under the Soviet and Moldavian constitutions,
as were elections to form legislatures and any actions by those
bodies. The Moldavian legislature has also voted to declare the
elections null and void.
</P>
<P>
After residents of the Gagauz region began holding local
elections in late October, the Moldavian legislature clamped a
two-month state of emergency on the region, restricting movement in
and out of the area and banning public rallies.
</P>
<P>
Volunteer brigades of college-age Moldavians, who then flocked
to the region to try to stop the separatist movement, were ordered
dissolved by Gorbachev's decree. The volunteers were organized by
nationalist groups, including the Moldavian People's Front.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-40244
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>14
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Latvia 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Alksnis Warns of Ethnic Cleansing in Latvia 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Moscow NTV 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Viktor Alksnis, former USSR Supreme Soviet deputy, 
today reminded us of his existence. 
[Correspondent Irina Zaytseva] Viktor Alksnis, born 1950, 
Latvian, former deputy of the Supreme Soviet of the former USSR, 
soldier, resigned from the Army in order to fight for the 
restoration of the USSR. During the October events he left the 
White House with a head wound and was taken to hospital. 
</P>
<P>
After a long interval Viktor Alksnis held a news conference 
today in the Slavjanskaya Hotel. He began it with a short 
statement, the essence of which comes down to the fact that the 
adoption of the Latvian citizenship law violates not only human 
rights, but creates the conditions for a conflict similar, in 
his opinion, to the ones in Yugoslavia and the Caucasus. It was 
not only the Latvian Government Alksnis accused of this, but 
also the United States. According to him, during the latest 
visit to the United States by [Latvian President] Guntis 
Ulmanis, sanction was obtained for the adoption of the 
aforementioned discriminatory law. 
[Begin Alksnis recording] And thus carte blanche was given 
for mild ethnic cleansing of the Russian speaking population of 
the republic. [end recording] 
[Zaytseva] Apart from that, Alksnis added, according to 
information received from reliable sources, certain circles in 
Moscow want conflict in Latvia. 
[Begin Alksnis recording] A certain scenario exists to drive 
a so-called security corridor along the route 
Daugavpils-Yekabpils-Riga where stringent ethnic cleansing of 
the Latvian population will take place in reply to the mild 
ethnic cleansing of the Russian population in order to bring 
so-called independent Latvia to its knees. [end recording] 
[Zaytseva] Journalists asked for more precise information 
about what Alksnis called reliable sources. 
[Begin Alksnis recording] You understand that I cannot name 
these sources. But I can say that they are fairly 
authoritative. [end recording] 
[Zaytseva] Asked what he intends to do, Alksnis said his 
opportunities are unfortunately limited, and that is why he is 
appealing to journalists. In his opinion, only joint efforts 
can bring this information to the attention of world public 
opinion, point out the seriousness of this issue, and avoid the 
coming tragedy. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-62505
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>5
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Tajikistan 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Communist Leader Calls for `Renovated' Soviet Union 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Moscow ITAR-TASS 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
[Report by ITAR-TASS correspondent Galina Gridnyova] 
Dushanbe 16 May TASS - The Tajik Communist Party 
has called for the restoration of a renovated Soviet Union in 
the form of a federation as the only means to ensure the 
development of the political, economic, and spiritual potential 
of former Soviet republics. 
</P>
<P>
Tajik communists' leader Shodiy Shabdolov told ITAR-TASS on 
Monday [16 May]that the disintegration of the Soviet Union and 
the parade of sovereignty that followed it have led to economic 
and political chaos in all republics. Radical market reforms 
"imposed by quasi- democrats" and "wild privatisation" have 
enriched a small group of nouveau riches and plunged the rest of 
the population in poverty and hunger, he said. 
</P>
<P>
The mass drive for sovereignty was accompanied by armed 
inter-ethnic conflicts in many ex-Soviet republics and outburst 
of nationalism. Tajikistan was hit most hard. The civil war in 
the Republic claimed the lives of more than 100,000 people, 
Shabdolov said. 
</P>
<P>
He noted that the majority of the population support Tajik 
communists' call for the restoration of the Soviet Union. Over 
one million people, about two-thirds of the adult population, 
signed appeals "for unity, brotherhood and friendship of the 
peoples of the USSR" adopted by numerous conferences and 
meetings held all across the Republic. 
</P>
<P>
Supporters of the restoration of a renovated union held a 
founding congress of their movement in Dushanbe on Saturday. 
</P>
<P>
Apart from the communist party, the founders of the new 
movement include Tajik trade unions, the Union of Tajik Women, 
organisations of veterans and ethnic and cultural associations. 
</P>
<P>
"We are confident that our movement is growing so strong 
that 
it cannot be stopped," Shabdolov said. He stressed that it will 
act within the framework of the law and use only constitutional 
methods. "We are against barricades and use of force," he said. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-4937
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>06
</DAY> 
<MONTH>03
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>92
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
FT  06 MAR 92 / Shooting threatens Moldova peace
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MOSCOW
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A CEASEFIRE in Moldova was threatened yesterday when a truck driver
transporting militiamen was shot dead by machinegun fire in the
self-proclaimed Trans Dnestr republic, home of the Russian-speaking
minority.
</P>
<P>
The shooting came shortly after the ceasefire came into effect between the
Moldovan authorities, dominated by ethnic Romanians, and the minority based
in the republic on the east bank of the river Dnestr. At least nine people
have been killed in clashes over the past week.
</P>
<P>
As in the more severe conflict in Nagorno-Karabakh, the underlying tensions
are growing and neither side believes it is losing. In other respects,
however, the conflicts are quite different and illustrate the complexity of
conflict with which the former Soviet Union is now faced.
</P>
<P>
The Trans Dnestr conflict stems directly from the breakup of the Soviet
Union while Nagorno-Karabakh has been a source of tension between Azeris and
Armenians for centuries.
</P>
<P>
Moldova (formerly Moldavia) was finally taken under full Soviet control in
1944.
</P>
<P>
The Soviet leadership sought to stifle any attempts to preserve its former
links with Romania - calling Moldovan a separate language from Romanian, and
constructing a separate history for the Moldovan people.
</P>
<P>
Industry was largely situated on the left bank of the Dnestr, in the sliver
of the republic next to Ukraine, and largely staffed by Russians and
Ukrainians. Ukrainians and Russians together represent some 27 per cent of
the population, with Moldovans accounting for 64 per cent.
</P>
<P>
The little republic (4.5m people) was slow to respond to the stirrings of
reform. When it did, in 1989, a language movement quickly put the hardline
Communist Party on the defensive and it lost power in 1990 to the present
nationalist government, headed by President Mircea Snegur, the former
secretary of the Moldovan Party's central committee.
</P>
<P>
From the beginning of the nationalist movement, it was clear that the
Russian and, to a lesser extent, the Ukrainian minorities would be hostile,
reacting to laws establishing Moldovan as the official language and to calls
for renewed union with Romania with strikes and demonstrations, and, finally
last year, proclaiming Trans Dnestr independent under a Russian president,
Mr Igor Smirnov.
</P>
<P>
During the August coup last year, the Moldovan government stoutly rejected
it and the Trans Dnestr authorities welcomed it, siding with the Soviet army
in its brief efforts to impose military rule.
</P>
<P>
Thereafter, the two sides have gathered military forces. The Trans Dnestr
side has been augmented by Cossacks from nearby areas returning to their
traditional role as defenders of Russia's borders. The daily Izvestia
reported yesterday that the Cossacks appear to have appointed themselves
mercenaries for the Russians (they are paid from Rbs2,000 to Rbs5,000 a week
by the Trans Dnestr authorities).
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-5959
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>29
</DAY> 
<MONTH>02
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>92
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
FT  29 FEB 92 / Troops to pull out of Nagorno Karabakh
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MOSCOW
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
TROOPS OF the former Soviet Union were ordered to pull out from the Armenian
enclave of Nagorno-Karabakh yesterday after they were fired on during
clashes between Azeri and Armenian militants.
</P>
<P>
Marshal Yevgeny Shaposhnikov, the Commonwealth of Independent States'
defence minister, announced the decision as fighting worsened in the
disputed territory in spite of efforts to secure a truce.
</P>
<P>
The enclave is administered by Azerbaijan but largely populated by
Armenians.
</P>
<P>
The order for the pull-out of the 366th motorised regiment follows the
deaths earlier this week of a handful of soldiers caught in the fighting
between Armenian guerrillas and Azerbaijani forces.
</P>
<P>
Fighting flared again yesterday in the capital Stepanakert, where the
regiment is based. Azerbaijani and Armenian officials claimed their civilian
targets were under particularly vicious attack.
</P>
<P>
Marshal Shaposhnikov, who is also commander-in-chief, has long warned that
he would withdraw troops rather than allow them to become targets of ethnic
conflicts in the former Soviet Union. No dates have been given for the
withdrawal.
</P>
<P>
Troops under fire along the Armenian-Azerbaijani border will also be
withdrawn. Commanders of the Trans-Caucasus military district, which
encompasses Georgia as well as Armenia and Azerbaijan, have been ordered to
rebuff attacks on military installations.
</P>
<P>
Azeri and Armenian officials say sophisticated weapons, including combat
helicopters, tanks and armoured personnel carriers, are being used by
guerrillas on both sides in the four-year-old conflict.
</P>
<P>
Armenian militants attacked the last Azeri stronghold in Nagorno-Karabakh
yesterday, according to Azerbaijan's interior ministry, which said residents
of the town of Shusha fled as helicopter gunships swooped down from
snow-covered mountains.
</P>
<P>
Armenians in the enclave want unification with Armenia, but Azerbaijan will
not give up any territory.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-13244
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>15
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>92
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
FT  15 JUL 92 / Peace-keepers sent into South Ossetia
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MOSCOW
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
RUSSIA and Georgia yesterday deployed 'blue helmet' troops to stop ethnic
fighting in the disputed region of South Ossetia in the first peace-keeping
operation since the collapse of the Soviet Union, Reuter reports from
Moscow.
</P>
<P>
Reports from the remote Transcaucasian region said hundreds of heavily armed
Russian troops from the 104th paratroop battalion moved into a 7km-wide
security zone separating rebel South Ossetia from the rest of Georgia.
</P>
<P>
Georgian national guards occupied similar positions on their side of the
border and pulled out all their men from the South Ossetian capital of
Tskhinvali.
</P>
<P>
But Itar-Tass news agency said gunfire overnight near the city killed four
civilians and injured two others, underscoring the difficulties facing the
operation.
</P>
<P>
The mission was the first peace-keeping attempt anywhere in the former
Soviet Union, whose disintegration last year has prompted waves of
bloodletting in ethnic flashpoints from the Romanian to the Afghan borders.
</P>
<P>
Reports from the former Soviet republic of Moldova said several people had
been killed overnight in fresh ceasefire violations between government
forces and separatists.
</P>
<P>
In the Transcaucasian republic of Armenia, Radio Russia said five civilians
had died overnight in Azerbaijani shelling, the latest victims of a
four-year undeclared war which has killed 2,000 people.
</P>
<P>
Russia and Georgia were cautiously optimistic that Ossetia could be the
first region of the former Soviet Union where armed conflict could be
resolved with the help of 'political measures and actions'.
</P>
<P>
South Ossetia is part of Georgia but wants to unite with neighbouring North
Ossetia, which was assigned to Russia by Stalin. Hundreds have been killed
since 1990 in fighting between Georgians and Ossetians.
</P>
<P>
The peace-keepers have been issued with UN-style light-blue helmet bands and
matching chevrons on their sleeves.
</P>
<P>
They will be joined later by a multi-ethnic force - Russians, Ukrainians,
Ossetians and other mountain peoples - under the nominal command of North
Ossetian leaders.
</P>
<P>
The peace-keepers' mission is to form a physical barrier between the two
sides, opening the way to future talks.
</P>
<P>
The greatest threat is expected to come from hundreds of armed fighters on
both sides, operating independently in a dozen or so bands outside the
control of either Russian or Georgian authorities.
</P>
<P>
Interfax news agency said Russia's Vice-President Alexander Rutskoi, at
present on a visit to Moldova, proposed a similar peace-keeping operation
there.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-10185
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>02
</DAY> 
<MONTH>11
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>92
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
FT  02 NOV 92 / Russia sends troops to Caucasus to back North Ossetian
regime
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MOSCOW
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
RUSSIA flew 3,000 special forces to halt ethnic fighting in the troubled
Caucasus mountains at the weekend, its second troop deployment in a week to
support a beleaguered government in its former empire.
</P>
<P>
Russian President Boris Yeltsin sent Spetsnaz commandos and elite police to
Vladikavkaz, capital of the Russian autonomous republic of North Ossetia,
1,100 miles south of Moscow. The troops were sent to halt fighting between
Ossetians and a regional ethnic group, the Ingush, who officials claimed
were setting fire to Ossetian-owned homes. Scores were reported killed and
injured in street fighting between Ossetians and Ingush in the past several
days.
</P>
<P>
Ingush rebels were reported yesterday to have taken hostage 80 Russian
interior ministry soldiers based in the region. A local official said the
soldiers were seized on Friday in the Dzhermen settlement, located near the
regional capital, Vladikavkaz, and populated mostly by Ingushis, Mr Felix
Gutnov, spokesman for the North Ossetian interior ministry, said.
</P>
<P>
The Ingush, who declared an independent state in June, are demanding the
return of lands that Russian leader Josef Stalin expropriated in 1944 and
declared part of North Ossetia.
</P>
<P>
Mr Yeltsin and Russian Prime Minister Yegor Gaidar held emergency meetings
on the crisis on Saturday and yesterday. At the same time, the North
Ossetian government said it would distribute Russian army-supplied automatic
weapons to civilian volunteers.
</P>
<P>
'The Russian authorities are strong enough to make all those violating the
law respect it,' Russian Deputy Prime Minister Georgy Khizha, Mr Yeltsin's
specialist on the Caucasus, told Russian television.
</P>
<P>
The Russian action mirrored recent developments in the former Soviet
republic of Tajikistan, where Russian troops have also been deployed. The
Central Asian nation, which has yet to form its own army since the Soviet
Union collapsed last December, has also distributed weapons to civilians. On
October 26-27 Russian soldiers played a crucial role in crushing a coup
attempt in the Tajik capital of Dushanbe.
</P>
<P>
The Caucasus mountains, which stretch from southern Russia to the borders of
Turkey and Iran, are engulfed by several conflicts. Among them are Georgia's
war with Abkhazian separatists, and Azerbaijan's conflict with ethnic
Armenians in Nagorno-Karabakh.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-2439
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>14
</DAY> 
<MONTH>12
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>93
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
FT  14 DEC 93 / Challenge of peacekeeping: A possible framework for
co-operation
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The international community is starting to look beyond the conflict in the
former Yugoslavia, and is becoming increasingly aware of the true magnitude
and seriousness of ethnic and political conflicts in the former Soviet
Union. The problem is indeed a pressing one.
</P>
<P>
The disputes in the Transcaucasus, central Asia, and elsewhere in the former
Soviet Union are causing great suffering for those involved. They are a
source of legitimate concern to the Russians, who are worried by clashes
close to their borders. They are concerned too about the safety of ethnic
Russians living in those countries where there are conflicts, and about the
economic and social consequences of refugees fleeing to Russia (whose
potential number is estimated at more than 2m).
</P>
<P>
They believe that the problems in some of the former Soviet republics are
either ignored or misunderstood. The Russians fear that if they do nothing,
the conflicts will worsen and probably spread. They argue that they have a
legitimate concern in trying to resolve conflicts that threaten their
security. They ask why, when the international community is engaged in
peacemaking and peacekeeping in many of the world's trouble spots, similar
efforts should not be undertaken in the hot spots near them.
</P>
<P>
Equally, these disputes are of legitimate concern to Britain, its western
partners and the whole international community, both for humanitarian
reasons and because such flashpoints risk provoking regional instability. If
uncontrolled, they pose a variety of threats to European security, including
increased traffic in drugs and arms as well as international terrorism.
</P>
<P>
Crises in Russia's newly independent neighbours may also complicate Russia's
relations with the west: unless they are carefully handled, they risk
prejudicing the emerging relationship between us.
</P>
<P>
The west is sometimes suspicious of Moscow's attitude. There are no
differences about the need to resolve these conflicts: but there are
differences over how to go about it. The British government will not
underwrite Russian involvement unless it is sure that peacekeeping troops
will not turn into occupying forces. Nor are countries that secured their
independence when the Soviet Union was dissolved keen that the west should
concede to Moscow the same role it played in the Soviet empire. They fear
that this would compromise their sovereignty. When they are willing for
Russian troops to play a peacekeeping role, they want there to be some form
of international monitoring. This has meant that, even though the west lacks
the resources to engage directly in those trouble spots, it has been wary of
appearing to endorse Russian involvement instead, in case it had imperial
tendencies.
</P>
<P>
If we are to fashion a joint approach by Russia and its western partners to
the problem of peacekeeping in the former Soviet Union, we must address all
these concerns. Clearly Russia has an important role to play in this area.
</P>
<P>
If the Russians want international recognition and more active support from
the international community, the west in turn needs guarantees that Russia
will not regard recognition of its involvement as giving it carte blanche in
the former Soviet Union. Peace-keeping in the former Soviet Union, as indeed
peacekeeping elsewhere, must comply with internationally recognised
principles. It needs to be looked at on a case by case basis. Respect for
the sovereignty of the newly independent countries must remain paramount.
</P>
<P>
We agreed that the principles underlying Russian, CIS or international
peacekeeping operations would need to include: strict respect for the
sovereignty of the countries involved; an invitation from the government
concerned and the consent of the parties to the conflict; commitment to a
parallel political peace process; a clear mandate setting out the role of
the peacekeeping forces (which should whenever possible be multinational in
character); and an exit strategy for the peacekeeping forces deployed.
</P>
<P>
These principles should help stimulate a dialogue and political settlement
between the parties to the conflict, focus attention and, where possible,
resources on the settlement of conflicts in the former Soviet Union.
</P>
<P>
All this will help enhance Russian peacekeeping practices. Although the
Conference for Security and Co-operation in Europe and the UN lack the
resources to put large numbers of peacekeepers on the ground themselves,
they may be able to suggest measures to enhance transparency and to monitor
the peace process. Extending co-operation within the North Atlantic
Co-operation Council, and also co-operation between Russia and Nato, might
help improve training for Russian peacekeepers. This is an area we shall
need to explore further.
</P>
<P>
We also need to put much more emphasis on preventive diplomacy. One of the
ways in which we can help prevent conflicts is to strengthen the democratic
institutions in the newly independent countries of the former Soviet Union.
</P>
<P>
The CSCE and other international institutions can play an important role
here, drawing the newly independent countries into a more active dialogue on
ways of promoting democratic values and principles. We discussed ways of
strengthening the CSCE's role, including the role of the High Commissioner
for National Minorities, at the recent Rome ministerial meeting.
</P>
<P>
We must try to find ways of managing and resolving tensions before they
erupt into conflict. It will not be easy, but we must try. Potentially
explosive cocktails of ethnic and political animosities could spread the
fire of intolerance all too easily to other countries and regions.
</P>
<P>
We need to deal with it together in the spirit of partnership. And we need
to deal with it urgently. Our security is indivisible and we must ensure it
by vigorous and imaginative efforts aimed at promoting peace for all as well
as rights for all.
</P>
<P>
The authors are UK foreign secretary and Russian foreign minister
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA070289-0167
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>2
</DAY> 
<MONTH>7
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>89
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
GORBACHEV SAYS ETHNIC STRIFE IS THREAT TO UNITY 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
MOSCOW 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev warned the nation Saturday night that the 
country's growing ethnic strife is endangering its unity as a state as well as 
threatening his program of political and economic reforms. 
</P>
<P>
Appealing for calm and for the cool consideration of grievances after weeks of 
continuing unrest in scattered areas of the country, Gorbachev made clear the 
leadership's fear that the nation is heading into a political maelstrom that 
could tear the Soviet Union apart. 
</P>
<P>
As president, Gorbachev said, it is his "duty to warn you about the mounting 
danger of worsening inter-ethnic relations and the consequences for society, 
for every family and for every person." 
</P>
<P>
"The fate of perestroika and the unity of our state is at stake," he declared 
in a sober, 20-minute address broadcast on radio and television. "Irresponsible 
slogans, political instigation, setting one national group against another, the 
domination of some ethnic groups by others - this could lead to disaster for 
us all. 
</P>
<P>
"The living and the succeeding generations will curse those who pushed the 
nation on this course and those who failed to caution it against the dangers 
involved in time to prevent madness." 
</P>
<P>
With serious ethnic clashes in Soviet Central Asia over the past month, with 
troops needed to maintain the peace in the southern republics of Armenia, 
Azerbaijan and Georgia and with nationalism growing stronger in the Baltic 
republics of Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania, Gorbachev is struggling to hold the 
Soviet Union together as a state while he pushes broad reforms that he believes 
will resolve most of the grievances. 
</P>
<P>
Even as he spoke, Soviet officials reported new violence in the south - this 
time between Georgians and Azerbaijanis inside the Georgian republic but in an 
area with many Azerbaijanis. Roving gangs, armed with hunting rifles, gasoline 
bombs and other weapons, had clashed in three towns south of the capital of 
Tbilisi last week, leaving one man dead and 22 people seriously wounded. 
</P>
<P>
Although limited so far in scope, some of the ethnic conflicts could grow to 
the point where various regions of the country would be thrown into virtual 
civil war, Gorbachev suggested, and some national republics could find 
themselves in violent disputes with their neighbors. 
</P>
<P>
Those who encourage the unrest are "playing with fire," Gorbachev said, warning 
that the government will use its full powers and take "the most decisive 
measures" against those provoking the clashes, organizing attacks on minority 
groups or urging secession. 
</P>
<P>
Nearly 300 people have been killed in communal clashes and related political 
disturbances over the past two years; tens of thousands of people have had to 
flee their homes, including 40,000 last month alone, to seek refuge from the 
violence, and nearly 25,000 special troops are now deployed in various parts of 
the country to maintain order. 
</P>
<P>
"There will be no pulling of our punches in relation to those who have taken 
the criminal path," Gorbachev said, warning of stern measures against those 
engaged in communal violence or in political agitation. 
</P>
<P>
Political Energy Drained 
</P>
<P>
The ethnic strife, much of it rooted in past Soviet policies of domination by 
ethnic Russians or in the forced deportation of hundreds of thousands of people 
during the Stalinist era, has increasingly drained the political energy 
necessary to push through major reforms and has provided conservative critics 
of reform with a potent argument against faster and broader change. 
</P>
<P>
For Gorbachev, the spread of the unrest has forced the humiliating admission 
that the Soviet Union, a superpower in world terms, cannot ensure the domestic 
tranquility that is a first priority for any government - nor can it protect 
its own minorities against pogroms. 
</P>
<P>
If the strife here continued and grew, he asked, "What kind of example shall we 
set for others while calling on the whole of mankind to build a nonviolent 
world?" 
</P>
<P>
Of equal gravity for Gorbachev in domestic political terms has been the growth 
of not only nationalism but the appearance of secessionist groups in the Baltic 
republics and in Armenia, Georgia and Moldavia, a Soviet republic on the 
Romanian border. 
</P>
<P>
The whole issue is believed to have been the subject of a high-level Communist 
Party conference here late last week, and Gorbachev's unusual television 
address underscores the threat posed by the conflicts. 
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev acknowledged that ethnic relations are "wound in a tight knot of 
contradictions" because of previous Soviet policies, particularly the effort to 
pull the country's 100-plus ethnic groups into a new "Soviet nationality" with 
a unified culture. 
</P>
<P>
This policy had, in fact, collided head on with growing ethnic awareness 
throughout the country and made the problems even worse. 
</P>
<P>
Past economic policies, including the "stagnation" in many regions under the 
regime of the late President Leonid I. Brezhnev, had also made the problems 
more acute. 
</P>
<P>
"We are also reaping today the results of lawlessness in preceding decades - 
the deportation of whole peoples from their lands and the burying in oblivion 
of the national interests of small ethnic groups," Gorbachev said, alluding to 
actions carried out decades ago by the dictator Josef Stalin. 
</P>
<P>
"Such excesses resulted in indifference to ethnic interests, to many 
outstanding social and economic problems in constituent republics and 
autonomous regions, deformities in the development of the languages and 
cultures of the country's different peoples, the deteriorating demographic 
situation and many other negative consequences that ultimately provoked tension 
in inter-ethnic relations." 
</P>
<P>
Although these questions will be dealt with during a special meeting of the 
Communist Party's policy-making Central Committee in late July and then debated 
again by the Congress of People's Deputies, the country's new national 
assembly, Gorbachev apparently felt that he could not wait for those debates, 
and he set out his own broad guidelines for dealing with the crisis. 
</P>
<P>
Right of Equality 
</P>
<P>
"Everyone, regardless of his nationality, should feel an equal citizen in any 
part of the country and have a possibility to exercise all the rights 
guaranteed by the Soviet Union's constitution," he said. 
</P>
<P>
The refusal to recognize the basic principle of equality had led to attacks on 
minority groups in several parts of the country, Gorbachev said, alluding to 
the particularly vicious assaults on Mesketian Turks in Uzbekistan last month 
in which about 100 people died. 
</P>
<P>
The Soviet leader outlined an approach that would seek to increase the feeling 
of various ethnic groups that they are "at home in their own land" and could 
preserve and develop their own cultures, languages and social traditions, with 
the Soviet Union evolving politically to be much more of a federal system. 
</P>
<P>
But he said that minority communities also need to be protected so that there 
is a balance of rights. "We have lived and will continue to live in a 
multi-ethnic community," he observed. 
</P>
<P>
Gorbachev said that "profound transformations in the Soviet federation" are 
clearly essential, promising further political reforms to make it a real 
federation and not just one in name only. 
</P>
<P>
Demands Rejected 
</P>
<P>
But he declared at the same time his firm opposition to near-total independence 
demanded by some nationalists, particularly in Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania, 
and to the calls by others for the redrawing of the borders of ethnic 
territories. The Soviet Union's ethnic groups have "a common destiny," 
Gorbachev said. 
</P>
<P>
"In quest of the better, one should not embark on the path of destroying what 
has been built and abandoning what has already been given by the federation and 
what can be multiplied within its framework," he said. 
</P>
</TEXT>
<KEYWORDS>
GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S; SPEECHES; ETHNIC GROUPS; DEMONSTRATIONS - USSR; RACIAL 
RELATIONS - USSR; NATIONALISM 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
