<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880711-0056
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>11
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
U.N. Agency Projects Food Shortages Due To U.S. Drought
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The crippling drought hitting North America is
expected to reduce world grain stocks to levels that may cause food
shortages in many poor countries, the U.N. Food and Agriculture
Organization reported today.
</P>
<P>
The agency projects world cereal production in 1988 to total
1.785 billion tons, only two million tons more than last year's
level, which was already below the expected production.
</P>
<P>
If the drought in the United States ended now, grain production
would fall close to the low levels of 1983, when a drought and
farmers' participation in a government crop reduction program
decreased output, the agency reported.
</P>
<P>
As a result, world grain stocks are projected to fall below 310
million tons, or 17 percent of the level the agency considers
necessary to safeguard world food security, the report said. If
crop conditions in the United States and Canada continue to
deteriorate, the ratio could drop even further.
``Such a development would have serious implications for the
food security, particularly of many low-income, food-deficit
countries,'' the report said.
</P>
<P>
The high grain prices resulting from a lower supply would hit
poor, food-importing countries the hardest, the U.N. agency warned.
</P>
<P>
It said the rising prices could also reduce food aid from developed
countries.
</P>
<P>
The most severely hit crops are coarse grains _ mostly maize,
barley and oats, the report said.
</P>
<P>
The agency projected good harvests in other parts of the world.
</P>
<P>
In Asia the yearly monsoon rains started on time, and production in
Europe and the Soviet is expected to be larger than last year.
</P>
<P>
Grain production in South America should be slightly lower this
year than last.
</P>
<P>
In the Sahel region of sub-Saharan Africa, however, locusts
flourishing in unexpectedly heavy rains have damaged this year's
harvest. Potential crop losses from the pests could hit 1 million
tons, FAO said.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880711-0221
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>11
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Lyng Says Drought Could Prompt Relaxed Crop Acreage Controls Next
Year
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The drought may force the government to ease
crop acreage controls next year to help the United States rebuild
its grain inventories, Agriculture Secretary Richard E. Lyng said
Monday.
</P>
<P>
But the United States ``will continue to be a major player'' in
world agriculture and in 1989 ``should be able to bounce back''
from this year's drought losses, he said.
</P>
<P>
Lyng's remarks were prepared for delivery at a meeting of farm
magazine, extension, advertising, co-op and broadcast editors.
</P>
<P>
A larger portion of the United States suffered from some degree
of drought stress in May and June than at any point since records
began in 1895, he said.
</P>
<P>
Moreover, on July 2, about 35 percent of the contiguous United
States was in the ``severe to extreme'' drought category, he said.
</P>
<P>
In 1934, more than 60 percent was so rated, and in August 1954 more
than 50 percent was in that category.
``Because of the large early season area now experiencing
drought in the U.S., 1988 appears to have the potential to approach
or exceed the drought-affected areas of the 1930s and 1950s,'' Lyng
said.
</P>
<P>
Even with the severe drought, there will be an adequate supply
of food grains and livestock feed grains so that the United States
``will be able to take care of our domestic needs and our export
demand,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Lyng said total consumption of 1988 crops will probably be
somewhat less than previously estimated because prices are much
higher.
``But it is important to note that we will have no shortages,
that we will still be able to accommodate the needs of our overseas
buyers,'' he said.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880712-0250
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>12
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Kentucky's governor has criticized the federal government for
being too slow in dealing with the drought, and Iowa's governor
warns that farmers in his state still face potential disaster
despite up to five inches of rain over the weekend.
</P>
<P>
Crews began installing pumps on barges Monday to haul fresh
water to southern Louisiana towns plagued by rising salt levels in
the lower Mississippi River.
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, House Speaker Jim Wright said in Washington he hopes
that a relief package with disaster payments of up to $100,000 for
drought-stricken farmers will win committee approval and be ready
for floor action in Congress this week.
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The drought may force the government to ease
crop acreage controls next year to help the United States rebuild
its grain inventories, says Agriculture Secretary Richard E. Lyng.
</P>
<P>
But the United States will continue to be a major player in
world agriculture and in 1989 should be able to bounce back from
this year's drought losses, he said Monday.
</P>
<P>
A larger portion of the United States suffered from some degree
of drought stress in May and June than at any point since records
began in 1895, Lyng said.
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Grain and soybean futures have dropped to their
lowest levels in more than five weeks as weekend rains in the
Midwest prompted a third straight day of plummeting prices on the
Chicago Board of Trade.
</P>
<P>
July soybeans fell 66 cents a bushel Monday to $8.58, the lowest
price for that contract since June 3. Corn for July delivery
dropped 20{ cents to $2.89 a bushel, the lowest level since June 15.
</P>
<P>
Wheat and oat futures also closed lower.
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Crude oil futures prices have hit their lowest
closing level since late 1986, hurt by a selloff that traders blame
on too much supply and renewed skepticism about OPEC's ability to
restrain production.
</P>
<P>
Monday's decline erased gains made last week that had been based
on fears of supply disruptions caused by the oil platform explosion
in the North Sea.
</P>
<P>
On the New York Mercantile Exchange, an important barometer of
price trends, the August-delivery price for West Texas Intermediate
crude settled at $14.78 per barrel, down from $15.46 late Friday.
</P>
<P>
It was the lowest closing price for the near-month crude contract
since a $14.71 close on Nov. 3, 1986.
</P>
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Savings institution depositors withdrew more
money from their accounts than they deposited in May for the first
time in seven months, while losses continued to erode the ailing
industry's capital, the government reports.
</P>
<P>
The Federal Home Loan Bank Board said Monday net withdrawals at
the nation's 3,102 federally insured S
</P>
<P>
amp;
</P>
<P>
Ls totaled $941 million in
May. But the decline came after seven consecutive months of net
deposit gains totaling $28 billion.
</P>
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
<P>
Stock prices crept higher Monday in quiet trading. The Dow Jones
average of 30 industrials rose 5.16 points to 2,111.31.
</P>
<P>
The dollar limbed to recent highs against several major
currencies. Gold prices fell sharply.
</P>
<P>
Bond prices rose modestly in quiet trading following a week of
steady decline.
</P>
<P>
Grain and soybean futures plunged, while wheat and oat futures
also declined.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880713-0121
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>13
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Deluge in Some Drought Areas
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Heavy rain deluged some drought-hit areas as Congress began
working on a package of relief for America's farmers, and farmers
in Kentucky today greeted the arrival of the first shipment of hay
airlifted free from Oregon.
``Everything looks so good with a bit of rain over the past 24
hours,'' farmer Herman Krone said Tuesday at his 2,800-acre farm in
southern Illinois, which President Reagan plans to visit Thursday
during a tour of the drought-stricken area.
</P>
<P>
However, Krone said, almost one-third of his 1,200 acres of corn
already have been lost.
</P>
<P>
Marth Wilkinson, wife of Kentucky Gov. Wallace Wilkinson and
business manager of the family's farm, was at Louisville's
Standiford Field today for the arrival of the first hay shipment
from Portland, Ore. United Parcel Service plans to ship free of
charge 20 to 30 tons of hay from Portland to Louisville each day
for the next two weeks.
</P>
<P>
The Agriculture Department, meanwhile, issued a report
predicting severe damage to the harvest from the drought. It
estimated, for example, that corn output this year would shrivel to
5.2 billion bushels, down from 7.06 billion last year.
</P>
<P>
The dry weather is ``the largest drought that our nation has
ever experienced,'' Agriculture Secretary Richard E. Lyng told
legislators. ``I think history will show that it's truly more
mammoth than any of us has ever experienced.''
Extremely heavy rain fell Tuesday in sections of Texas,
Louisiana, Oklahoma and Arkansas.
</P>
<P>
In Texas, more than 6{ inches fell in 75 minutes in Mesquite,
washing a pickup truck and several cars into a creek and leaving
some homes 8 inches deep in water. Water was up to the tops of cars
in Garland and street flooding was reported in Heath. Nearly 6
inches fell in DeQueen, Ark.
</P>
<P>
Showers and thunderstorms were widespread over the Middle
Atlantic States, the Tennessee Valley and the Gulf Coast states.
</P>
<P>
Thunderstorms boomed today over the Dakotas and Minnesota.
</P>
<P>
In Washington, the House and Senate Agriculture committees began
working on wide-ranging legislation that would provide payments of
up to $100,000 each to farmers whose crops have been wiped out by
the dry spell.
</P>
<P>
House Agriculture Committee Chairman E. ``Kika'' de la Garza,
D-Texas, called for final action on the measure by mid-August.
</P>
<P>
The drought has dried up pastures, forcing livestock farmers to
go far afield for hay.
</P>
<P>
The hay that arrived in Kentuky today will be stored at a
fairgrounds, and distributed next week by lottery to farmers, who
will pay for the hay, officials said.
``It seems like everyone in the state wants this hay,'' state
Department of Agriculture spokesman Roger Nesbitt said Tuesday.
</P>
<P>
The delay has angered some farmers, such as Bernetta Smith, who
expects to run out of hay for her 147 beef cows in one to two days.
``I don't see any sense in storing it because people need this hay.
</P>
<P>
I don't understand it,'' she said.
</P>
<P>
At least 50 truckloads of hay gathered from the Carolinas and
Virginia are being shipped to Ohio on Thursday in a drive organized
by the Charlotte Motor Speedway and the National Association for
Stock Car Auto Racing.
</P>
<P>
Despite the recent rain, communities with dried-up water
supplies continue to restrict water use.
</P>
<P>
Until the drought ends, the 650 residents of Vintondale, Pa.,
about 50 miles east of Pittsburgh, will have to do without running
water from 7 p.m. to 7 a.m. every day, Mayor Michael Palovich said
Tuesday. Palovich said he was trying to arrange for an emergency
supply to be trucked in.
</P>
<P>
The drought has had a silver lining for anglers in the Reno,
Nevada, area. The state Board of Wildlife Commissioners removed the
limit on catches at Rye Patch and Lahontan reservoirs because the
reservoirs are expected to be dry by the end of summer, leaving
fish high and dry.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880713-0175
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>13
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
State-By-State Survey of Drought Developments
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here is a state-by-state summary of drought developments
Wednesday:
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
ALABAMA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Alabama National Guard is still hauling up to 25,000 gallons
of water a day to 10 communities across the state despite recent
rains.
</P>
<P>
At the height of the drought last month, the Guard was hauling
water to 12 locations. The Guard's water-hauling program has been
in continuous operation since last July in west-central Alabama
because of a low water table.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
GEORGIA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In an effort to help Georgia farmers locate hay, the state
Department of Agriculture announced it will start compiling a list
of sources.
</P>
<P>
Commissioner Tommy Irvin urged those with a surplus for sale to
contact the department. He said information will be compiled and
updated regularly.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
ILLINOIS
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
State Treasurer Jerry Cosentino announced a program to provide
drought-stricken farmers with access to commercial loans with
below-market interest rates. The treasurer's office will commit $50
million to banks at a lower-than-normal interest yield and in turn
those banks will offer farmers loans with rates as low as 10
percent.
``I know what the farmers first need is rain but that is out of
our hands right now,'' Cosentino said. ``The next best thing they
can get ... would be additional funds to carry them over until next
year.''
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
INDIANA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A group of Indiana farmers sued a New Jersey insurance company,
saying the company acted in bad faith when it reneged on $2.5
million in drought insurance. The lawsuit seeks an
``undeterminable'' amount of damages from Pio-Gard Agency of Ohio
Inc. and Federal Insurance Co., a subsidiary of the Chubb Group
Insurance Cos. of Warren, N.J.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
IOWA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Forecasters say Iowa's weather is returning to the hot, dry
drought pattern which settled over the state for much of June.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
KENTUCKY
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The first emergency shipment of Oregon hay to help
drought-stricken Kentucky farmers arrived, but logistical problems
forced agriculture officials to delay its distribution until next
week.
``It's a nightmare trying to find a fair way to do this,'' said
Roger Nesbitt, a spokesman for the Kentucky Department of
Agriculture.
</P>
<P>
Nesbitt said Wednesday's 20-ton shipment, flown free from
Portland, Ore., by United Parcel Service, will be sold to farmers
on Monday.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
MINNESOTA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Heavy rain fell on some of the driest areas of central and
east-central Minnesota, but it was ``way, way below what we should
have, as far as precipitation goes,'' a National Weather Service
hydrologist said.
``We need ... a widespread distribution over a long period of
time, say maybe 10 inches of rainfall to get us back to what we
normally should be,'' Gary McDevitt said.
</P>
<P>
It was the heaviest rainfall for the east-central part of the
state since April 26, when the area got about a half-inch of rain.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
MISSISSIPPI
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Weather experts say Mississippi could see above normal rainfall
in the coming week. Rainfall during the week ending Wednesday
averaged 1 inch in some areas, with some extreme northern counties
receiving greater amounts.
</P>
<P>
But the weather service said all Mississippi farm communities
still had only 30 percent to 50 percent of normal moisture.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
MISSOURI
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Road builders in the Kansas City area say the effects of dry
weather in the Midwest this year are not all bad. Engineers say
several highway projects in the area will be open to traffic at
least a month earlier than expected because of fewer interruptions
caused by rain and wet weather.
__
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
MONTANA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As many as 20 fires, sparked by lightning from thunderstorms,
have blackened about 1,500 acres in the Custer National Forest. The
fires are being fought by from 150 to 200 firefighters. A
lightning-caused fire in the Bob Marshall Wilderness Area of
northwest Montana was being allowed to burn naturally, officials
said.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
NEBRASKA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
State Agriculture Director Roy Frederick said Nebraska farmers
probably will have better crops than are expected nationwide and
may benefit from higher prices.
</P>
<P>
Nebraska's outlook for the corn crop is rosier than national
predictions because 75 percent of the corn comes from irrigated
acres and Nebraska has received more rain than some other states,
he said.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
NORTH DAKOTA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Gov. George Sinner has asked federal officials to declare all 53
North Dakota counties disaster areas because of the drought. Sinner
says the drought has wiped out small grain crops and is beginning
to take a toll on row crops.
</P>
<P>
The State Agricultural Statistics Service said North Dakota
farmers will abandon 31 percent of their spring wheat this year and
harvest the smallest crop in 19 years because of the drought. That
compares to a normal abandonment of about 5 percent. Abandonment
has not been so high in the state since the 1930s.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
OHIO
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Lt. Gov. Paul Leonard, who heads a state drought task force,
said he would not advocate statewide mandatory water restrictions
but said local governments should have the authority to impose
restrictions where necessary.
</P>
<P>
In central Ohio, farmers awaited what will be the largest
haylift of the season _ 50 truckloads of hay from the South
scheduled to arrive Thursday night in Columbus.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
SOUTH DAKOTA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Thunderstorms hit Brown County with heavy rain and hail that
damaged drought-stricken crops. Rain was heavy north and east of
Aberdeen and spotty elsewhere.
</P>
<P>
Stanley and Thelma Dennert, who live three miles west of
Houghton, reported 3.75 inches of rain within an hour. ``It was
hard with a little bit of hail. It really came down in sheets,''
said Mrs. Dennert.
</P>
<P>
Authorities said no tornado sightings were confirmed, but about
a dozen funnel clouds were reported.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
TENNESSEE
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The drought-plagued Mississippi River measured seventh-tenths of
a foot higher than expected at Memphis because of rainfall
throughout West Tennessee. The Mississippi was still 21 feet lower
than normal for this time of year, however, and the Coast Guard
said the slight rise had no effect on commercial traffic on the
river.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
WISCONSIN
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The drought has dried up summer jobs at the Stokley USA cannery
in Merrill.
</P>
<P>
During most summers, the plant provides three months' employment
for about 300 workers on three shifts, but this year there are only
225 seasonal employees on two shifts, said Vern Warren, plant
manager.
``It's been on and off so far. The drought conditions have made
it a little difficult for us,'' Warren said.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880714-0085
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>14
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Most of U.S. To Be Hot, Dry Until Mid-August, Weather Service Says
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Weather forecasters today were offering
drought-stricken farmers little prospect of relief in separate
outlooks for the next 30 days and three months.
</P>
<P>
A new climate assessment of the ongoing drought said ``many
areas now experiencing extreme drought have less than a 4 percent
chance of recovering from the drought within 3 months.''
The disappointing forecast came as President Reagan headed to
the Midwest to inspect drought-plagued farms.
</P>
<P>
On Tuesday the Agriculture Department reported sharp declines in
the outlook for several crops.
</P>
<P>
That was followed Wednesday by a 30-day forecast from the
National Weather Service saying that drought-stricken areas from
the Dakotas east to New York and from the Canadian border to
Oklahoma, Arkansas and Tennessee are likely to continue to be short
of rain.
</P>
<P>
That area, which includes the major grain-growing states where
crops already are suffering, is given a 55 percent chance of less
than normal rainfall.
</P>
<P>
And some states in the center of the area, stretching from West
Virginia to Nebraska and from Wisconsin to Missouri, may be even
drier. They are given a 60 percent chance of being short of
precipitation.
</P>
<P>
A slice of southern California, including Los Angeles, is the
driest area in the forecast, with a 70 percent chance of having
below normal rainfall. The rest of coastal California also will be
dry, the forecast said.
</P>
<P>
The outlook also says there's a 55 percent chance of hotter than
normal temperatures through the U.S. heartland from New England to
Idaho and from the Canadian border to Oklahoma. Within that area,
the chances of high temperatures are above 65 percent in Wyoming,
while central Midwestern states have a 60 percent chance of above
average temperatures.
</P>
<P>
Wetter than normal weather is predicted for west and south
Texas, and parts of New Mexico, Arizona and Utah. Normal
precipitation is forecast for the Atlantic and Gulf coast states,
along with the Northwest and northern Mountain States.
</P>
<P>
The Weather Service said normal temperatures are expected for
the Atlantic states from Virginia south, and for the Gulf Coast
states. West Texas and New Mexico may be cooler than normal, but
the far West is expected to see its normal quota of summer heat.
</P>
<P>
The separate drought impact assessment, issued by the National
Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Climate Office, points out
that predicting an end to the drought is a complex thing, since dry
spells have no normal lifetime. The low 4 percent probability of an
end within 3 months is based simply on a statistical analysis of
past droughts, the agency said.
</P>
<P>
The report noted that as of the end of June, 29 percent of the
continental United States was experiencing severe or extreme
drought, with parts of 35 states affected. That puts the current
drought on the same level as the one in 1911, but still less severe
than the droughts of 1936, 1931, 1956 and 1934.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880714-0156
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>14
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Expert Suggests Planets Affect Drought
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Drought-Northeast Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>SMYRNA, Ga. (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Weather experts discussed the drought
Thursday and its possible causes and effects, and said they hoped
to produce a consensus on how much longer it will last.
</P>
<P>
All of the speakers at the 1988 Drought Symposium called for
more research and study.
``There's an enormous number of possibilities that one could
chase. The next business of the scientist is to eliminate the
possibilities of ... and extend the range of analysis and look for
cause and effect,'' said David Rodenhuis, director of the federal
Climate Analysis Center in Washington.
</P>
<P>
The symposium attended by 13 state and national experts was
sponsored by The Weather Channel, an Atlanta-based cable network,
which broadcast the meeting live.
</P>
<P>
John Hope, the network's hurricane specialist and a former
forecaster with the National Hurricane Center in Miami, Fla., said
the drought in the Southeast might be lessened or ended in the next
few months by a heavier than normal hurricane season.
</P>
<P>
Hope said current weather conditions point to more tropical
storms, more of which should become hurricanes, in this hurricane
season.
</P>
<P>
He stressed that a hurricane's effect on drought is variable,
depending on the intensity and speed of the storm. Nevertheless, he
said, some Southeastern states get as much as 25 pecent of their
rainfall in some months from hurricanes.
</P>
<P>
Georgia state climatologist Gayther Plummer told the symposium
he thought the position of the planet Jupiter had something to do
with drought in the Southeast.
</P>
<P>
However, Rodenhuis said he was skeptical about Plummer's thesis.
``It's very necessary to be cautious and analytical about the
issue,'' he said.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880715-0065
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>15
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Experts: Public Interest In Climate May Dry Up After Drought
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>SMYRNA, Ga. (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Public interest in the Earth's troubled
climate may be washed away with the heavy rains that are needed to
end the current U.S. drought, weather experts warned during a
drought symposium here.
``Society tends to flit from hysteria to hysteria,'' said Pat
Michaels, Virginia's state climatologist and moderator of the
symposium.
</P>
<P>
He said the 1988 drought, although not as dry as a 1986 drought
in many places, has drawn much attention because some of the
affected areas include large media centers.
``I'm worried ... that when the next drought happens, we are
going to have to rediscover the climate problem,'' said Michaels,
president of the Association of State Climatologists.
</P>
<P>
Experts said Thursday that the greenhouse effect _ the warming
of the Earth's atmosphere _ has brought needed attention to changes
in the global climate, even though it is not directly related to
the drought.
</P>
<P>
Many of the 13 climatologists and meterologists at the symposium
agreed that the Earth's temperature is warming, but they debated
whether it is a short- or long-term phenomenon and its impact on
Earth.
</P>
<P>
However, Alan Hecht, director of the National Climate Program in
Washington, D.C., said the uncertainty means policymakers should
begin to deal with the possible effects, especially undertaking
policies that ``make sense in their own right.''
Mankind must reduce reliance on fossil fuels, he said, by
becoming more energy efficient, replanting forests and
investigating alternative energy supplies.
</P>
<P>
Scientists have warned in recent years that Earth's atmosphere
is gaining in carbon dioxide and other gases, which trap heat and
cause the overall temperature to rise. Besides fossil fuels, the
depletion of forests in South America has been blamed for the
increase of carbon dioxide and methane.
</P>
<P>
Some have warned that higher temperature will change the
character of many countries, for example drying out the U.S.
</P>
<P>
Midwest or melting polar ice caps.
</P>
<P>
The symposium was sponsored by The Weather Channel, an
Atlanta-based cable network, which broadcast the meeting live.
</P>
<P>
Earlier Thursday, the climatologists were told the movement of
planets and the moon and sunspots may help lead to drought in the
Southeast.
``There is some evidence that as Jupiter goes around the sun at
its fastest point, there are drought conditions in the Southeast in
the months of April and October,'' Georgia state climatologist
Gayther Plummer said.
</P>
<P>
However, David Rodenhuis, director of the federal Climate
Analysis Center in Washington, said he was skeptical of Plummer's
thesis.
``There's an enormous number of possibilities that one could
chase,'' Rodenhuis said. ``The next business of the scientist is to
... extend the range of analysis and look for cause and effect.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880716-0052
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>16
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
State-By-State Survey of Drought Developments
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Here is a state-by-state summary of the latest drought
developments:
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
ALABAMA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Recent rain in central and south Alabama haven't helped cities'
water supplies enough to lift surcharges and limits on outdoor
watering.
</P>
<P>
Northern Alabama has missed most of the rain and the region's
top crop, cotton, is in a critical situation, said John Trotman,
state director of the Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation
Service.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
GEORGIA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Georgia's carpet industry may be forced to reduce production and
lay off workers if the drought continues for an extended period,
industry officials said.
``It is something you don't like to think about, but if you
don't have water, you can't run your mills,'' said John A. Shaheen,
vice chairman of World Carpets Inc. in Dalton.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
ILLINOIS
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The drought has inflicted serious damage to wildlife along the
Illinois River, even though the water level has remained near
normal.
</P>
<P>
Wayne Herndon, a biologist with the state Department of
Conservation, said the drought, now nearly midway through its
second summer, has damaged the river's backwater lakes, virtually
eliminating a year's supply of the river's gamefish.
</P>
<P>
The mercury hit 100 degrees Friday at O'Hare International
Airport, bettering the previous high for the day of 99 and
establishing a second record by giving the city its fifth
100-degree or better temperature of the summer. Chicago sweltered
through four 100-degree days in 1934, 1947 and 1953.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
INDIANA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Thunderstorms brought rain, lightning and 70 mph winds to
northern Indiana Friday night, causing widespread power outages in
the city of Fort Wayne and apparently causing a toy factory to
collapse. No injuries were reported.
</P>
<P>
The Indiana Board of Health issued a heat warning as
temperatures soared above 100 and humidity levels boosted the heat
index to more than 110 degrees. The National Weather Service said
the conditions likely would continue through the weekend.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
IOWA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
National Guardsmen stood by with 400 gallons of drinking water
for about 50 homes in Elk Horn while officials tried to find more
water to get the town through the drought.
</P>
<P>
The U.S. Agriculture Department announced Agriculture Secretary
Richard Lyng would visit Iowa as part of a 10-state tour of drought
areas.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
KANSAS
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Severe thunderstorms spawning tornadoes and strong winds rolled
across central Kansas Friday night. A tornado touched down near
Clay Center, destroying an unoccupied mobile home and damaging
barns and hog sheds. High winds also damaged trees and power lines.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
KENTUCKY
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Agriculture Commissioner Ward ``Butch'' Burnette returned from
Oregon, saying he had prospects for perhaps 10,000 tons of hay,
badly needed by cattle producers. One railroad, CSX Transportation
Corp., offered to bring the hay free of charge from Chicago if the
Union Pacific or Burlington Northern lines could get it to Chicago.
</P>
<P>
Thirty tons of Oregon hay arrived by jet in Louisville, courtesy
of United Parcel Service. That shipment, like several others, was
earmarked for distribution Monday.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
MICHIGAN
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Severe thunderstorms accompanied by high winds and hail moved
over much of Michigan on Friday, downing trees and causing power
outages. Concern over the effects of the drought on the timber
industry outweighed relief brought by the showers.
``You have to take more precautions, and you can't use certain
machinery with exhaust systems that send sparks that might set a
fire,'' said Matt Repar, who has been logging for 28 years.
</P>
<P>
The U.S. Forest Service has banned all machinery with internal
combustion engines from the Upper Peninsula's Hiawatha National
Forest after noon. John McGregor of the state Department of Natural
Resources has said that if the drought keeps up, the state may ban
commercial logging.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
MINNESOTA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A brief thunderstorm brought little relief following record heat
that helped kill 3,000 young turkeys near Princeton and prompted
health warnings.
</P>
<P>
Friday's high of 102 degrees in the Twin Cities topped the
previous record for the date, 101 degrees i 1931. With the ``heat
index'' _ the summertime equivalent of the wind-chill factor _
forecasters said 102 degrees felt like 114.
``This is the kind of situation that is really bad for the sick
and elderly, and especially the elderly,'' said Greg Spoden,
assistant state climatologist.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
MISSOURI
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Gov. John Ashcroft issued his second statewide heat alert of the
summer, urging private and public organizations to aid those
suffering from the sizzling temperatures. ``Unless we act now to
gear up public and private efforts to care for those without
shelter from the stifling heat, the potential for human loss over
the weekend is staggering,'' Ashcroft said.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
MONTANA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
More than 700 firefighters battled a lightning-caused blaze that
combined with other fires and spread to 14,800 acres in the Custer
National Forest of southeast Montana. Bulldozers, helicopters and
bombers dropping fire retardant fought the blaze in the tinder-dry
forest on the South Dakota border
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
NORTH DAKOTA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Army Corps of Engineers has further reduced the flow of
water through Orwell Dam on the Otter Tail River near Fergus Falls,
Minn., a main feeder of the Red River, which runs along the
Minnesota-North Dakota border.
</P>
<P>
The reduction could affect Fargo's supply of water, according to
Ron Hendrickson, city water plant superintendent.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
OHIO
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Gov. Richard Celeste signed an executive order banning open
burning because of extraordinary dry conditions.
</P>
<P>
In Columbus, farmers began loading up their shares of more than
40,000 bales of hay delivered this week from three Southern states.
</P>
<P>
Farmers in the southwestern corner of the state postponed
cloud-seeding because there were no clouds.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
SOUTH DAKOTA
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Representatives from Japanese flour mills visited with wheat
producers. Ben Handcock, executive director of the South Dakota
Wheat Commission, said the Japanese would buy wheat, but probably
not from this year's crop because of the drought.
``They heard about the drought the same as everybody else did
and they think we're out of wheat. The fact of the matter is that
we have a lot of good quality wheat left from last year and
previous years,'' Handcock said.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
TENNESSEE
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Farmers say the drought is causing a shortage of feed, grass and
water, leading them to sell more livestock. At the
Tennessee-Kentucky Livestock Inc. auction barn in Guthrie, Ky.,
livestock sales have doubled, said an owner of the barn, Dorris
Bryant.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
WISCONSIN
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Gov. Tommy G. Thompson signed a drought relief bill Friday
making $35 million in emergency loans available to Wisconsin
farmers. Legislators said it could help up to 5,000 farmers avoid
losing their farms.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
