<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26242
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>19
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Central-South Region 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Reportage On Provincial Flood Situation 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
    Flood Hits Hunan Capital 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Beijing XINHUA 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Changsha, June 19 (XINHUA) - This capital of 
central China's Hunan province has been hit by floods in the 
wake of a succession of rainstorms on the upper and middle 
reaches of the Xiangjiang River. 
</P>
<P>
The water level of the river, which flows through Changsha, 
is still rising sharply, according to local sources. 
</P>
<P>
By four o'clock this afternoon the level recorded at the 
Changsha monitoring station had risen to 38.93 m, some 0.56 m 
higher than the highest figure ever previously recorded. The 
flood has caused serious losses to people along both banks of 
the river, especially in Changsha, according to the sources. 
</P>
<P>
In the early hours of yesterday six villages and one fishing 
ground at Yulushan township were flooded when an embankment 
collapsed. 
</P>
<P>
Most of the 15,000 people affected by the flood there have 
been evacuated to safer places. 
</P>
<P>
By six o'clock yesterday afternoon 19 dykes in the Changsha 
area had collapsed, and a total of 128,000 urban and rural 
residents had been affected. 
</P>
<P>
A partial collapse of the grand Longwangang embankment at 
the 
Xihu fishing ground in the Wangyuehu district of Changsha has 
put the lives and property of 60,000 people in danger. 
</P>
<P>
But thanks to the concerted rescue efforts of 2,000 local 
cadres, residents and soldiers there was no loss of life. 
</P>
<P>
The city government of Changsha has asked residents within 
the endangered areas to relocate themselves and remove their 
property to safer places, in case of the occurrence of more 
serious flooding. 
</P>
<P>
By the early hours of this morning roads and surfaces of 
bridges in the Wangyuehu district had been inundated. The flood 
waters had also reached the boulevard along the Xiangjiang 
River, Xiahe Street and the western part of Zhongshan Street in 
Changsha proper. 
</P>
<P>
So far, more than 500,000 soldiers and local residents have 
moved in to help fight the floods. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, the Changsha city committee of the Communist 
Party 
has held an emergency meeting, urging all departments and the 
people of the whole city to carry forward the spirit of 
continuous fighting and unite as one in battling the floods. 
</P>
<P>
Wang Maolin, secretary of the Hunan Provincial Party 
Committee, who is now in the province's southern city of Zhuzhou 
to direct anti-flood efforts there. In a telephone call to the 
Changsha city government, he called on local officials to adopt 
effective measures, ensure the safety of the lives and property 
of the residents of Changsha and make an overall success of the 
work to conquer the flood. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26245
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>20
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Central-South Region 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Reportage On Provincial Flood Situation 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
    Floods Continue in Guangdong, Hunan 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Beijing XINHUA 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Beijing, June 20 (XINHUA) - Floods continue to have 
serious effects in Guangdong, Hunan and Jiangxi Provinces and 
the Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region in southern China. 
</P>
<P>
Information from the State Flood Control and Drought Relief 
Headquarters revealed that the flood peak on the Xijiang River 
today reached Guangdong Province. 
</P>
<P>
By eight o'clock yesterday morning, a peak flood water level 
of 25.91 m [meters] was recorded at the flood monitoring station 
of Guangxi's Wuzhou city, 10.91 m above the danger level. 
</P>
<P>
Flood water has entered urban and suburban areas of Wuzhou 
city, and most of its transport and telecommunications with the 
outside were suspended. 
</P>
<P>
This city borders Guangdong and lies on the Xunjiang River, 
the name for the upper reaches of the Xijiang River. 
</P>
<P>
The speed of the flood-water was recorded as 46,200 cu 
[cubic] m per second, the most ferocious since the founding of 
New China in 1949. 
</P>
<P>
The flood peak on the Beijiang River in Guangdong Province 
passed through Qingyuan city by 23:00 hours last night, and the 
water level was recorded as 14.72 m, about 4.22 m above the 
danger mark; the speed was 17,400 cu m per second. 
</P>
<P>
Flood control work in the Pearl River (Zhujiang) Delta area 
is also very intense. 
</P>
<P>
The State Council, China's highest governing body, recently 
sent a joint working group formed by the Ministries of Water 
Resources, Construction and Civil Affairs to help fight floods 
in Guangxi and in Guangdong. 
</P>
<P>
At 11 o'clock on Saturday, the flood peak on the Xiangjiang 
River passed through Changsha city, capital of central China's 
Hunan Province. 
</P>
<P>
The water level recorded at the local monitoring station was 
38.93 m, some 3.93 m above danger level. High flood water 
levels were also recorded at Hengyang and Xiangtan cities. 
</P>
<P>
About 118 towns of eight prefectures and cities along the 
Xiangjiang River were flooded. 
</P>
<P>
Flood water has also entered more than 20 streets and lanes 
of Changsha, and more than 300,000 city dwellers were affected. 
</P>
<P>
More than 400 factories and 5,000 shops were forced to stop 
production or stop business. 
</P>
<P>
More than half a million Armymen and local residents, under 
the leadership of the Hunan provincial party provincial 
committee and provincial people's government, are going all out 
to fight the flood. 
</P>
<P>
By 22:00 hours last night, the flood peak passed through 
Nanchang city, provincial capital of Jiangxi. Statistics from 
the local monitoring station show that the flood water level was 
25.42 m, about 2.62 m above the danger mark, and the speed of 
the flood was 19,100 cu m per second. 
</P>
<P>
The Jiangxi provincial party committee and people's 
government are mobilizing local people and the troops stationed 
there to combat the floods. 
</P>
<P>
The State Flood Control and Drought Relief Headquarters has 
sent special teams of people to help fight floods in Hunan and 
Jiangxi. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, drought is continuing to blight most areas of 
northern China and northeastern China, with about 15.3 million 
hectares of land affected. 
</P>
<P>
In the drought-stricken areas, 12 million people and 12 
million head of livestock are short of drinking water, according 
to the State Flood Control and Drought Relief Headquarters. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26327
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>19
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> NATIONAL AFFAIRS 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Political &#60;amp; Social 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Jiang Zemin, Li Peng Express Concern Over Floods 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Beijing XINHUA Domestic Service 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Guangzhou, 19 Jun (XINHUA) - Jiang Zemin, general 
secretary of the CPC Central Committee Political Bureau and 
chairman of the Central Military Commission, and Li Peng, 
premier of the State Council, are very much concerned about 
floods in Guangdong Province. Recently, they repeatedly 
inquired about the flood situation in the Zhu Jiang valley, 
particularly that of Bei Jiang and Xi Jiang. They expressed 
their deep concern for the people in the flood-hit areas, as 
well as extended their warm greetings to the vast number of 
cadres, officers, and men of the People's Liberation Army; armed 
police officers; and public security police who battle on the 
frontline against floods and provide disaster relief. 
</P>
<P>
Jiang Zemin and Li Peng gave important directives for 
current 
flood prevention and disaster relief tasks in Guangdong. They 
expressed the hope that under the leadership of the Guangdong 
provincial party committee and government, the Guangdong army 
and people would make concerted efforts in disaster relief; 
earnestly help flood victims solve their living problems; and go 
all out to battle floods to ensure the safety of the Bei Jiang 
dike, Guangzhou city, and the Zhu Jiang Delta. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26392
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>21
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> NATIONAL AFFAIRS 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Political &#60;amp; Social 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Water Level `Dropping Slowly' 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Beijing XINHUA Domestic Service 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Beijing, 21 Jun (XINHUA) - According to the State 
Flood Control and Drought Relief Headquarters, after the largest 
or the second largest flood peaks since the liberation of China 
occurred a few days ago in the Xi Jiang, Bei Jiang, Xiang Jiang, 
and Gan Jiang rivers, water levels in these rivers are dropping 
slowly; however, high water levels will remain in these rivers 
for the next few days. Due to interaction of the Bei Jiang and 
Xi Jiang, the Zhujiang Delta will face a high water-level test. 
</P>
<P>
Heavy rainfall over a wide area since mid-June resulted in 
the largest flood waters since liberation of the country in the 
Xi Jiang, Bei Jiang, and Xiang Jiang rivers. The flood water in 
Guangdong's Xi Jiang crested in Gaoyao County on 20 June; the 
water level in Gaoyao's Xi Jiang dropped to 13.37 meters at 0600 
today. A flood peak occured in Bei Jiang in Guangdong's Sanshui 
at 0400 on 20 June, raising the water level to 10.39 meters - 
the largest flood level ever recorded. The water level droppped 
to 10.16 meters at 0600 today. 
</P>
<P>
Drops in water levels in Guangdong's Bei Jiang and Xi Jiang 
do not mean that Guangdong's flooding situations have eased, 
because flood waters in the Xi Jiang and Bei Jiang will remain 
at high levels for quite long a period and will enter the sea 
after the two flood waters jointly flow through the low-lying 
Zhujiang Delta. In particular, the sea tide may add to the 
flood waters on 25 June. With these factors combined, the 
Zhujiang Delta, which has a developed economy and a forest of 
factories, will face the most rigorous flood water test since 
the liberation of the country. 
</P>
<P>
The situation in the Xiang Jiang is also not an easy one. 
</P>
<P>
The flood peak passed Changsha on 19 June, but the water level 
at the Changsha Station was still at 25 meters at 0200 today 
[1800 GMT 20 June]. Because the water level has remained high 
for a long period, several dangerous situations have occured 
along the river's dikes. Dike reinforcing work needs to be 
stepped up. 
</P>
<P>
The flood peak in Gan Jiang entered Boyang Lake on 20 June. 
</P>
<P>
However, due to continued rains over the last few days, the 
water level in the upper reaches west of Ganzhou has begun to 
rise again. At 0800 today, the water level at the Ganzhou 
Station was 100.95 meters, 3.45 meters above the warning level. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26516
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> REGIONAL AFFAIRS 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> East Region 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Fujian Governor Addresses Flood Teleconference 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
    Heavy Agricultural Losses Incurred 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Beijing ZHONGGUO XINWEN SHE 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Fuzhou, June 22 (CNS) - Flood lasting for ten or 
more days in Fujian Province has brought about heavy losses in 
agriculture there. According to the latest information offered 
by the Provincial Agricultural Bureau, a total area of 2.465 
million mu of crops have been hit by the flood and of which, 446 
000 mu of crops will have no yield, 1.957 million mu of grain 
have been heavily hit and some 300 million kilogram grain are 
expected to be lost. 
</P>
<P>
Among nine cities and prefectures in Fujian, those seriously 
hit by the flood are Sanming, Nanping, Ningde, Fuzhou, Quanzhou 
and Putian. Of these, Sanming City is worst hit by the flood. 
</P>
<P>
In May, the city was hit by the heavy rainstorm and had big 
losses and now it suffers again from the flood with some 600 000 
mu of crops damaged by flood and 200 million kilogram grain 
expected to be lost. 
</P>
<P>
Per capita possession of cultivated land in Fujian is only 
0.05 mu. Even if in the normal years, grain output there is not 
self- sufficient. The consecutive flood has made agricultural 
production situation there more grim. Disaster-relief groups 
have been sent to the flood-stricken areas striving for 
minimizing losses. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26532
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Central-South Region 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Hunan Flood Control Work, Relief Efforts Underway 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
    Wen Jiabao Inspects Area 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Changsha Hunan People's Radio Network 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Comrade Wen Jiabao [member of CPC Central Committee 
Secretariat] and his party left Changsha for Zhuzhou and 
Xiangtan yesterday. He inspected the flooded areas, including 
Zhuzhou City's Xiawan dike, the Hexi New and High Technology 
Development Zone, and Linghuayuan and Xiangtan's Yangtianhu, 
Xingxiadi, Zhoujiangdi, and Shiwandalou, where rescue and relief 
work was in full swing. After listening to reports submitted by 
the two cities on their efforts to fight the flooding and do 
relief work, he issued important instructions. 
</P>
<P>
Comrade Wen Jiabao fully affirmed the initial victories that 
the two cities have scored in their flood fighting and relief 
work under the leadership of the provincial party committee and 
government. He said: In fighting floods and doing relief work, 
the broad masses of cadres and people in Zhuzhou and Xiangtan 
sacrificed their interests to rescue a large number of 
industrial and mining enterprises, the Beijing-Guangzhou 
Railway, the 107 National Highway, and cities and thus minimized 
the losses caused by floods. This fully shows that, with party 
leadership and the socialist system, we will be able to overcome 
all difficulties. Regarding the work in the next stage, he 
pointed out: We should continue to take flood fighting and 
relief tasks as the focus of our current work and simultaneously 
do a good job of reform, opening up to the outside world, 
stability, other fields of work, and industrial and agricultural 
production. He said: After the water recedes, we should firmly 
grasp the opportunity and repair the damaged dikes and 
embankments. As the highest flood season has not yet arrived, 
we should be prepared at any time to meet new flood peaks 
head-on rather than slacken our efforts. We should try every 
possible means to provide food, clothing, and shelter to flood 
victims, pay special attention to preventing and curing 
diseases, and concentrate efforts on the resumption of 
production and the reconstruction of homes. He particularly 
stressed: The current flooding has revealed problems in the 
construction of water conservancy facilities and urban flood 
control. In the past, inadequate consideration has been given 
to urban flood control and the coordination of urban and rural 
flood control. In the next step, we should earnestly draw a 
lesson from this negative experience. 
</P>
<P>
Governor Chen Bangzhu urged the party committees and 
governments of Zhuzhou and Xiangtan to convey Comrade Wen 
Jiabao's regards and instructions on behalf of the party Central 
Committee and the State Council for the broad masses of cadres 
and people to the party committees and governments at all levels 
as soon as possible, earnestly implement them, and effectively 
carry out the work of fighting floods, doing relief work, and 
helping oneself by engaging in production. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26604
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> REGIONAL AFFAIRS 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Central-South Region 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Over 200 Dead, 11 Million Affected by Guangdong Flood 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
    Highest `Peaks' Have Passed 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Beijing XINHUA 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Guangzhou, June 23 (XINHUA) - The highest flood 
peaks on the Xijiang and Beijiang Rivers have passed, said Zhu 
Senlin, governor of south China's Guangdong Province. 
</P>
<P>
While inspecting flood control and relief work in Qingyuan 
city on the Beijiang River yesterday, he attributed Guangdong's 
success in combating this flood - almost the biggest in 100 
years - to concerted efforts by the armymen stationed in 
Guangdong and local residents. 
</P>
<P>
More than 200 people lost their lives in the natural 
disaster, which destroyed 189,000 rooms and ruined crops on 1.2 
million hectares. 
</P>
<P>
The flood was caused by successive torrential rainstorms in 
the Xijiang and Beijiang River valleys in early and middle June. 
</P>
<P>
Major flood monitoring stations on the two rivers recorded 
their highest water levels, all four meters above the danger 
mark. 
</P>
<P>
Local governments at various levels in the province have 
paid 
close attention to flood control work, and leading government 
and communist party officials of different localities have gone 
to the flood-fighting front. 
</P>
<P>
No breaches of major embankments or reservoirs were reported 
despite the most serious flood in a hundred years, effectively 
protecting the safety of the provincial capital, Guangzhou, and 
the Pearl (Zhujiang) River Delta. 
</P>
<P>
But the losses caused by the flood were quite serious, said 
the governor. 
</P>
<P>
According to him, 11 million people in the province's nine 
cities and 55 counties were affected, and more than 200 people 
died in the natural disaster, with 189,000 rooms destroyed and 
1.2 million hectares of crops ruined. The direct economic 
losses were set at 10.2 billion yuan. 
</P>
<P>
The governor warned that though the flood danger had 
receded, 
the determination to fight possible further floods could not 
slacken, as this is just the beginning: the main flood season, 
which usually begins in late July and early August, has not yet 
arrived. 
</P>
<P>
He urged local officials to be on constant alert against 
further possible floods and be meticulous about flood prevention 
and control measures, while doing their utmost to help flood 
victims, assisting them to resume production as soon as possible 
and maintaining social stability. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26614
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>20
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> REGIONAL AFFAIRS 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Central-South Region 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Hunan Governor Interviewed on Flood Situation 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Changsha Hunan People's Radio Network 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
The following is a recorded report filed by this 
station's reporter on the front lines of the province's battle 
against the flooding yesterday. 
[Begin recording] Dear audience, it is now almost noon on 20 
June. I'm reporting in Changshanyuan at the eastern gate of 
Changsha City. This morning, Provincial Party Committee 
Secretary Wang Maolin, provincial Governor Chen Bangzhu, and 
some other provincial party and government leaders arrived here 
in Changshayuan, on the front line of the province's flood 
resistance effort, to direct the fight against the flooding. 
</P>
<P>
Governor Chen Bangzhu and vice Governor Zheng Peimin just 
arrived back in Changsha at about 0700 this morning after 
attending a Beijing meeting. As soon as they stepped out from 
the train, they set out for Changshayuan, the front line of the 
province's flood resistance. I interviewed Governor Chen 
Bangzhu here on the spot. 
[Reporter] How are you, Governor Chen? You have inspected 
some flood-stricken areas in Changsha City this morning. Will 
you please tell our audience something about the province's 
flood situation? 
[Governor] This year, Hunan has been hit by a flood of a 
severity unseen for the past 100 years in terms of both water 
level and quantity. Over the past few days, the broad masses of 
Army personnel and people across the province have been bravely 
fighting the flood and have been making concerted efforts to 
provide disaster relief to afflicted areas, with the result that 
some of the province's key dams have remained sound and economic 
losses have been reduced to a minimum. 
</P>
<P>
I would like to take this opportunity to extend my warm 
regards and thanks to the broad masses of Army personnel and 
people fighting in the front lines of the province's battle 
against the flood. At the moment, the province's flood 
situation remains very serious, because the water level is still 
high. According to weather forecasts and meteorological 
reports, the province is expecting more rain to fall over the 
next few days. We will definitely encounter more hardships and 
difficulties. Under the current circumstances, the broad masses 
of Army personnel and people across the province should further 
step up their work and devote more energy to flood prevention 
and disaster relief work, this being an overriding task at the 
moment. 
</P>
<P>
We are full of confidence that, under the leadership of the 
CPC Central Committee and the State Council, the broad masses of 
the Hunan Army personnel and people will be able to overcome the 
difficulties and hardships caused by natural calamities such as 
flooding, waterlogging, and so on and will win a complete 
victory in the on-going flood prevention and disaster relief 
struggle. [end recording] 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26768
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>24
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> NATIONAL AFFAIRS 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Political &#60;amp; Social 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Wen Jiabao Inspects Flood Situation in Jiangxi 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Beijing XINHUA Domestic Service 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
[By JIANGXI RIBAO reporter Zhang Wei (1728 3555) and XINHUA 
reporter Wu Huaguo (0702 5478 0948)] 
Nanchang, 24 Jun (XINHUA) - A central work team led 
Wen Jiabao, alternate member of the CPC Central Committee 
Political Bureau and member of the CPC Central Committee 
Secretariat, arrived in Jiangxi from Hunan this morning to 
provide on-the-spot guideance for Jiangxi to conduct 
flood-fighting and relief work and to resume industrial and 
agricultural production. 
</P>
<P>
Immediately after disembarking from the plane, Wen Jiabao 
and 
his party - accompanied by Mao Zhiyong, secretary of the 
Jiangxi Provincial Party Committee, and Governor Wu Guanzheng - 
successively rushed to the Nanchang Bridge, the Leigongao 
construction work site along the Nanchang-Jiujiang Highway which 
is reserved for vehicles, Weidong Village under Changling Town 
in Xinjian County, and Houtian Township's Sanzhou Village. They 
inspected the flood situation along the Ganjiang River, visited 
the masses of flood victims, and extended greetings and 
appreciation to the servicemembers and civilians who have been 
performing rescue and emergency tasks. The same evening, Wen 
Jiabao and his party earnestly listened to reports by the 
Jiangxi Provincial Party Committee and government on Jiangxi's 
flood situation and its flood-fighting and relief work. 
</P>
<P>
Wen Jiabao highly commended Jiangxi's servicemembers and 
people for their spirit that stresses fostering unity and 
coordinated efforts, striving to help and rescue themselves, and 
continually fighting when encountering extraordinarily 
disastrous floods. He also fully affirmed Jiangxi's preliminary 
victories in its flood-fighting and relief work. Wen Jiabao 
pointed out: At present, the Ganjiang River's water-level is 
declining, but the Jiangxi Provincial Party Committee and 
government are still facing very arduous tasks. While 
continually and properly conducting flood-fighting and relief 
work along the Ganjiang River valleys, we should stress 
flood-prevention in the Poyang Lake area and should promptly 
organize the masses in the disaster-stricken areas to resume 
production so as to be self-reliant and to rebuild their homes. 
</P>
<P>
Jiangxi is a major agricultural province. We should take 
measures to promptly salvage the early-ripening rice, and should 
expand the planting of late-ripening rice and autumn grain as 
much as possible so as to attain a bumper harvest of grain for 
the whole year. While carrying out flood-fighting and relief 
work, we should also continually and properly handle various 
tasks concerning reform, stability, and development in Jiangxi. 
</P>
<P>
It has been learned that on 25 June Wen Jiabao and his party 
will visit other localities including Xingan, Fengcheng, and 
Jian where the flooding has been the most serious. They will 
further inspect the flood situation and extend sympathy and 
solicitude to flood victims there. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>FBIS4-26769
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> FBIS 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>6
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>94
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> NATIONAL AFFAIRS 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<DATELINE_COUNTRY> Political &#60;amp; Social 
</DATELINE_COUNTRY>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   Wen Jiabao, Spokesman Comment on Flood Situation 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<ORIG_SOURCE>  Beijing XINHUA 
</ORIG_SOURCE>
<TEXT>
<P>
BFN 
Beijing, June 26 (XINHUA) - Floods have all 
receded along Xijiang, Beijiang, Xiangjiang and Ganjiang except 
at a section of the Xijiang River in Wuzhou city, Guangxi, a 
spokesman from the State Flood Control and Drought Relief 
Headquarters announced today. 
</P>
<P>
The spokesman attributed the falling water level to the 
major 
water conservancy projects which help to mitigate losses. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, he said, tension has been eased in the Pearl River 
delta as the latest tropical storm has been weakened after 
landing in Yangjiang city, Guangdong Province. 
</P>
<P>
Floods hit Guangdong, Guangxi, Hunan, Jiangxi, Fujiang and 
Zhejiang provinces following the first heavy rains and floods 
which typically hit China from the south to the north from June 
to August. 
</P>
<P>
Earlier reports said that successive torrential rainstorms 
in 
the Xijiang and Beijiang river valleys in early and mid-June 
resulted in a big flood, one of the most serious in 100 years, 
in Guangdong Province and caused heavy losses. Major flood 
monitoring stations on the two rivers recorded their highest 
water levels, all four meters above the warning level. 
</P>
<P>
In an urgent conference late yesterday, the Guangdong 
provincial government urged localities to help flood victims 
with food, shelter, clothing and medical care so that no one 
would die of hunger and no epidemic disease would break out in 
the flooded areas. 
</P>
<P>
The province has allocated 300 million kg of grain and 110 
million yuan in cash along with over 10 million tons of such 
farm production supplies as chemical fertilizer and diesel oil 
to the flood-stricken areas. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, 740 million yuan in loans and another 50 million 
yuan in donations have also been sent to flooded areas in 
Guangdong Province. 
</P>
<P>
While inspecting flood control and relief work in Jiangxi 
Province, through which the Ganjiang flows, Wen Jiabao, 
alternate member of the Political Bureau and member of the 
Secretariat of the CPC Central Committee, said the flooded areas 
should work hard to mitigate losses through their own efforts 
and with support from various departments. 
</P>
<P>
While inspecting Nanchang, the capital city of Jiangxi, and 
Fengcheng, Xingang, Jian and Taihe, on June 24-26, Wen said the 
key to mitigating economic losses is to resume production as 
soon as possible. 
</P>
<P>
The localities should waste no time in implementing various 
measures to resume production and rehabilitate their homeland, 
he said. 
</P>
<P>
As one of China's major bread baskets, Jiangxi is of key 
importance to China in agricultural production, Wen said. It 
has a direct bearing on the grain supply in south China. He 
urged the local governments to farmers resume agricultural 
production. 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
