<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900731-0113
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>31
</DAY> 
<MONTH>07
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
100,000 Troops Massed on Iraq-Kuwait Border as Talks Begin
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>JIDDAH, Saudi Arabia (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Kuwaiti and Iraqi negotiators
embraced warmly Tuesday as they began talks on their oil and border
dispute, sources said. Diplomats reported that Iraq had massed
100,000 troops on Kuwait's border.
</P>
<P>
Gulf-based diplomatic sources said the Iraqi force, triple the
number earlier reported, included about 300 Soviet-made tanks, and
dwarfed the entire Kuwaiti army of 20,000 troops.
</P>
<P>
The diplomats, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the
troops have been concentrated along the border since last week,
when Iraq began threatening Kuwait. Iraq accused the small Persian
Gulf state of stealing oil from a disputed border region and
forcing oil prices to drop. The diplomats said the number of troops
was at first difficult to determine.
</P>
<P>
The delegation leaders, Crown Prince and Prime Minister Sheik
Saad al-Abdullah al-Sabah of Kuwait, and Izzat Ibrahim, deputy
chairman of Iraq's Revolutionary Command Council, met privately for
two hours.
</P>
<P>
There were no details on the negotiations, but sources said the
meetings will continue Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
Diplomatic sources have said they expect Arab mediators to push
the two sides to sign a treaty of non-belligerency to be followed
by protracted negotiations on borders and compensation.
</P>
<P>
The Iraq-Kuwait crisis broke out on July 17 when Iraqi President
Saddam Hussein accused Kuwait and the United Arab Emirates of
driving down oil prices by exceeding quotas set for them by the
Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries. Saddam said the move
cost Iraq $14 billion in lost revenue.
</P>
<P>
Saddam also demanded compensation for the $2.4 billion in oil he
claimed Kuwait pumped illegally from an oil field which straddles
the unmarked border between the two countries.
</P>
<P>
Iraq also demanded that Kuwait forgive $15 billion in loans it
extended to Baghdad during the eight-year Iran-Iraq war.
</P>
<P>
Iraq's tough talk appeared to have succeeded. Kuwait and the
U.A.E agreed to stick to their oil quotas at an OPEC meeting last
week. OPEC member states also agreed to a longstanding Iraqi demand
to raised target crude oil prices from $18 to $21 a barrel.
</P>
<P>
Kuwaiti and Iraqi officials agreed to meet in Jiddah after
intensive mediation efforts by King Fahd and Egyptian President
Hosni Mubarak.
</P>
<P>
Kuwaiti leaders had insisted that Iraq pull back its troops
before conciliation talks could began, but later dropped that
demand.
</P>
<P>
Kuwaiti officials also asked that Iraq agree to demarcate the
disputed border between the nations, a move Iraq has refused.
</P>
<P>
Iraq has historically laid claim to all of Kuwait and has long
coveted the Kuwaiti islands of Bubiyan and Warba, which command
access to Iraq's sole outlet into the Persian Gulf.
</P>
<P>
The mediators have succeeded in toning down a vitriolic campaign
against Kuwait by the Iraqi state-run media.
</P>
<P>
On Tuesday, the Iraqi delegation left Baghdad without any public
announcement.
</P>
<P>
The leading Al-Thawra daily newspaper called the Jiddah meeting
``an opportunity ... for Kuwait ... to perceive Iraq's demands and
respond to its rights.''
In contrast, the Kuwaiti delegation left for Jiddah with fanfare
and publicity.
</P>
<P>
The Kuwaiti papers said they hoped the Jiddah meeting was the
start of ``a final just settlement'' of the differences between
Iraq and Kuwait, in a manner ensuring the ``legitimate rights of
each.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900802-0092
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>02
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
U.N. Security Council Condemns Iraqi Invasion, Seeks Pullout,
Talks
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The U.N. Security Council today swiftly
condemned Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, demanding an unconditional
withdrawal of Iraqi troops and calling for immediate negotiations
between the countries.
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi envoy said his country's troops would withdraw ``as
soon as the situation is stable,'' perhaps within ``a few days or
some weeks.''
The Security Council resolution was adopted 14-0 in an emergency
session requested by the United States and Kuwait hours after
today's pre-dawn invasion. Neither Kuwait nor Iraq is on the
15-member council.
</P>
<P>
The representative of Yemen said he did not vote because he had
not received instructions from his government.
</P>
<P>
Britain's U.N. envoy, Crispin Tickell, condemned the invasion as
an ``ugly moment in world affairs.'' Kuwait is a former British
colony.
``The United States has made it clear that it will stand
shoulder to shoulder with Kuwait in this time of crisis,'' U.S.
</P>
<P>
Ambassador Thomas Pickering told the council. ``It is our
understanding that the present aggression was completely
unprovoked.''
Baghdad radio claimed Iraq had come to the aid of
``revolutionary youth in Kuwait'' whom it said had toppled the
Kuwaiti government.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's ambassador to the United Nations, Mohammad Abulhasan,
denied the invasion was in response to a call from help from a new
government.
``The pretext to invade an independent, sovereign state is a
false, flimsy pretext,'' he said. ``This kind of pretext, if it's
not going to be deterred in a decisive manner and by this august
assembly, all international relations will be threatened. No
country at all will be safe after this.''
A statement read by Sabah Talat Kadrat, Iraq's deputy permanant
representative said Iraq's forces would withdraw when what it
referred to as the ``free Kuwaiti interim government'' requested it.
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi statement was also reported by the Iraqi News Agency
in Baghdad.
</P>
<P>
The Security Council resolution said the council supports all
efforts for negotiations between Iraq and Kuwait. It specifically
endorsed mediation efforts by the Arab League, which met in
emergency session in Cairo today.
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi invasion posed ``a breach of international peace and
security,'' the Security Council said.
</P>
<P>
Kadrat said the events were related to an internal matter that
was not the council's concern.
``The Iraqi government firmly believes and states that Iraq is
pursuing no goal or objective and wishes only cordial relations
with Kuwait,'' said Kadrat. ``Furthermore, it is the Kuwaitis
themselves who will determine their own future and Iraqi forces
will withdraw as soon as order has been restored.''
Members of the 15-member Security Council began gathering at the
United Nations shortly after midnight. Diplomats held more than
three hours of private consultations before convening the formal
meeting.
</P>
<P>
Kuwaiti spokesman Nasser Al-Sabeeh said before the formal
meeting that Kuwait wants negotiations with Iraq to be mediated by
the Arab League.
``But if it's necessary, then we would seek U.N. mediation,'' he
said.
</P>
<P>
Two weeks ago, President Saddam Hussein of Iraq threatened
military action with Kuwait over its violation of OPEC oil
production ceilings and a disputed border oil field.
</P>
<P>
Saddam also has accused some Persian Gulf nations of conspiring
with the United States and Israel to weaken Iraq's economy and
undermine its military buildup.
</P>
<P>
Today's resolution was sponsored by Canada, Colombia, Ivory
Coast, Ethiopia, Finland, France, the United States, Britain and
Malaysia.
</P>
<P>
The 15 members of the Security Council are China, Yemen,
Romania, the Soviet Union, Cuba, Canada, Colombia, Ivory Coast,
Ethiopia, Finland, France, the United States, the United Kingdom,
Malaysia and Zaire.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900802-0135
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>02
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
URGENT
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Iraq Invades Kuwait; U.S. Responds With Sanctions
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhotos NY4,5,6,8; LaserGraphics
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>KUWAIT (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iraq's powerful army invaded this small oil-rich
kingdom early today. Tank-led troops quickly seized the ruler's
palace and government buildings, and the emir fled to Saudi Arabia,
Kuwaiti officials said.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's U.S. ambassador said the Iraqis occupied all government
buildings in the capital and were moving south toward the country's
oil facilities. He appealed for U.S. military intervention.
</P>
<P>
A Pentagon source said U.S. Navy ships were diverted to the
region, but President Bush said the subject of intervention was not
being discussed.
``The Iraqis have occupied all of Kuwait!'' a Kuwaiti government
official shouted in a telephone interview. Diplomatic sources in
the Persian Gulf estimated that more than 200 Kuwaitis were killed
or wounded.
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi government of President Saddam Hussein claimed it
invaded at the request of revolutionaries who had already staged a
coup and established ``The Provisional Government of Free Kuwait.''
Kuwait and U.N. diplomats labeled the coup report a farce.
</P>
<P>
The assault followed two weeks of tension between Kuwait and
Iraq, caused by Iraqi accusations that Kuwait stole oil from a
disputed border area. Saddam also accused Kuwait of exceeding OPEC
production quotas, thus driving down the price of oil, a major
Iraqi revenue source.
</P>
<P>
The attack had wide-ranging ramifications:
_Oil prices soared $3 a barrel in early trading because of fears
the invasion would disrupt supplies. Prices were about $2 higher
later.
_President Bush signed orders freezing Iraqi assets in the
United States and blocking most Iraqi imports, including oil. Oil
accounts for 97 percent of Iraqi imports to the United States and
makes up about 3.5 percent of U.S. oil consumption. Bush also froze
Kuwaiti assets to prevent Iraq from seizing them.
_The Soviet Union, Iraq's main arms supplier, halted weapons
sales.
_The U.N. Security Council voted 14-0 to denounce the invasion
and demanded immediate withdrawal of Iraqi troops.
_A Pentagon source said the aircraft carrier USS Independence,
escorted by a six-ship battle group, was diverted from the Indian
Ocean toward the gulf, where other U.S. ships were already
patrolling.
_Secretary of State James A. Baker III planned to fly to Moscow
to issue a rare joint statement Friday with Soviet Foreign Minister
Eduard A. Shevardnadze about the invasion. The plan, which was
announced in Washington, illustrates the dramatic improvement in
relations between the superpowers, who once routinely lined up on
opposite sides of most regional disputes.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's U.S. ambassador, Sheik Saud Nasir al-Sabah, told
reporters in Washington: ``We are desperate for any help we can
get.'' He appealed specifically for American intervention.
</P>
<P>
In recent days, diplomats said Iraq had massed more than 100,000
troops at the border. Kuwait's entire armed forces has 20,300
soldiers.
</P>
<P>
Bush said the United States would ``take whatever steps
necessary'' to defend interests in the gulf. Asked if this included
military force, Bush said: ``We're not discussing intervention.''
But he said he would not discuss military options publicly.
</P>
<P>
It was the first time in modern history an Arab nation had
invaded another and taken over its government.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's army was no match for Iraq, battle-hardened after eight
years of war with Iran. Iraq has emerged as the Arab world's
strongest and most militant military power, and Saddam has a vast
arsenal of chemical and conventional weapons.
</P>
<P>
Diplomats said about 350 Iraqi tanks wheeled into the capital a
few hours after crossing the border 40 miles away at dawn.
</P>
<P>
Witnesses said the bombardment of ports and military airports by
artillery and the air force was vicious.
</P>
<P>
The invaders surrounded the palace of Kuwait's ruler, Sheik
Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah. Residents said the palace was seized after
about two hours of heavy artillery barrages.
</P>
<P>
Diplomats said Sheik Fahd al-Ahmed al-Sabah, one of the emir's
brothers, was killed while trying to defend the palace.
</P>
<P>
There were about 50 tanks around the palace and the neighboring
American Embassy, residents said.
</P>
<P>
The al-Sabah family has ruled the city-state for almost 250
years. The Kuwaiti ambassador said the leaders were safe in Saudi
Arabia.
</P>
<P>
Operating from an unknown location, al-Ahmed's government
responded to the formation of the provisional government by
stating: ``Kuwait is Kuwait to its people, let by the emir, Sheik
Jaber, and his Crown Prince Sheik Saad. God preserve them from all
harm.''
For its part, the provisional government announced through
Baghdad's official Iraqi News Agency that it was dissolving
parliament and would hold ``free and honest elections'' at a future
date.
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi forces were led by the elite Republican Guard, which
did the brunt of fighting in the Iran-Iraq war. Troops set up
roadblocks at major intersections and shot at cars that did not
stop.
</P>
<P>
Baghdad television said Iraq qould withdraw its forces within
days or weeks, depending on how quickly the situation stabilized.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's land and sea borders were closed, as was the airport.
</P>
<P>
Diplomats said the invasion was too swift to arrange the
evacuation of nationals, and foreigners were asked to keep a low
profile.
</P>
<P>
There are about 4,000 Americans among the large expatriate
community in Kuwait, where more than 60 percent of the 1.8 million
residents are foreigners. U.S. officials monitoring the situation
had no reports of harm to U.S. citizens in Iraq, White House
spokesman Roman Popadiuk said.
</P>
<P>
Foreigners reached by telephone said they watched from their
windows or dived for cover as the invasion began. ``We were totally
unprepared,'' said Catherine Baker of Illinois. ``One feels like
there should have been a bit of warning.''
The British Embassy was hit by shell-fire and the Sheraton and
Hilton hotels evacuated their clientele, the diplomats said.
</P>
<P>
The invasion came hours after Iraq broke off talks intended to
mend its differences with Kuwait.
</P>
<P>
Iraqi first threatened military action against its former ally
Kuwait two weeks ago. Washington declared its support for Kuwait
from the start.
</P>
<P>
During the Iran-Iraq war, American ships protected U.S.-flagged
Kuwaiti tankers from attacks in the gulf.
</P>
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Kuwait radio, 1st graf, a0571
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900802-0159
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>02
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Arab League Fails at Emergency Meeting to Condemn Iraq's Invasion
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An emergency Arab League Council failed to
publicly condemn Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on Thursday and
adjourned its meeting for 24 hours as Arab leaders held urgent
consultations on how to handle the crisis.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's Cabinet affairs minister, Abdel-Rahman el-Awadi told
reporters he asked the 21-nation Arab League to condemn the attack.
</P>
<P>
He accused Iraq of using the ``laws of the jungle.''
President Hosni Mubarak and Jordan's King Hussein met in
Alexandria and telephoned Iraqi President Saddam Hussein, President
Bush, Saudi King Fahd and Yemeni President Ali Abdallah Saleh on
the crisis. Hussein later left for home.
</P>
<P>
Sources close to the Arab League Council said its members agreed
to convene an emergency Arab summit but decided to leave the when
and where up to Arab leaders. The sources spoke on condition of
anonymity.
</P>
<P>
The Council meeting of foreign ministers was convened in Cairo
at Kuwaiti request hours after Iraqi military forces took over the
small Persian Gulf state. Some member nations sent lower-level
representatives.
</P>
<P>
Following its evening session, attended by Saadoon Hamadi, a
member of the Iraqi Revolutionary Council, Foreign Minister Esmat
Abdel-Meguid of Egypt told reporters the Council would meet again
Friday.
</P>
<P>
Saddam promised Mubarak two weeks ago that he would not invade
Kuwait in their oil dispute.
</P>
<P>
At Thursday's closed session, Hamadi reiterated Iraq's claim its
forces entered Kuwait at the request of a Kuwaiti revolutionary
group that had overthrown the government.
</P>
<P>
A conference source said several Arab foreign ministers replied
that ``they considered this to be an Iraqi invasion which is
against all United Nations and Arab League conventions.''
So far, only Lebanon's prime minister and foreign minister,
Salim Hoss, has joined Kuwait in Cairo in publicly condemning the
invasion _ the first time in modern history one Arab country
invaded another to take control of the government.
</P>
<P>
Hoss told reporters, ``We do not see any justification for what
happened, whatever the arguments and pretexts.''
The invasion was denounced by the United States and other
Western nations and by the Soviet Union.
</P>
<P>
The Arab League Council met early Thursday and then adjourned to
await the arrival of Hamdoon. Iraq's ambassador to Egypt, Nabil
Najm, sat in until Hamdoon arrived.
``The United Nation's Security Council has condemned the
invasion and the issue is now being discussed within the framework
of the Arab League and we hope that it will issue a condemnation
within the hour and that Arabs stand against this invasion,''
Kuwait's Awadi said.
``Arab leaders must take the initiative and stop this bloodshed
and return things to their normal situation. We also call on Iraq
to withdraw its troops.''
Hamadi told reporters upon arrival, ``I see this meeting as
unnecessary ... There is no government presently in Kuwait. There
is a group which started the revolution and which will reveal
itself shortly.''
His comments were carried by the Middle East News Agency.
</P>
<P>
MENA said Kuwait invoked the 1950 Arab joint defense pact and
asked the Arab League Council to dispatch a joint Arab force to
``defend Kuwait against the invasion.''
In the event of military aggression against any League member,
the pact all members, to ``take, individually and collectively, all
steps available, including the use of armed force, to repel the
aggression and restore security and peace.''
The ministers were in Cairo to attend the Organization of
Islamic Conference's foreign ministers meeting. All Arab League
members also belong to the Islamic conference.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900802-0164
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>02
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Kuwaiti `Free Government' Statements Indicate Iraqi Control
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iraq says it invaded Kuwait at the
request of a revolutionary organization there, but diplomats
dismiss that rationale as a large-scale charade.
</P>
<P>
The diplomatic world has remained largely unconviced by the
flood of statements issued from Iraq in the name of the Provisional
Free Kuwait Government.
</P>
<P>
Britain's U.N. ambassador, Crispin Tickell, called the Iraqi
action ``an invasion from the outside ... a phony coup d'etat from
within.'' He said the invasion had led to ``the purported
establishment of a puppet government.''
In a rare display of solidarity, the United States and the
Soviet Union called for Iraq to withdraw and imposed sanctions. The
U.N. Security Council voted 14-0 to condemn the invasion.
</P>
<P>
But Iraq's deputy permanent U.N. representative, Sabah Talat
Kadrat, said the Security Council should not be debating the issue,
because the fall of the Kuwaiti Emir, Sheik Jaber Al-Ahmed
Al-Sabah, was an internal matter.
</P>
<P>
The official Kuwait News Agency, monitored in Nicosia, did not
issue a single story all day. Its computer periodically sputtered
out the phrase ``Line cut.''
On the other hand, state-run Iraqi News Agency from Baghdad came
alive with a series of communiques from the ``provisional
government.'' The members were not identified.
</P>
<P>
The first statement said the provisional government ``finds that
one of its primordial obligations is to remedy the harm done by the
deposed, corrupt government to our brothers in Iraq.''
Iraq has been feuding with Kuwait over a border dispute. It has
also accused Kuwait of violating its oil production quotas set by
the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, costing Iraq of
much-needed revenues because oil is cheaper when supplies are
higher.
</P>
<P>
The statement on the Iraqi News Agency said the border dispute
would be settled with ``fraternity and Arab national interests,''
indicating Iraq would probably take the land it wants.
</P>
<P>
The statement also said the Al-Sabah family, which had ruled
Kuwait for almost 250 years, was working in concert with Zionist
and colonial powers to plot against Iraq.
</P>
<P>
That is the charge the Iraqi press leveled at Kuwait when
tensions began to rise in mid-July.
``Falsification of elections, authoritarianism, persecution of
patriotic personalities have always been characteristics of the
Al-Sabah family,'' the statement said.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait is one of the few Arab states that has experimented with
a freely elected parliament. A new National Council with 50 members
voted into office and 25 appointed by the emir took office after
June elections.
</P>
<P>
The communiques from the Iraqi News Agency said the National
Council has been disbanded.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900802-0180
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>02
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Basic Facts of Iraq's Invasion of Kuwait
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
THE INVASION: Iraq's troops, led by about 350 tanks, crossed the
border at dawn Thursday, and seized the Kuwaiti palace and
government buildings 40 miles away. Early Friday, the invaders
controlled Kuwait city, the capital. The soldiers were also making
sweeps through the southern oilfields, according to residents and
Lloyds' insurance service in London. Diplomatic sources estimate
more than 200 Kuwaitis were killed or wounded, mainly from the
Emiri Guard which bore the main brunt of the invasion. Kuwait's
Sheik Saad al-Abdullah al-Sabah fled to safety in Saudi Arabia.
</P>
<P>
THE FORCES: Iraq, a country of more than 17 million, has the
Arab world's most battle-trained army, and had massed more than
100,000 soldiers on the Kuwaiti border. Kuwait, an oil-rich
city-state, has 1.9 million residents _ 60 percent foreigners _ and
an army of 20,300 soldiers.
</P>
<P>
CAUSE OF CONFLICT: President Saddam Hussein of Iraq accused
Kuwait of stealing oil from its territory and forcing down oil
prices through overproduction. Kuwait and U.N. diplomats dismissed
Iraq's claim that it invaded at the request of Kuwaiti
revolutionaries.
</P>
<P>
REACTION: The U.N. Security Council voted 14-0 to condemn the
invasion.
</P>
<P>
President Bush denounced it as ``naked agression.'' He froze
Iraq's assets in the United States and blocked almost all Iraqi
imports, including oil. The order also froze Kuwait property under
U.S. jurisdiction _ a move intended to keep Iraq from seizing it.
</P>
<P>
The Soviets also condemned the invasion and stopped arms sales
to Iraq.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's U.S. ambassador said the nation had asked for American
military intervention.
</P>
<P>
A Pentagon source said a U.S. naval group was diverted toward
the Persian Gulf.
</P>
<P>
Oil prices soared in frenzied trading amid fears the invasion
would reduce the supply of oil.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900803-0004
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>03
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Saddam Grabs Kuwait to Fulfill Territorial, Financial Ambitions
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhotos NY4, LON2 of Aug. 2
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
An AP News Analysis
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iraqi President Saddam Hussein seemed
determined to solve his financial problems and fulfill territorial
ambitions by dethroning the government of neighboring Kuwait.
</P>
<P>
The invasion, unprecedented in modern Arab history, reflected
the brutality Saddam has used to crush all opposition at home since
coming to power in 1979.
</P>
<P>
The sentence for criticizing Saddam is death, and the president
considered Kuwait's oil overproduction and the subsequent fall in
the price of oil a personal affront to Iraq.
``Iraqis will not forget the saying that cutting necks is better
than cutting means of living. Oh God Almighty, be witness that we
have warned them,'' he said last month after prices tumbled below
$14 per barrel.
</P>
<P>
He accused Kuwait and the United Arab Emirates of costing Iraq
$14 billion in lost oil revenue by ignoring their quotas assigned
by the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries.
</P>
<P>
He also accused Kuwait of stealing $2.4 billion by pumping oil
from a disputed field that straddled their border, and demanded
that Kuwait write off an estimated $15 billion it loaned Iraq
during the Persian Gulf war.
</P>
<P>
Saddam was reported to be incensed that Kuwait was demanding
repayment for the wartime loans. Saddam said he fought the war to
protect the Arabs from the fundamentalist revolution fomented by
the late Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini in Persian, mainly Shiite
Moslem Iran.
</P>
<P>
Never mind that Iraq started the war in 1980 by invading Iran
after a series of border skirmishes along the Shatt-al-Arab
waterway, Iraq's only outlet to the Gulf.
</P>
<P>
Despite claims that the war was an unprecedented victory, the
long conflict stalled Iraq's development, dragging on for eight
years. It has still not formally ended.
</P>
<P>
The war bills kept the government from delivering material
benefits promised to the Iraqi people directly after the war. The
1990 budget slashed funds for imports and Iraqis were told to brace
for another year of austerity. Private investment has failed to
take hold.
</P>
<P>
Iraq ended the war an estimated $70 billion in debt. Its main
gulf port of Basra is still blocked and its oil infrastructure
damaged. Tens of thousands of Iraqi prisoners of war languish in
Iranian prisons and an estimated 500,000 Iraqis were killed or
wounded.
</P>
<P>
Despite its puny size, Kuwait's oil reserves almost match Iraq's
100 billion barrels.
</P>
<P>
By controlling Kuwait, Saddam could help solve the financial
hangover from the Persian Gulf war and fulfill Iraq's longstanding
wish for more gulf coastline.
</P>
<P>
Iraq's 100,000 troops massed at the border in the past few weeks
were believed part of a pressure campaign to make Kuwait capitulate
to Iraq's demands.
</P>
<P>
But Kuwait's pledge two weeks ago to obey new OPEC quotas and
Saddam's promise to Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak that he would
not invade lulled the Arab world into the sense the crisis was over.
</P>
<P>
Homage to the cause of Arab unity has been paramount in Middle
East politics since postwar independence from colonial powers.
</P>
<P>
Although a civil war in Yemen in the 1960s brought Egyptian and
Saudi Arabian intervention on opposing sides, no Arab state has
ever directly deposed the government of a fellow Arab League member.
</P>
<P>
Despite Iraqi claims that it is helping internal opposition
liberate Kuwait, it has long coveted the tiny emirate.
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi government refused to recognize its independence in
1961 and threatened to attack then, but backed down when Britain
landed troops in Kuwait.
</P>
<P>
The invasion shook Kuwait's neighbors along the Gulf. It proved
the decade-old Gulf Cooperation Council that groups Saudi Arabia,
Bahrain, Qatar, the United Arab Emirates, Oman and Kuwait was
toothless. The GCC did not issue a statement, much less implement
its mutual defense treaty.
</P>
<P>
While Iraq was unlikely to invade Saudi Arabia, it could use the
precedent of Kuwait to browbeat its neighbors on local policy
issues. Bombing an oil field would be a sufficient reminder of what
happened to Kuwait when it balked at Iraqi demands.
</P>
<P>
Also in a region entirely ruled by absolute monarchs, the fall
of one makes the rest feel extremely vulnerable.
</P>
<P>
In a series of bellicose statements in recent months, Saddam has
sought to focus domestic attention outside Iraq.
</P>
<P>
In March he threatened to burn half of Israel with Iraq's
chemical weapons _ banned under international law _ if Iraq was
attacked. It was a popular stance among Arabs frustrated with the
lack of progress toward peace and a Palestinian nation in the
Arab-Israeli conflict.
</P>
<P>
Then Britain arrested several people on charges they were
smuggling nuclear triggers into Baghdad. Weeks later, police in
Europe impounded what they said was parts to a supergun capable of
firing chemical or nuclear shells into Israel.
</P>
<P>
Saddam cried foul, claiming the West was trying to wreck the
scientific progress of the Arabs.
</P>
<P>
Saddam has sought to inherit the mantle of the late Egyptian
President Gamal Abdel Nassar as the leader of the Arab world.
</P>
<P>
His relentless personality cult has dubbed him ``The Knight of
the Arabs.'' For Kuwait on Thursday, he was a dark knight.
</P>
<P>
Asked the reason for the invasion, Kuwait's ambassador to
Washington Sheik Saud Nasir Al-Sabah said at a news conference:
``Ambition. Hegemony. Control of the whole area. There is not any
reason for it.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900804-0057
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>04
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Saudis Take No Steps Against Iraq
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With PM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Saudi Arabia, an oil-rich ally of Kuwait,
has been subdued in its reaction to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
</P>
<P>
The only direct Saudi statement since the invasion was made by
an anonymous government spokesman through the official Saudi Press
Agency the day after the Iraqi move. It did not condemn Thursday's
invasion.
</P>
<P>
It said Saudi Arabia was following the Kuwait situation ``with
extreme concern'' and that King Fahd would be seeking to calm the
situation and to find a solution ``in a manner ensuring the
interests of all.''
The only tangible help Saudi Arabia gave the Kuwait government
was to shelter members of the ruling family, including the emir,
Sheik Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah, and his crown prince. Both nations
are tightly run by royal families.
</P>
<P>
The Saudis also allowed them briefly to operate a radio,
reportedly from a mobile van in the area around the Saudi-Kuwait
border. It broadcast calls for resistance to the Iraqis.
</P>
<P>
But on Friday the radio went off the air after a desperate call:
``The people of Kuwait appeal to you oh brethren, oh Arabs, oh
beloved brothers, oh Moslems, rush, rush to their help.''
It was not known if the radio had been discovered by the Iraqis
or shut down by the Saudis to avoid provoking Iraqi President
Saddam Hussein at a time when fears were being expressed that he
might invade Saudi Arabia as well.
</P>
<P>
Oil executives said Saudi Arabia has not and will not take the
most potent action possible against Iraq _ closing the pipeline
that carries Iraqi oil for export across Saudi Arabia to the Red
Sea.
</P>
<P>
The executives said the Saudis realize this would give the
belligerent Saddam an excuse to attack and occupy the Saudi oil
fields 150 miles south of Kuwait, giving Iraq control of more oil
than any other country in the world.
</P>
<P>
Turkey also has refused to comment about President Bush's
suggestion that Turkey cut off Iraq's oil pipeline to the
Mediterranean. Two parallel pipelines pump Iraqi crude oil to a
terminal at Yumurtalik at the eastern corner of Turkey's
Mediterranean coast and constitute Iraq's major oil export outlet.
</P>
<P>
The Saudis did condemn the invasion as part of a joint statement
issued by the Gulf Cooperation Council, in which it is allied for
economic and security cooperation with Kuwait, the United Arab
Emirates, Qatar, Oman and Bahrain.
</P>
<P>
The six states issued a statement saying, ``We strongly condemn
and are very sorry for this attack that one Arab state took against
another Arab state. ... We do not recognize anything resulting from
it.''
Iraq's huge armed force is clearly too much for the joint
3,000-man Gulf Cooperation Council force, based at Hafr al-Baten in
northeastern Saudi Arabia 65 miles south of Kuwait. But there was
no talk of specific action against Iraq by Kuwait's partners.
</P>
<P>
Saudi Arabia was also one of the 14 members of the 21-member
Arab League that condemned the invasion in the same terms as the
Gulf Cooperation Council.
</P>
<P>
The Arab League, with one-third of its members voting against
the resolution or abstaining, was clearly unable to take any direct
action.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900804-0067
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>04
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Saudis Take No Steps Against Iraq
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Saudi Arabia has been subdued in its
reaction to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, which places Iraqi forces
near the oil-rich kingdom's border.
</P>
<P>
Oil executives said Saudi Arabia has not and will not take the
most potent action possible against Iraq _ closing the pipeline
that carries Iraqi oil for export across Saudi Arabia to the Red
Sea.
</P>
<P>
The executives said the Saudis believe this would give Iraq's
belligerent president, Saddam Hussein, an excuse to attack and
occupy Saudi oil fields 150 miles south of Kuwait, giving Iraq
control of more oil than any other country in the world.
</P>
<P>
The only direct Saudi statement since the invasion was made by
an anonymous government spokesman through the official Saudi Press
Agency the day after the Iraqi move.
</P>
<P>
The statement said Saudi Arabia was following the Kuwait
situation ``with extreme concern'' and that King Fahd would be
seeking to calm the situation and to find a solution ``in a manner
ensuring the interests of all.'' The statement did not condemn the
invasion.
</P>
<P>
The only tangible help Saudi Arabia gave the Kuwaiti government
in the wake of the invasion was to shelter members of the ruling
family, including the emir, Sheik Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah, and the
crown prince. Both nations are tightly run by royal families and
have been close allies.
</P>
<P>
The Saudis also allowed the Kuwaiti royal family to briefly
operate a radio, reportedly from a mobile van, in the area around
the Saudi-Kuwait border.
</P>
<P>
But Friday the radio went off the air after a desperate call:
``The people of Kuwait appeal to you oh brethren, oh Arabs, oh
beloved brothers, oh Moslems, rush, rush to their help.''
It was not known if the radio had been discovered by the Iraqis
or shut down by the Saudis to avoid provoking Saddam at a time when
fears were being expressed that he might invade Saudi Arabia as
well.
</P>
<P>
Saudi Arabia borders Kuwait and Iraq's invasion forces were
reportedly near the Saudi border.
</P>
<P>
The Saudis did condemned the invasion as part of a joint
statement issued by the Gulf Cooperation Council, in which it is
allied with Kuwait, the United Arab Emirates, Qatar, Oman and
Bahrain.
</P>
<P>
The six states issued a statement saying, ``We strongly condemn
and are very sorry for this attack that one Arab state took against
another Arab state. ... We do not recognize anything resulting from
it.''
Iraq's 1-million-member armed forces is clearly too much for the
joint 3,000-member Gulf Cooperation Council force or Saudi Arabia's
65,700-member army.
</P>
<P>
Saudi Arabia was also one of the 14 members of the 21-member
Arab League that condemned the invasion in the same terms as the
Gulf Cooperation Council.
</P>
<P>
The Arab League, with one-third of its members voting against
the resolution or abstaining, was clearly unable to take any direct
action.
</P>
<P>
Turkey has also refused to take action and has not commented
about President Bush's suggestion that it cut off Iraq's oil
pipeline to the Mediterranean. Two parallel pipelines pump Iraqi
crude oil to a terminal at Yumurtalik at the eastern corner of
Turkey's Mediterranean coast and constitute Iraq's major oil export
outlet.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900805-0060
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>05
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
United State Pushes for Iraqi Sanctions at United Nations
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
UNITED NATIONS _ The United States urged other U.N. members at
talks Sunday to impose broad economic and military sanctions on
Iraq. Western diplomats said the world body is expected to adopt
the measures.
</P>
<P>
Should the U.N. Security Council impose comprehensive sanctions,
it would be the first time since 1967 it has taken such action
against a member state. The last time such sanctions were imposed
was against the white minority government of Rhodesia.
</P>
<P>
Western diplomats said they expected up to 14 positive votes on
the 15-member council for sanctions against Iraq. They said they
expected no vetoes, allowing the legally binding measure to be
adopted, probably on Monday. They said Cuba was the holdout.
</P>
<P>
U.S. Ambassador Thomas R. Pickering told reporters after
closed-door talks Sunday that the council discussed ``the absolute
necessity of moving ahead toward a broad resolution of sanctions.''
He said he expected a vote Monday.
</P>
<P>
Pickering said the United States had circulated six or seven
drafts of a detailed resolution. It calls for an embargo on Iraq's
oil exports, an embargo on imports to Iraq, and a halt to all arms
and other military supplies for Iraq.
</P>
<P>
British Ambassador Crispen Tickell told reporters later that he
detected ``strong support, with the exception of one member, for
action and a vote tomorrow.''
Speaking of Iraqi President Saddam Hussein, Canadian Ambassador
L. Yves Fortier declared, ``This madman must be stopped.''
Cuban envoy Ricardo Alarcon said Cuba would vote for sanctions
against Iraq only if the council imposed sanctions on South Africa
for occupying Namibia, Israel for occupying Palestinian territories
and the United States for invading Panama.
</P>
<P>
In Kuwait, the Iraqi-installed provisional government, in a
statement carried by the Iraqi News Agency, told other countries to
refrain from taking ``punishing measures'' against it or Iraq. The
provisional government said countries ``have to remember they have
interests and citizens in Kuwait.''
Kuwait's U.N. Ambassador Mohammad Abulhasan told reporters that
the Iraqi-installed government was employing ``pure blackmail'' by
saying it could not ensure the safety of foreigners if their
governments support sanctions.
</P>
<P>
In Aspen, Colo., British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher
renewed her call for the United Nations to apply a total economic
embargo against Iraq unless it withdraws immediately from Kuwait.
``Iraq's invasion of Kuwait defies every principle for which the
U.N. stands. If we let it succeed, no small country can ever feel
safe again. The law of the jungle takes over,'' she said, in
remarks at the Aspen Institute.
</P>
<P>
The U.N. role in the Iraq-Kuwait crisis assumed increasing
importance after divided Arab nations cancelled an emergency summit
on the invasion.
</P>
<P>
On Thursday, the Security Council condemned Iraq's invasion,
demanded immediate and unconditional troop withdrawal, and
threatened to impose sanctions if Iraq did not pull out.
</P>
<P>
Sunday's session was scheduled after weekend meetings of the
council's five permanent members _ the United States, the Soviet
Union, China, Britain and France _ and between the United States
and representatives of the Non-Aligned Movement. They are the
nations with the power to veto proposals.
</P>
<P>
The United States contends that stiff sanctions by a united
international front are necessary to punish Iraq and to force it to
withdraw from Kuwait, which was invaded Thursday.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900806-0077
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>06
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Iraq Prepares for Attack; Turkish Oil Pipeline Closed
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
LaserPhoto AMS2, BON1-2
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Ruling party members said today that the
government, fearing a U.S. air attack, was distributing automatic
weapons to tens of thousands of supporters and preparing to
evacuate the Iraqi capital.
</P>
<P>
A boycott of Iraqi oil forced Baghdad today to close one of two
pipelines in Turkey that were pumping the bulk of Iraq's exported
oil, Turkish officials said.
</P>
<P>
A British official said Iraqi troops rounded up American and
British visitors in Kuwait and taking them to Iraq. The Foreign
Office spokesman said most were passengers from a British Airways
flight stranded in Kuwait since the Iraqi invasion Thursday.
``There is no evidence that they are in any way in trouble,'' the
official said.
</P>
<P>
Saudi Arabia was reported reinforcing its troops along the
Kuwaiti border following concerns Iraq may try to invade it.
</P>
<P>
Pentagon sources said the USS Independence and its carrier
battle group are now on station in the Arabian Sea, a position that
would allow it to launch fighter planes into the Persian Gulf
region.
</P>
<P>
Gulf-based diplomats said soldiers from the American rapid
deployment force, formed to react to crises in the Middle East, had
been dispatched to the area.
</P>
<P>
In other developments:
_The new Kuwait government installed by Iraq hinted it might
take hostages or seize property of nations that take punitive
measures against Iraq.
_Iraqi President Saddam Hussein said the 100,000 soldiers who
invaded Kuwait began to pull back Sunday. President Bush said Iraq
was lying.
_Oil prices jumped more than $3 a barrel on news Europe and
Japan were joining the embargo of Iraqi oil. Stocks slumped
worldwide.
_Hospital officials said at least 300 Kuwaiti and Iraqi soldiers
were killed during the invasion. In London, Kuwaitis arriving on a
special plane said 700 Kuwaitis died.
</P>
<P>
The embargo of Iraqi oil grew over the weekend to include Japan
and the European Community. Along with the United States, they
bought more than half Iraq's exported oil, with most of it pumped
through Turkey.
</P>
<P>
An official of the state-run Turkish pipeline company BOTAS said
pumping stopped at one of the two Turkish pipelines at 5 p.m. Iraq
reduced flow in the second, wider, pipeline to 70 percent of
capacity, they said.
</P>
<P>
There was no comment from Iraq.
</P>
<P>
The two pipelines pump Iraqi crude from Kirkuk oil fields in
northern Iraq to a terminal at the northeastern tip of the
Mediterranean. They carry 70 million tons of crude annually,
providing the outlet for the major share of Iraqi exports.
</P>
<P>
The BOTAS official said all the countries participating in the
embargo purchase their Iraqi crude from the Turkish outlet.
</P>
<P>
Iraq also exports oil through a Saudi Arabian pipeline and via
tankers in the northern Persian Gulf.
</P>
<P>
A Foreign Office spokesman said today as saying a total of 366
people had been assembled by Iraqi troops in Kuwait, mostly
passengers from a stranded British Airways flight. They were being
transported by bus to the Iraqi border.
</P>
<P>
Baghdad did not give any reason for its action.
</P>
<P>
Immediately after the invasion Thursday, 11 Americans were
rounded up by Iraqi troops. They turned up safe in Baghdad.
</P>
<P>
The new Iraqi-installed foreign minister of Kuwait, Lt. Col.
</P>
<P>
Walid Sa'oud Mohammed Abdullah, warned against further sanctions in
a statement broadcast Sunday by Iraqi radio.
``Countries that resort to punitive measures against the
provisional free Kuwait government and fraternal Iraq should
remember that they have interests and nationals in Kuwait,'' he
said.
</P>
<P>
Iraqi soldiers invaded Kuwait after complaining that its
violation of OPEC production quotas was driving down world crude
prices, lowering Iraqi oil revenues. Saddam also accused Kuwait of
stealing oil from a field that includes land both sides claim.
</P>
<P>
The respected Middle East Economic Survey reported today that
Kuwait's oil export facilities had been shut down.
</P>
<P>
It also said there was considerable doubt Saudi Arabia, with the
world's largest oil reserves, would be willing to make up the
potential world oil shortage. Kuwait and Iraq together account for
one-fifth of the 23.5 million barrels produced daily by the 13 OPEC
nations.
</P>
<P>
Tensions remained high in the region; a U.S. official said in
Washington that Iraqi troops massed on the Kuwaiti-Saudi border
were apparently digging in. An American technician at a secret
Saudi Arabian base said the kingdom had sent 200 to 300 tanks
toward its border with Kuwait.
</P>
<P>
Oil industry sources in Saudi Arabia reached by telephone from
Bahrain said Saudi troops were entering the region of Khafji, near
the border. Residents reached by telephone reported intense air
activity near the Saudi airport overnight.
</P>
<P>
The Washington Post reported today that Egypt was mobilizing
some elements of its armed forces to assist Saudi Arabia in the
event of an invasion.
</P>
<P>
U.S. officials said there was no indication Iraqi troops were
preparing to invade Saudi Arabia. But Bush sent Defense Secretary
Dick Cheney to the kingdom to confer with its leaders, and the
White House said Secretary of State James A. Baker would go this
week to Turkey.
</P>
<P>
Saadi Mehdi Saleh, the Iraqi army commander, was quoted by the
Al-Iraq newspaper as saying tens of thousands of volunteers had
joined the army to defend what he called ``Iraq and the revolution
in Kuwait.''
Americans, he was quoted as saying, ``should understand that the
people of the great leader Saddam Hussein cannot be frightened.''
Local members of the ruling Baath party said preparations were
under way to evacuate all of Baghdad's 4 million people to camps
outside the city. They were being told that the U.S. Air Force
might attack or that Israel might attack with chemical or nuclear
weapons.
</P>
<P>
The party members also said the party had distributed guns,
mainly AK-47 automatic rifles, to tens of thousands of people
around the country.
</P>
<P>
State radio said Saddam had ordered the formation of 11 new
Iraqi army divisions, expected to generate 100,000 troops. The Arab
world's most formidible military force is already estimated at 1
million men.
</P>
<P>
At a border checkpoint 30 miles south of the Iraqi port city of
Basra, dozens of tanks, armored personnel carriers and trucks
carrying hundreds of soldiers crossed back into Iraq on Sunday.
</P>
<P>
But thousands of Iraqi soldiers remained behind in Kuwait,
controlling major government buildings, commerical centers and
ports.
</P>
<P>
Diplomats in the region said a new Kuwaiti army fanned out
through Kuwait. The force comprises about 80,000 troops, mostly
Iraqis.
</P>
<P>
The nine-member Kuwaiti military government, announced by Iraq
on Saturday, remained a mystery. No photographs of the named
leaders have been shown and 12 reporters brought to Kuwait by the
Ministry of Information could not locate any of them.
</P>
<P>
Kuwaiti diplomats said they were all Iraqis, including a
son-in-law of Saddam, a charge official Iraqi media denied.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900806-0095
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>06
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
U.N. Security Council Approves Sanctions Against Iraq
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The U.N. Security Council today
overwhelmingly approved sweeping trade and military sanctions
against Iraq, including a ban on oil purchases, to punish Baghdad
for invading Kuwait.
</P>
<P>
The vote was 13-0, with two abstentions by Cuba and Yemen on the
15-member council, which adopted the sanctions resolution proposed
by the United States. It said Iraq had launched an armed attack
against Kuwait and usurped the authority of Kuwait's legitimate
government.
</P>
<P>
The sanctions were intended to force Iraq to withdraw its troops
from Kuwait and the resolution bans ``the import into their
territories of all commodities and products originating in Iraq or
Kuwait and exported there from after the date of this resolution.''
President Bush praised the decision and called for ``full and
total implementation of these sanctions, ruling out nothing at
all.''
He told reporters at the White House: ``The will of nations
around the world will be to enforce these sanctions.''
It was the third time in its 45-year existence that the world
body had voted sanctions against a member state. The last time was
1967 when the Security Council voted similar, comprehensive
sanctions against the white minority government of Rhodesia.
</P>
<P>
An arms embargo against South Africa still is in effect.
</P>
<P>
The sanctions are legally binding for all member nations,
although past council resolutions have often been ignored or
flouted. The United Nations has no enforcement mechanism but later
could call on members to take military action against Iraq or
impose a blockade.
</P>
<P>
The vote followed similar sanctions imposed on Iraq by much of
the West, including the United States, Japan and the European
Community. The Soviet Union and China said they would halt arms
shipments to Iraq.
</P>
<P>
In a statement carried by the Iraqi News Agency on Sunday, the
Iraqi-installed military government of Kuwait warned other nations
not to take ``punishing measures'' against it or Iraq. The
provisional government said countries ``have to remember they have
interests and citizens in Kuwait.''
The U.N. role in the Iraq-Kuwait crisis assumed increasing
importance after divided Arab nations canceled a weekend emergency
summit on the invasion.
</P>
<P>
In an emergency session just hours after Thursday's invasion,
the Security Council condemned Iraq's invasion, demanded immediate
and unconditional troop withdrawal, and called for negotiations
between Iraq and Kuwait.
</P>
<P>
The council threatened to impose sanctions if Iraq did not
comply.
</P>
<P>
The council includes the five permanent members with veto power
_ the United States, Britain, China, France and the Soviet Union.
</P>
<P>
The 10 non-permanent members are: Canada, Colombia, Cuba, Ethiopia,
Finland, Ivory Coast, Malaysia, Romania, Yemen and Zaire.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA080290-0233
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>2
</DAY> 
<MONTH>8
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
IRAQ TRAMPLES KUWAIT; 
TROOPS SEIZE CAPITAL, PALACE; EMIR FLEES; 
200 KUWAITIS SAID KILLED OR INJURED; U.S. AID SOUGHT 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
KUWAIT 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iraq's powerful army claimed victory today in its lightning invasion of this 
small, oil-rich kingdom. Tank-led troops quickly seized the ruler's palace and 
government buildings, and the emir fled to Saudi Arabia, Kuwaiti officials 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's U.S. ambassador said the Iraqis occupied all government buildings in 
the capital and were moving south toward the country's oil facilities. He 
appealed for U.S. military intervention. 
</P>
<P>
"The Iraqis have occupied all of Kuwait!" a Kuwaiti government official shouted 
in a telephone interview. Diplomatic sources in the Persian Gulf estimated that 
more than 200 Kuwaitis were killed or wounded. 
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi government of President Saddam Hussein claimed that it invaded at the 
request of revolutionaries who had already staged a coup and established "the 
provisional government of free Kuwait." Kuwait and U.N. diplomats labeled the 
coup report a farce. 
</P>
<P>
Baghdad television said Iraq could withdraw its forces within days or weeks, 
depending on how quickly the situation stabilized. 
</P>
<P>
The assault followed two weeks of tension between Kuwait and Iraq, caused by 
Iraqi accusations that Kuwait stole oil from a disputed border area. Saddam 
also accused Kuwait of exceeding OPEC production quotas, thus driving down the 
price of oil, a major Iraqi revenue source. 
</P>
<P>
In recent days, diplomats said Iraq had massed more than 100,000 troops at the 
border. Kuwait's entire armed forces has 20,300 soldiers. 
</P>
<P>
It was the first time in modern history that an Arab nation had invaded another 
and taken over its government. 
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's army was no match for Iraq, battle-hardened after eight years of war 
with Iran. 
</P>
<P>
Diplomats said about 350 Iraqi tanks wheeled into the capital a few hours after 
crossing the border 40 miles away at dawn. Witnesses said the bombardment of 
ports and military airports by artillery and the air force was vicious. 
</P>
<P>
The invaders surrounded the palace of Kuwait's ruler, Sheik Jabbar al Ahmed al 
Sabah. Residents said the palace was seized after about two hours of heavy 
artillery barrages. 
</P>
<P>
Diplomats said Sheik Fahd al Ahmed al Sabah, one of the emir's brothers, was 
killed while trying to defend the palace. 
</P>
<P>
There were about 50 tanks around the palace and the neighboring American 
Embassy, residents said. 
</P>
<P>
The al Sabah family has ruled the city-state for almost 250 years. The Kuwaiti 
ambassador said the leaders were safe in Saudi Arabia. 
</P>
<P>
Operating from an unknown location, al Ahmed's government responded to the 
formation of the provisional government by stating: "Kuwait is Kuwait to its 
people, led by the emir, Sheik Jabbar, and his Crown Prince Sheik Saad. God 
preserve them from all harm." 
</P>
<P>
For its part, the provisional government announced through Baghdad's official 
Iraqi News Agency that it was dissolving Parliament and would hold "free and 
honest elections" at a future date. 
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's land and sea borders were closed, as was the airport. 
</P>
<P>
RELATED STORIES, PICTURES: Pages 2,3, BACK PAGE 
</P>
<P>
Military Forces Compared: 
</P>
<P>
Total Troops: 
</P>
<P>
Iraq: 1,000,000 
</P>
<P>
Kuwait: 20,300 
</P>
<P>
Main Battle Tanks: 
</P>
<P>
Iraq: 5,500 
</P>
<P>
Kuwait: 275 
</P>
<P>
Combat Aircraft: 
</P>
<P>
Iraq: 513 
</P>
<P>
Kuwait: 36 
</P>
<P>
Ships: 
</P>
<P>
Iraq: 51 
</P>
<P>
Kuwait: 46 
</P>
<P>
Source: International Institute for Strategic Studies 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA080690-0111
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>6
</DAY> 
<MONTH>8
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
IRAQIS SEIZE WESTERNERS; 
HUNDREDS ROUNDED UP DURING SWEEP OF KUWAIT HOTELS; 
U.N. COUNCIL VOTES BROAD SANCTIONS 
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iraq struck back against the West today, rounding up hundreds of foreign 
nationals in Kuwait, as the U.N. Security Council overwhelming approved 
sweeping trade and military sanctions against Iraq to punish it for invading 
the emirate. 
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi invaders scoured hotels looking for some of the thousands of 
Westerners based in Kuwait or caught by the invasion. More than 1 million 
foreigners live and work in Kuwait. 
</P>
<P>
Several hundred Britons, Americans and West Germans were grabbed in the hotels, 
and some were taken to Iraq, the West German and British foreign ministries 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Britain said Baghdad had given no reason for detaining 366 people, most of them 
passengers from a British Airways flight stranded at Kuwait airport by the 
invasion. 
</P>
<P>
The U.N. sanctions, which included a ban on oil purchases, came on a vote of 13 
to 0, on the 15-member council. Cuba and Yemen abstained on the resolution, 
which was proposed by the United States. 
</P>
<P>
The Iraqi-installed Kuwait government had earlier warned foreign countries that 
they should not forget their citizens in Kuwait while heaping on economic 
punishments, and today's roundup appeared to be a reaction against the 
sanctions. 
</P>
<P>
Iraqi troops rolled into its New Jersey-sized neighbor Thursday, conquering the 
capital and moving south toward the Saudi Arabian border. 
</P>
<P>
Persian Gulf oil sources said today that they had seen Saudi troops moving 
north toward the Kuwaiti frontier near the oil port of Khafji, but the Saudis 
denied that they had sent reinforcements to the border. 
</P>
<P>
Iraqi authorities today told Turkey's state-run pipeline company that one of 
the twin pipelines that carry Baghdad's oil through Turkey will be closed "for 
reasons of marketing," officials said. 
</P>
<P>
World oil prices soared to their highest level in more than four years today as 
more countries joined the attempt to strangle Baghdad's economy and force it to 
withdraw its invasion troops. 
</P>
<P>
Iraq's oil revenues totaled more than $11 billion last year. It has been 
pressing for higher oil prices to rebuild an economy damaged by the 1980-88 war 
with Iran and settle foreign debts of up to $80 billion. 
</P>
<P>
One of the reasons Iraq gave for invading Kuwait was Kuwaiti reluctance to slow 
its flow of oil and push oil prices higher, but it was Iraqi oil that had 
slowed today. 
</P>
<P>
"There are very few tankers loading Iraqi oil at Yumurtalik," a senior Turkish 
government official said, referring to the export jetties on the Turkish side 
of the Mediterranean Sea. 
</P>
<P>
In Baghdad, President Saddam Hussein ordered drills for millions of people in 
case mass evacuations were needed. 
</P>
<P>
He warned his nation's 17 million people to be on alert for possible U.S. or 
Israeli attacks. The United States has warned Iraq against any attack on Saudi 
Arabia, and President Bush has said all options are open for the United States. 
</P>
<P>
Hundreds of Kuwaitis took to the desert to flee into Saudi Arabia, their 
children and a few belongings crammed into four-wheel-drive vehicles. 
</P>
<P>
RELATED STORIES: Pages 2,3 
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>WSJ900803-0023
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> WSJ 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>03
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
   The Iraqi Invasion of Kuwait:
   CIA Had Given Warning
   Of Iraq's Move on Kuwait
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>03
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>90
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<TEXT>
<P>
WASHINGTON - U.S. intelligence officials had been
sounding alarms in recent days about a possible Iraqi
invasion of Kuwait.
</P>
<P>
Emphasizing that the Central Intelligence Agency wasn't
surprised by the Iraqi action, an agency spokesman said
yesterday, "We provided policy makers with very useful and
timely information on these events and we continue to do so."
Administration and congressional officials agree that the
CIA did its job. Since last week, President Bush had been
warned by intelligence analysts that what originally looked
like a military bluff was quickly turning into the kind of
troop deployment that could be used to invade Kuwait or even
Saudi Arabia.
</P>
<P>
Central Intelligence Agency Director William Webster even
hand-delivered certain fresh details on the Iraqi buildup to
National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft. Among the
assessments he conveyed was a conclusion that, by this week,
President Saddam Hussein's force would be capable of
penetrating Kuwait or Saudi Arabia.
</P>
<P>
The agency lacked hard evidence of an intent to invade,
intelligence officials say. But as the buildup grew, the CIA
became more alarmed, partly because Mr. Hussein is so
unpredictable, and partly because, unlike many other Arab
leaders, he has been known to carry out his threats.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
