<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880821-0008
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>21
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
100 Feared Dead In Earthquake That Hits Nepal And Eastern India
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A strong earthquake hit the Himalayan
kingdom of Nepal and parts of eastern India on Sunday morning,
triggering landslides and collapsing buildings. First reports said
100 people may have died.
</P>
<P>
Nepal's Department of Geology said the earthquake struck at 4:54
a.m. (7:09 p.m. EDT Saturday) and measured 5.7 on the Richter scale.
</P>
<P>
The department said the quake was centered near Udayapur, a town
near the Indian-Nepalese border and 100 miles southeast of
Katmandu, Nepal's capital. Officials said the temblor lasted about
40 seconds.
</P>
<P>
In New Delhi, the Seismologoical Observatory said the quake
measured 6.5 on the Richter scale.
</P>
<P>
The state-run Radio Nepal said at least 27 people were killed in
the towns of Bhaktapur and Dharan when they were buried by
collapsing houses.
</P>
<P>
Press Trust of India news agency said that in addition to 100
feared dead in India and Nepal, 1,000 people were injured in the
Indian states of Bihar, Sikkim and West Bengal.
</P>
<P>
A Nepalese journalist in Dharan, 130 miles southeast of
Katmandu, said by telephone that ``20 people have already died. A
large number of injured were being taken to local hospitals and a
rescue operation is under way. Men of the Royal Nepal Army, police,
social workers and other local inhabitants are taking part in the
rescue operation.''
The journalist added that ``90 percent of the house of Vijapur
area of Dharan collapsed.''
Police reported seven people died in Bhaktapur, an ancient town
seven miles east of Katmandu, while 20 others suffered injuries.
</P>
<P>
The quake was also felt in the Indian capital of New Delhi and
Calcutta, but there was no report of any casualties.
</P>
<P>
One hard-hit Indian city was Dharbhanga in Bihar state, where 14
children were believed killed when their school hostel collapsed.
</P>
<P>
Dharbhanga, with a population of 200,000, is 550 miles east of
New Delhi.
</P>
<P>
Several homes in the residential areas of Dharbhanga have
collapsed, killing an unspecified number of people.
</P>
<P>
The Richter scale is a gauge of energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by ground motion recorded on a seismograph.
</P>
<P>
Every increase of one number means the ground motion is 10 times
greater.
</P>
<P>
A quake of magnitude 5 can cause considerable damage in
populated areas while one measuring 6 can cause severe damage.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880821-0010
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>21
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Quake Along India-Nepal Border Reportedly Leaves More Than 200
Dead
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A strong earthquake triggered landslides
and destroyed houses in the mountainous India-Nepal border region
early Sunday, killing at least 237 people and injuring more than
1,500, officials and news reports said.
</P>
<P>
Seismologists said it was the deadliest earthquake to strike the
Himalayan region since 1950.
</P>
<P>
More than 100 people died when the quake rumbled through the
eastern Indian state of Bihar, officials said. In Nepal,
authorities said at least 137 people were dead. Officials in both
countries predicted the death toll would rise after they received
reports from remote areas which were hit harder.
``The tolls have come in only from urban areas,'' said V.K.
</P>
<P>
Sharma, deputy secretary in the Bihar government.
</P>
<P>
The temblor also jolted parts of northern Bangladesh and the
capital of Dhaka, but there were no immediate reports of casualties
or damage.
</P>
<P>
Witnesses said windows and doors rattled, buildings cracked and
people roused from their sleep ran screaming from their homes as
objects tumbled from shelves and tables.
``My bed rattled, then it began swinging,'' said R.N. Rudra, a
resident of Patna, the Bihar capital. ``My dogs began barking and I
rushed out of the house.''
At least 1,000 people were injured when the quake triggered
landslides and house collapses in Bihar and the surrounding states
of Uttar Pradesh, West Bengal and Orissa, all heavily populated,
largely agricultural areas.
</P>
<P>
The quake also was felt in Sikkim and Tripura, located in the
Himalayan foothills, the Press Trust of India news agency said.
</P>
<P>
In Nepal, a Foreign Ministry official, Shailendra Kumar
Upadhyaya, said more than 500 people were injured and thousands of
houses collapsed from the quake's impact.
``Most of them (were) buried alive under collapsed houses,''
said Indra Shrestha, a social worker involved in the rescue
operation in Dharan Bazar, a township of about 100,000 people about
18 miles from the Indian border.
</P>
<P>
Shrestha said rescue operations were being hampered by the
monsoon rains, which hit the subcontinent in late June and usually
last through September.
</P>
<P>
Both countries were rushing emergency medical teams to the area.
</P>
<P>
The Red Cross of Nepal issued urgent appeals for blood donations.
</P>
<P>
In India's Bihar state, communications with Darbhanga, which
appeared to be the worst-hit area, were disrupted. The Press Trust
of India said a school hostel in the town collapsed, killing at
least 17 children. It said more bodies were feared buried under the
debris.
</P>
<P>
The quake damaged most of the houses in Darbhanga, the news
agency said, quoting P.K. Patnaik, the top civil administrator in
the district. Deaths were also reported in the neighboring towns of
Munger, Keoti and Narpatnagar.
</P>
<P>
The tremor also was felt in the eastern city of Calcutta, Press
Trust of India said. There were no immediate reports of casualties
but residents were quoted as saying windows of several homes
vibrated and doors rattled.
</P>
<P>
The Seismological Observatory in New Delhi said the quake hit at
4:40 a.m. (7:10 p.m. EDT Saturday) and was centered 40 to 50 miles
northeast of the town of Darbhanga in Bihar state, along the
India-Nepal border. Observatory Director H.N. Srivastava said the
quake measured 6.5 on the Richter scale.
</P>
<P>
Srivastava said the quake lasted about one minute and
aftershocks continued for about an hour. Seismologists warned
aftershocks could continue for days.
</P>
<P>
The U.S. Geological Survey said its initial seismograph readings
placed the center of the quake 100 miles southeast of Katmandu, the
capital of Nepal. Geological Survey monitors in Golden, Colo.,
recorded the earthquake at a preliminary magnitude of 6.7 on the
Richter scale.
</P>
<P>
The Richter scale gauges the energy released by an earthquake as
measured by the ground motion recorded on a seismograph. A quake of
magnitude 6 is capable of causing severe damage.
</P>
<P>
Earthquakes are common in the Himalayan region. On Aug. 6 a
quake of magnitude 7.3 shook the states of Assam, Manipur, West
Bengal and Bihar. Four people were killed. India's worst earthquake
was in 1950, when at least 30,000 people were killed in Assam state.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880822-0075
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>22
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Precede NEW DELHI
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
One-Third Of Nepal Devastated By Quake
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Rescuers searched through debris today
for victims of an earthquake that ravaged one-third of this
country's territory and parts of India, killing at least 650 people
and injuring thousands.
</P>
<P>
The death toll was expected to climb from Sunday's pre-dawn
quake on the India-Nepal border, which triggered landslides and
floods and was the mountainous region's deadliest in 38 years.
</P>
<P>
Officials in both countries said they had yet to receive reports
from the remote Himalayan areas hardest hit by the temblor, which
knocked out power and communications and was said to injure at
least 3,000 people.
</P>
<P>
Niranjan Thapa, Nepal's minister of state for home affairs, told
a news conference at least 450 were dead and up to 1,000 injured.
</P>
<P>
He said officials expected the numbers to climb.
</P>
<P>
Indian officials reported at least 200 people dead and more than
2,000 injured, most by debris from collapsing buildings.
</P>
<P>
The quake, centered almost on the India-Nepal border, registered
6.5 on the Richter scale.
</P>
<P>
Indian television today showed the devastation in the Indian
state of Bihar: crumbled buildings, makeshift morgues lined with
rows of bodies wrapped in white shrouds, damaged hospital wards
packed with survivors.
</P>
<P>
Medical teams in India carried medicine and other supplies to
overcrowded hospitals and the army was deployed to help search for
victims.
</P>
<P>
But the monsoons, which hit the subcontinent in late June and
usually last through September, hampered relief operations.
</P>
<P>
Nepal's Thapa told a news conference that ``the rains have been
a great hindrance in carrying out rescue works. Access to some
areas of this mountain country is impossible.''
He said 21 of the kingdom's 75 districts suffered extensive
damage. The hardest hit appeared to be Dharan, a sparsely populated
border region where Thapa said at least 131 people died.
</P>
<P>
Bir Bahadur Shahi, secretary of the home affairs ministry, flew
to eastern Nepal on Sunday. He said 50,000 to 60,000 houses were
destroyed in the Dharan district alone.
``Ninety percent of the remaining houses are cracked,'' Shahi
said, adding that most of the damage was to modern houses of stone
and older houses from mud and bricks. Wooden houses were not
affected, he said.
</P>
<P>
Many people were given shelter in schools, guesthouses and
public buildings, ``but most of the people do not want to leave
their homes,'' Shahi said. He said water supplies were still
adequate and there were no reports of disease breaking out.
</P>
<P>
Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi flew to Bihar to tour some of the
hardest hit areas. The government said it would release a detailed
report after he returned to the capital tonight.
</P>
<P>
Prime Minister Marich Man Singh Shrestha of Nepal visited some
of the victims at Bir Hospital in his capital, Katmandu.
</P>
<P>
The quake roused people from their sleep in Bihar and nine other
Indian states and central and eastern Nepal. It lasted about a
minute and aftershocks continued for about an hour.
</P>
<P>
Rail tracks sank into the soggy ground and bridges over rising
rivers cracked, paralyzing train service and road travel in many
parts of the devastated areas.
</P>
<P>
Parts of northern Bangladesh and the capital, Dhaka, also felt
the tremor. There were reports that 50 people were injured, most by
jumping from their houses during the quake.
</P>
<P>
Witnesses in Darbhanga, an Indian city of 800,000 about 45 miles
south of the epicenter, said the only warnings were hissing sounds,
rattling doors and cracking windows. Women began blowing conch
shells, following an ancient tradition believed to appease the
weather gods.
</P>
<P>
More than 25,000 houses were flattened in Darbhanga, as well as
the districts of Munger and Madhubani, Indian officials said.
</P>
<P>
In Madhubani, the Bhootahi Balan River jumped its banks and
flooded nearly 50 villages. Officials said at least 45 people died,
but it was not known whether the deaths were due to floods or
collapsing houses.
</P>
<P>
It was the worst quake to strike the region in 38 years. A
temblor rumbled through the Indian state of Assam on the
India-China border in August 1950. Official accounts said more than
1,500 people died, but seismologists said their records showed
30,000 were killed.
</P>
<P>
The Richter scale is a gauge of energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by ground motion recorded on a seismograph.
</P>
<P>
Every increase of one number means the ground motion is 10 times
greater. A quake of magnitude 6 can cause severe damage in
populated areas.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880823-0059
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Rescuers Cope With Rains, Aftershocks
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BIRATNAGAR, Nepal (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Rescue workers coped with aftershocks
and heavy rain today in an effort to reach remote regions of the
Himalayas to help victims of an earthquake whose official death
toll neared 700.
</P>
<P>
Rumors predicting another large quake sent thousands of
panic-stricken people fleeing from their homes in India and Nepal.
</P>
<P>
Sunday's pre-dawn quake registered 6.5 on the Richter scale and
claimed at least 497 lives in Nepal and 200 in India, government
officials said.
</P>
<P>
Officials in both countries said they expected the death toll to
climb when reports arrived from regions difficult to reach even in
good weather.
</P>
<P>
The quake injured at least 2,000 people in India and 1,000 in
Nepal, officials said.
</P>
<P>
In Biratnagar, a city near the Indian border 150 miles east of
the Nepalese capital Katmandu, residents poured into the streets
before dawn today as men ran from houses to house, shouting that a
message came from Katmandu that a new quake was expected before
dawn.
</P>
<P>
Police in the city of 300,000 people said they received no such
message.
``I have tried to tell them they are making a mistake, but no
one will listen to me,'' said Dabal Singh, an inspector.
</P>
<P>
Anonymous telephone calls with similar rumors roused hundreds of
people in Katmandu, also before dawn. Sunday's quake was felt in
the capital, but no deaths or serious damage were reported in the
city.
</P>
<P>
In Patna, India, thousands of people huddled in the rain in open
courtyards Monday as rumors swept the city that another quake was
imminent. Patna is the capital of Bihar state, the worst hit area
in India.
</P>
<P>
A quake registering 5.1 on the Richter scale shook eastern Nepal
late Monday afternoon, but there were no immediate reports of new
casualties or damage.
</P>
<P>
In general, however, the intensity of aftershocks has lessened.
``Compared to the ones on Sunday and Monday, they have been
declining,'' Madhav Prasad Pandy, senior seismologist at Nepal's
Department of Geology, said in Katmandu. He said most aftershocks
had declined to a reading of 1 on the Richter scale.
</P>
<P>
Rain continued in quake-affected areas, hampering access on
muddy roads already cracked by the quake. Landslides blocked many
roads to devastated areas. Railroad tracks sank into the mud, and
the quake also cracked bridges over rivers swollen by the monsoon.
</P>
<P>
In India, the area with the greatest damage and casualties was
just south of the border in Bihar, India's poorest state.
</P>
<P>
News reports said 400 people died in Bihar state, double the
Indian government's count. Bihar officials said the reports were
exaggerated, while opposition politicians in the state accused the
government of suppressing information and claimed the death toll
was close to 1,500.
</P>
<P>
Tremors flattened more than 25,000 houses in India, officials
said, and the Bhoothai Balan River flooded nearly 50 villages in
the Madhubani district.
</P>
<P>
Indian army soldiers helped with relief efforts, and the navy
and air force were put on alert. Nepalese soldiers, police and
volunteers joined forces in the kingdom's remote mountains and
valleys.
</P>
<P>
Niranjan Thapa of the Home Minstry reported extensive damage in
21 of Nepal's 75 districts and at least four affected districts
reported 50 or more deaths.
</P>
<P>
Officials distributed 88-pound bags of rice to families in this
kingdom of 17 million people.
</P>
<P>
Government officials said many offers of assistance had come
from abroad, but no decision had been made about whether to accept
them.
</P>
<P>
A U.S. Embassy official said the embassy had offered $25,000 in
immediate aid but had not received a response.
</P>
<P>
The quake was the worst in the region since a temblor in India's
eastern state of Assam killed 1,500 people in 1950, according to
official accounts. Seismologists said their records showed a death
toll of at least 30,000.
</P>
<P>
The Richter scale measures ground motion as recorded on
seismographs and each number represents aa tenflod increaase in
intensity. A quake of 6 on the scale is capable of causing severe
damage, while one measuring 5 can cause considerable damage.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880823-0127
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>23
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Unsafe Buildings Bulldozed as Recovery From Killer Quake Continues
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>DHARAN, Nepal (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Police bulldozed teetering houses Tuesday
to keep people from returning to homes left unsafe by an earthquake
that killed at least 731 people in India and Nepal.
</P>
<P>
Officials in both countries expected the death toll to rise as
relief workers reached remote towns that have been inaccessible
since Sunday's devastating quake.
</P>
<P>
Some roads were flooded by heavy rains that continued Tuesday,
while others had 3-foot-deep cracks or were blocked by boulders the
size of houses in the Himalayan mountains and valleys.
</P>
<P>
At least 531 people were killed in Nepal, said Tek Bahadur
Thapa, additional secretary in the Home Affairs Ministry.
</P>
<P>
Prime Minister Marich Man Singh Shrestha visited Dharan, one of
the hardest-hit towns, and surveyed heaps of bricks that were once
three-story and five-story houses.
``This is the biggest calamity to strike Nepal,'' Shrestha said
as he toured the town.
</P>
<P>
India reported an official death toll of 200, but the figure was
disputed by news media and opposition politicians who put the
Indian death count at anywhere from 400 to 1,500.
</P>
<P>
In Darbhanga, India on Tuesday, worshipers offered sweets, milk
and coconuts to appease the Hindu god of destruction. Women dressed
in colorful saris gathered at countryside temples in the
quake-ravaged areas of eastern Bihar state to pray and present
their offerings to Lord Shiva, the god of destruction in the Hindu
trinity.
``If God is pleased, nothing will happen,'' said one woman, who
refused to give her name.
</P>
<P>
The earthquake, which struck shortly before daybreak Sunday when
most people were still asleep, registered 6.5 on the Richter scale.
</P>
<P>
It was the deadliest quake in the region since 1950 when a temblor
in the east Indian state of Assam killed 1,500 by official count
and 30,000 by seismologists' accounts.
</P>
<P>
Dharan, 105 miles southeast of Katmandu, sits on a rolling plain
at the base of a steep hill. At least 131 bodies have been found in
the town of 100,000.
</P>
<P>
Most of the victims died in their houses, which were made of
bricks held together by mud that had loosened during the seasonal
monsoon rains.
</P>
<P>
Police Inspector G. Adhikari said bulldozers have demolished
more than 50 houses deemed too dangerous for habitation. ``We will
continue to demolish houses until we are satisfied (the ones
remaining) are safe to live in,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
British soldiers from a nearby Gurkha recruiting center pitched
in with cranes to aid the demolition. Dharan is in the heart of
regional famed for fierce Gurkha fighters who have served in the
British army for more than 150 years.
</P>
<P>
Adhikari said local officials had not yet heard from the
government on compensation or new housing for people whose homes
were demolished. Most of the homeless have moved in with neighbors
of found shelter in tents erected on the soggy earth.
</P>
<P>
The hardest hit areas in India were in Bihar state just across
the Nepalese border.
</P>
<P>
Rescuers in army helicopters searched for survivors in Bihar's
Darbhanga, Madhubani and Mungar districts. Other helicopters
ferried medicine, rice, cooking oil, clothes and tents to police
trapped in the most remote regions of Bihar, India's poorest state.
</P>
<P>
Heavy rains, overflowing rivers and submerged bridges and roads
hampered attempts by 1,000 Indian soldiers to provide assistance.
</P>
<P>
In Nepal, 88-pound bags of rice were being distributed to
families affected by the quake, but officials were unable to give
any figures.
</P>
<P>
International agencies operating in Nepal were gearing up to
contribute supplies or assistance but have not yet heard from the
government on what was wanted, according to several foreign relief
workers who spoke on condition of anonymity.
</P>
<P>
Shrestha said the mountain kingdom had not sought foreign aid
because ``we are still assessing the magnitude of the tragedy.''
Some supplies, medicine and health workers arrived in eastern Nepal
on Tuesday. Donors included UNICEF and the government of Japan and
Britain.
</P>
<P>
Nepal is one of the world's poorest countries. Two-third of the
children under age of 5 suffer from malnutrition and life
expectancy is 52, according to UNICEF. A nation of 17 million,
Nepal has one doctor for every 22,650 people, compared with 5,000
people per doctor in India and 780 per doctor in the United States.
</P>
<P>
Aftershocks have persisted since Sunday's earthquake, and rumors
of an impending new quake sent thousands of people fleeing into the
streets in panic before dawn Tuesday in Katmandu and Dharan. The
rumors started with anonymous telephone calls and spread by word of
mouth. In Dharan, men ran from houses to houses rousing people from
their sleep.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880824-0050
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>24
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Death Toll at 749 In Quake
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>DHARAN, Nepal (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Police bulldozed unstable brick and mud
houses today while those left homeless by an earthquake that killed
at least 749 people sought shelter and awaited government aid.
</P>
<P>
Casualty reports continued to trickle in from remote parts of
this Himalayan mountain kingdom as relief workers fanned out
through the foothills and valleys. Sunday's pre-dawn quake struck
near the India-Nepal border.
</P>
<P>
Some roads were flooded by heavy rains that followed the quake.
</P>
<P>
Others had cracks three feet deep or were blocked by boulders the
size of houses.
</P>
<P>
At least 549 people were killed in Nepal, said Tek Bahadur Thapa
of the Home Affairs Ministry. Dharan was hardest hit. At least 131
bodies were found in the city of 100,000.
</P>
<P>
Indian officials have maintained since Monday that the death
toll in their country was 200 or less, but the figure was
questioned by opposition politicians, survivors and the local
media, including the Times of India, a newspaper that generally
supports the government.
</P>
<P>
They put the India death count at anywhere from 400 to 1,500.
</P>
<P>
Indian officials said 200 people were injured in the quake.
</P>
<P>
Nepalese officials listed 752 injured, down from their earlier
estimate of 1,000.
</P>
<P>
In Bhaktapur, a city of 50,000 where seven people died in the
quake, 63-year-old Nhuchhe Raj Sakya said his five-story brick and
mud house had nearly fallen down but that he and his family of 10
were still living in it.
``What else can we do?'' the goldsmith said. ``We have no tent.
</P>
<P>
How can I leave my place?''
Prime Minister Marich Man Singh Shrestha visited Dharan on
Tuesday and surveyed heaps of bricks that were once three-story and
five-story houses.
``This is the biggest calamity to strike Nepal,'' Shrestha said
as he toured the town.
</P>
<P>
Dharan, 105 miles southeast of Katmandu, sits on a rolling plain
at the base of a steep hill. Most of the victims died in their
houses, which were made of bricks held together by mud that had
loosened during the seasonal monsoon rains.
</P>
<P>
Police Inspector G. Adhikari said bulldozers have demolished
more than 50 houses deemed too dangerous for habitation.
``We will continue to demolish houses until we are satisfied
(the ones remaining) are safe to live in,'' he said.
</P>
<P>
Adhikari said local officials had not yet heard from the
government on compensation or new housing for people whose homes
were demolished. Most of the homeless have moved in with neighbors
or found shelter in tents erected on the soggy earth.
</P>
<P>
The earthquake, which struck when most people were still asleep,
registered 6.5 on the Richter scale and was the deadliest quake in
the region since 1950, when a temblor in the east Indian state of
Assam killed 1,500 by official count and 30,000 by seismologists'
accounts.
</P>
<P>
Aftershocks have persisted since Sunday's quake, and rumors of
an impending new quake sent thousands of people fleeing into the
streets in panic before dawn Tuesday in Katmandu and Dharan.
</P>
<P>
The rumors started with anonymous telephone calls and spread by
word of mouth. In Dharan, men ran from houses to houses rousing
people from their sleep.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880824-0139
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>24
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Earthquake Death Toll Rises As Rescue Teams Reach Remote Areas
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The death toll from the Himalayan
earthquake topped 750 on Wednesday as rescue workers hampered by
monsoon rains, aftershocks and washed out roads reached remote
areas of Nepal and found more bodies.
</P>
<P>
In eastern India, which also was devastated by the quake, cracks
were found in the embankments of six rivers in Bihar state, and
officials said floods could pose the next threat to the 10 million
people.
``It may be the second coming. All the rivers are in full spate,
and if the embankments breach, we are in for serious problems,''
said Puranman Mittal, the relief commissioner in Bihar state, which
suffered the most damage in India.
</P>
<P>
Bihar residents ran screaming through the streets on Wednesday
when a mild tremor rumbled through the area. No casualties or
damage was reported, witnesses and the Seismological Observatory in
New Delhi said.
</P>
<P>
Residents in Dharan, the worst-hit area of Nepal, also raced
from their homes Wednesday during two aftershocks, officials in
Katmandu said. No further damage was reported in the city, where
100 houses collapsed during the quake.
</P>
<P>
Rescue workers demolished 50 homes in Dharan on Wednesday that
were severely damaged in the temblor, police inspector G. Adhikari
said.
``We will continue to demolish houses until we are satisfied
(the ones remaining) are to safe to live in,'' he said.
``This is the biggest calamity to strike Nepal,'' Prime Minister
Marich Man Singh Shrestha, said Tuesday after a tour of devastated
areas in his nation.
</P>
<P>
At least 758 people died and 950 were injured in both countries
Sunday when the earthquake jolted the mountainous India-Nepal
border region.
</P>
<P>
It was the deadliest quake to strike the subcontinent since
1950, when, by official count, 1,500 people were killed in the
eastern Indian state of Assam.
</P>
<P>
Indian officials said Wednesday that at least 196 died in India
in Sunday's disaster. Officials in Nepal said at least 562 people
were killed in Nepal, including 31 people whose bodies were found
in remote areas on Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
In India's Bihar state, officials said the water had reached
dangerous levels and was still rising in six rivers: the Ganges,
the Ghagara, the Burigandak, the Bagmati, the Koshi and the
Mahananada.
</P>
<P>
To make matters worse, survey teams found cracks in the
embankments of the six rivers, which are swollen by monsoon rains
that began in late June.
</P>
<P>
Engineers tried to strengthen the weakened embankments with
cement, and helicopters made aerial surveys watching for ruptures.
</P>
<P>
As survivors in both countries began rebuilding homes damaged or
destroyed by the quake, medicine, food and financial aid began
arriving from abroad.
</P>
<P>
Elroy J. Carlson, an official at the U.S. Embassy in Katmandu,
said the United State offered $25,000 in aid. In New Delhi, U.S.
</P>
<P>
Ambassador John Gunther Dean presented the government with a
similar amount for Indian victims.
</P>
<P>
Michael Hamilton, an official at the British Embassy in
Katmandu, said three medical teams had been sent to Dharan. ``The
teams are carrying two truckloads of blood and medicine,'' Hamilton
said.
</P>
<P>
The British army also runs a military hospital in Dharan, where
at least 100 people were admitted. The government hospital in
Dharan treated hundreds of people injured when brick and wood
houses collapsed.
</P>
<P>
U.N. agencies and the Red Cross also sent medical teams to
Nepal, and the government began distributing 90-pound bags of rice.
</P>
<P>
The relief efforts were hampered in both countries by heavy
rains which cut off communications and road links to several of the
affected areas.
``The earthquake hit a wide area, and it is a big job to reach
the remote villages. But we are trying,'' said Mittal, the relief
official in Bihar state.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880825-0147
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>25
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Parents of Peace Corps Worker Find Out Son Is Safe
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>IOWA CITY, Iowa (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The parents of a Peace Corps worker
learned Thursday that their son, a volunteer in Nepal, was safe
following an earthquake last weekend that killed at least 750
people in that country and neighboring India.
``They called this morning, that's the first we had heard about
anything since the quake,'' said Arthur Giaquinta, whose
24-year-old son, Peter, lives in a village 10 miles north of the
hard-hit Dharan Bazar township.
</P>
<P>
Jim Flanigan, a Peace Corps spokesman in Washington, said Peter
Giaquinta was ``fine as far as we know.''
In Boston, the brother of Peace Corps volunteer Bettyjean
Bouffard, 27, said Thursday she called her relatives to say she was
safe. The call, said Dave Bouffard, was the first news the family
had had of her safety.
``We're ecstatic,'' he said, adding that his sister had been
living with a Nepalese family five miles from the earthquake
epicenter.
</P>
<P>
Flanigan said the Peace Corps has been able to track down all
but three of the 157 volunteers in Nepal. There are no Peace Corps
members in India, he said.
</P>
<P>
The three, he said, are from Michigan, Wisconsin and the
Philadelphia area; he declined to release their names.
``We have a problem with roads out, monsoon rains,'' Flanigan
said. ``In the best of times, reaching some of these volunteers is
several days.''
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880826-0161
</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP 
</SOURCE>
<DATE> 
<DAY>26
</DAY> 
<MONTH>08
</MONTH> 
<YEAR>88
</YEAR> 
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
<HL>
Death Toll Rises to 981, Legislator Beaten to Death
</HL>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>BHAKTAPUR, Nepal (AP) 
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An earthquake that devastated parts of
Nepal and India earlier this week has killed more than 980 people,
officials from the two countries said Friday.
</P>
<P>
Mourners paraded through the streets of this medieval town,
calling for revenge after a former legislator was beaten to death
by political rivals while he was distributing relief supplies to
earthquake victims.
``Hang the murderers,'' scores of young men chanted as they
marched in front of a jeep bearing the battered body of Karna
Hyanju, once a sympathizer of the now-outlawed Communist Party.
</P>
<P>
Witnesses said Hyanju was beaten with umbrellas and sticks late
Thursday afternoon, then dragged through the streets for nearly two
hours before police intervened. He died Friday at the Bir hospital
in Katmandu, 7 miles west of Bhaktapur.
</P>
<P>
Uttam Dhaubanjar, a 28-year-old bank employee and neighbor of
the dead man, said Hyanju had been handing out blankets, milk and
other food in Bhaktapur when he was accosted by a group of men who
accused him of giving relief supplies only to his own supporters.
</P>
<P>
Reports of damage and devastation continued to arrive from
remote parts of Nepal on Friday, and the Home Affairs Ministry
updated its confirmed death toll to 704.
</P>
<P>
In India, the official count rose to 277. But survivors, the
news media and opposition politicians say the toll could be as high
as 1,500.
</P>
<P>
Sunday's earthquake registered 6.5 on the Richter scale, which
records energy released by a tremor according to ground motion
measured by a seismograph. A reading of 6 indicates the possibility
of severe damage, while 7 signifies a major quake.
</P>
<P>
Dhaubanjar said he saw about 40 people rounded up by police
Thursday night after Hyanju's beating death. He said many belonged
to the same Communist faction that Hyanju once supported.
``People started beating him with umbrellas,'' Dhaubanjar said.
``There were a lot of scratches on his body, and a lot of blood. It
looked like one ear was missing. Then they made a necklace of their
shoes (by tying the laces together), put it around his neck and
pulled him through the streets.''
As Hyanju's body was taken through the winding streets of
Bhaktapur, a 12th-century town of ancient Hindu temples, thousands
of the town's 50,000 people jammed streets, temple steps and the
balconies of brick and mud houses.
</P>
<P>
Pashupati Rana, one of several Cabinet ministers who marched in
the funeral procession, said several people were arrested in the
killing, including the mayor, the deputy mayor and a member of the
Rashtriya Panchayat, or non-partisan assembly.
</P>
<P>
Rana, who is minister of local development and legislative,
affairs, called Hyanju's death ``political murder.''
Hyanju served in the Panchayat from 1981 until 1986 when he lost
the backing of the Communists in Bhaktapur, traditionally a leftist
stronghold.
</P>
<P>
The Panchayat, whose members are elected on non-party lines, was
created after the late king Mahendra abolished the old Parliament
and all political parties in 1960, saying a Western-style
parliamentary system was not suited to his mountain kingdom.
</P>
<P>
Dhaubanjar and a group of young men who gathered around him said
Hyanju was perceived as a government supporter despite his previous
communist leanings.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
