<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880331-0140</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>31</DAY> <MONTH>03</MONTH> <YEAR>88</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>It's The Time of Year For Funnels</HL></HEADLINE>


<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>

<TEXT>
   Rumbling spring thunderstorms have announced the
beginning of the unofficial tornado season that runs from April
through June across Texas and other Tornado Alley states in the
nation's heartland.
   From 1951 through 1986, there have been an average of 118
tornadoes in Texas per year, according to the state climatologist's
office in College Station.
   More than 60 percent of those occur between April and June,
records show. In April and June an average of 18 to 19 tornadoes
occur each month, but in May, when weather conditions are the most
unstable, that average increases to about 36.
   A few twisters were already recorded in early March in Texas but
they did little or no damage. A tornado that touched down Tuesday
in central Louisiana, near Bunkie, destroyed two brick homes.
   ``People should have plans of what they'll do in tornadoes. If
they wait until it gets there, it's going to be too late,'' said
Buddy McIntyre, a forecaster with the National Weather Service.
   Last May 22, a killer storm flattened the small West Texas town
of Saragosa, killing 30 people and injuring 162. In mid-November,
11 people died in East Texas when a series of tornadoes trashed
towns from Cherokee County to the Gulf Coast.
   ``A tornado is such a devastating kind of storm. No matter how
much preparation you do there is some property damage and some loss
of life. But there are some things you can do to protect yourself
and property,'' said Laureen Chernow, a spokeswoman for the
governor's division of emergency management.
   One is to know the difference between the tornado watches and
tornado warnings issued by the weather service.
   A watch means weather conditions are suitable for development of
a tornado, and people should keep a careful lookout for potential
funnel clouds.
   A tornado warning means one has already developed and has been
spotted. Take cover immediately and don't go outside, but if you
are in a car or mobile home you will be safer taking cover in the
nearest ditch or depression.
   At home, the best place to stay is a basement or underground
storm shelter. If no such shelter is available, go inside a closet
in the center of the house or bathroom or lie flat under a heavy
table.
   McIntyre noted that most fatalities in a tornado are from flying
debris, so ``we tell people to squat down, cover their heads and
present a low profile.''
   James R. McDonald, director of the Institute for Disaster
Research at Texas Tech University, says many people mistakenly try
to outrun tornadoes in their cars.
   During the 1979 Wichita Falls tornado that killed 53, McDonald
said, ``people jumped in their cars and drove down Main Street at
90 mph.'' Twenty-six people died while trying to outrun the twister.
   Another misconception is about opening windows. It was once
believed that windows needed to be open to equalize air pressure
between the storm and the inside of a house to prevent the house
from exploding.
   McIntyre said there are enough natural openings in a house to
equalize air pressure, and ``if that tornado wants to open your
windows, it'll do that for you.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880419-0131</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>19</DAY> <MONTH>04</MONTH> <YEAR>88</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>Four Die In North Florida Tornado</HL></HEADLINE>

<HEADLINE><HL>LaserGraphic NY20, LaserPhoto covering</HL></HEADLINE>


<DATELINE>MADISON, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>

<TEXT>
   A tornado blasted through this North
Florida town before dawn today, destroying several homes and a
college library, blowing off rooftops, flipping cars and leaving
four people dead and 15 injured, officials said.
   The tornado touched down at 4:30 a.m. just west of Madison,
about 50 miles east of Tallahassee, and cut a 12-mile swath of
destruction, authorities said.
   ``There was this huge roar and then I heard a tree crack out
there and thought we were all gone,'' said Marie Prince, a Madison
County sheriff's dispatcher. The tornado passed only four blocks
from her office.
   Four people were killed north of town, said Sheriff Joe Peavy.
Fifteen people were injured, but none of the injuries was critical,
according to Madison County Memorial Hospital administrator Jeannie
Baker.
   A house-to-house search found no more bodies, but a man and a
baby had to be freed from separate homes where they were trapped,
Peavy said.
   Two of the deaths occurred in mobile homes blown apart by the
tornado, and four other houses were seriously damaged as well, said
Madison County Civil Defense Director Bernard Wilson.
   ``It didn't leave any of it. Not even a dish. You'd never know
there was a trailer here,'' said Dorothy Butler, sister of one of
the victims.
   Rescue units from adjoining counties were helping out, along
with state law enforcement and forestry officials. State prisoners
were also on their way to help with the cleanup, Peavy said. He had
no estimate of the damage.
   The tornado was part of a storm system that struck across the
Southeast with high winds, lightning and hail. Trees, roofs and
mobile homes were damaged, and at least six other injuries were
reported.
   Madison, a town of about 3,500 people, is the county seat of
Madison County, a thinly populated tobacco growing area of piney
woods, rolling hills and swamps on the border with Georgia.
   The twister's destructive path started in front of a shopping
center and then proceeded straight into North Florida Junior
College, where it ``totaled the new library and took the roof off
the auditorium,'' Peavy said.
   The twister blew away several homes, blew the roof off a nearby
church, overturned cars and knocked down trees, Peavy said.
   As far as his office knew, all the damage was from one tornado,
Peavy said. He said the tornado's sweep through town lasted under
30 minutes.
   Electric company workers were restoring power throughout the
area.
   Two tornadoes struck near the towns of Malone and Bascom, about
100 miles to the west of Madison, said Jackson County emergency
management director John Mader.
   Three homes and a trailer were destroyed and five homes
seriously damaged, he said, and two people were slightly injured.
Many county roads were blocked by fallen trees, he said, and
officials were surveying the area by helicopter.
   The tornadoes were spawned by a belt of thunderstorms being
pushed by a cold front. Hail the size of golf balls and damaging
winds hit Louisiana, Mississippi, Alabama and Georgia.
   More than one inch of rain fell in one hour this morning in
Waycross, Ga., 70 miles northeast of here, and wind gusts of 40 mph
were reported in Valdosta, according to the National Weather
Service.
   Elsewhere in Georgia, trees and power lines were reported blown
down, a barn was reported destroyed and a tin roof was blown off an
old building.
   The winds destroyed up to nine mobile homes west of Bainbridge,
Ga., Monday night, injuring three people, one seriously. The
sheriff's office said the wind left the homes in shreds. Bainbridge
is 25 miles northwest of Tallahassee.
   A 9-year-old girl from Cottonwood, Ala., was injured by
lightning as she stood near a stove at her home Monday night. The
lightning accompanied a tornado that moved through southern Houston
County about 60 miles northwest of Tallahasse.
   In the eastern Georgia's Bulloch County, six mobile homes and
one house were heavily damaged shortly after dawn today, but no
injuries were reported, the weather service said.
   Tornado watches were still in effect across 14 southeastern
Georgia and 15 northeastern Florida counties until at least five
hours after the tornado hit.
   Madison County has been hit by seven tornadoes since 1959 with
only one injury reported, according to the National Weather Service.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890227-0016</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>27</DAY> <MONTH>02</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>Tornado Deaths Below Average in '88</HL></HEADLINE>


<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>

<TEXT>
   One of nature's most vicious spectacles, the
tornado, is poised to renew its annual assault on America, as
changeable spring weather breeds the storms that spawn twisters.
   Last year was one of fewer than normal tornado deaths, but even
so, more than 700 of the violent funnel clouds struck the nation.
   In 1988 the nation recorded 32 tornado deaths, down from the 59
killed a year earlier and well below the long-term average of 99
fatalities annually, the National Weather Service reported on Sunday.
   But while that's good news, it isn't an indication that the
danger has lessened.
   ``There is no way of knowing what this tornado season will bring,
but the way to survive is through preparedness,'' said Ed Ferguson,
deputy director of the National Severe Storms Forecast Center in
Kansas City.
   Meteorologists have attributed the decline in tornado deaths in
recent years to increased public awareness of the storms, which are
most common in May and June but can occur in any month of the year.
   Unusually warm and wet weather last November helped trigger a
record number of tornadoes for that month, at 121 across the
country. The average for November is only 23 tornadoes, and the
record had been 81, set in 1973.
   Last year also recorded the largest tornado outbreak in 14 years.
That took place on Mother's Day when 57 twisters tore through parts
of Arkansas, Illinois, Iowa and Wisconsin. That outbreak didn't
cause any deaths, although 10 injuries were reported.
   Arkansas and Tennessee recorded the most fatalities last year
with six deaths apiece, followed by Florida with five. Four people
were killed in North Carolina and two each in Mississippi and
Nebraska. States with a single fatality apiece were Kentucky,
Michigan, Missouri, New York, Oklahoma, South Carolina and Texas.
   The transition from winter to spring, spurring unsettled weather
and frequent thunderstorms, helps create tornadoes, violently
twisting winds that reach down from thunderclouds.
   After a low point in the winter they begin to increase sharply in
March and peak in May with a national average of 166 twisters in
that month, according to records kept at the National Climatic Data
Center.
   June ranks second, averaging 150 tornadoes, followed by April
with 109 in a typical year. Other months averaging more than a
twister-a-day somewhere in the nation are July, 82; August, 57;
March, 50 and September, 38.
   Hot weather stirring the air helps form thunderstorms and their
tornadoes, with 60 percent of all twisters occurring between noon
and sunset, according to the National Center for Atmospheric
Research. Tornadoes are least likely during the early morning just
before sunrise.
   The typical tornado is only about 50 yards wide and travels about
two miles on the ground _ 87 percent of the time heading toward the
northeast, NCAR researchers report.
   But while an individual twister can cover only a small area, they
often come in groups and in the affected area destruction can be
total.
   The familiar funnel cloud is the most common sign of a tornado
although adjacent winds can also cause severe damage.
   When twisters are in an area, common sense and knowing a few
simple rules can save lives, the National Weather Service says.
   If tornadoes threaten, turn on radio or television to keep
current on the danger, the agency says. The weather service even has
its own radio network which can provide continual updates. If a
twister is reported, safety rules include:
   _At home, seek shelter immediately in a basement or interior
hallway. Stay away from windows and outside walls.
   _At school, move to hallways and lie flat on the floor with head
covered.
   _In a mobile home or trailer, leave immediately. Head for a
secure shelter or lie flat on the ground. Be wary of areas with poor
drainage, however, because of the possibility of flooding from the
thunderstorm.
   _At work or in public buildings, head for interior hallways on
the lowest floor, or designated shelter areas.
   _In an automobile, leave immediately. Do not try to outrun a
tornado.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890403-0123</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>03</DAY> <MONTH>04</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>$adv06</HL></HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE><HL>For release Thursday, April 6, and thereafter</HL></HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE><HL>With BC-EXP--Tornado Season-Radar</HL></HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
   Here are some tornado facts from the National Weather Service,
Insurance Information Institute and news accounts:
   _Tornadoes can occur in any month, but are more frequent from
April through June and between 3 and 6 p.m.
   _Most tornadoes track southwest to northeast, but their paths
can spiral erratically.
   _The portion of a thunderstorm adjacent to large hail is where
tornadoes are most likely to occur.
   _There were 32 tornado-related deaths reported in 1988, down
from 59 in 1987 and well below the average of 99 a year.
   _Less than 2 percent of all tornadoes are classified as violent,
with wind speeds of more than 200 mph and a path averaging 26
miles. The longest tornado on record went 219 miles across
Missouri, Illinois and Indiana in March 1925.
   _Tornadoes travel at an average 30 mph, but can stand still or
go 70 mph.
   _The largest single outbreak of twisters on record was in April
1974, when 148 storms killed 300 people in 13 states over two days.
   _When a tornado threatens, seek shelter in the basement or
central parts of the house, office or school building, away from
windows.
</TEXT>

</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891116-0115</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>16</DAY> <MONTH>11</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>Twister Rips Through Alabama City, Killing 17</HL></HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE><HL>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `Gov. Guy...' with 3 grafs to UPDATE with 25-mile
path, tornado watches in Northeast. Picks up 6th graf, `Elsewhere:'</HL></HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE><HL>LaserPhotos WX9, HUN3; LaserGraphic</HL></HEADLINE>


<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>

<TEXT>
   Rescuers crawled through collapsed homes
and shops today looking for more victims of a tornado that carved a
3-mile stretch of destruction, killing 17 people, injuring 463 and
leaving 1,000 homeless.
   ``It's like taking six to 10 city blocks and putting them in a
blender and putting it on liquefy,'' said rescue worker Bob
Caraway, whose specialty is cave rescues. He was among those called
out to help dig through rubble for survivors or the bodies of the
dead.
   The tornado was one of a series that touched down Wednesday in
an arc spanning at least seven states from the Deep South to the
Midwest. The other tornadoes caused at least 19 injuries and
far-flung property damage.
   In Huntsville, teams with cranes and floodlights searched for
the injured or dead, hampered by wind-whipped rain and temperatures
that plummeted overnight from 73 degrees into the 30s.
   Gov. Guy Hunt sent 50 National Guardsmen to help and said he
would view damage Friday. His spokesman, Terry Abbott, said aerial
surveys indicate the twister hopped along a 25-mile path, much of
it straight through Huntsville.
   By this afternoon, severe thunderstorms were crossing the
Northeast. The National Weather Service put out a tornado watch for
parts of Maryland, Delaware, Pennsylvania, New Jersey, New York,
all of Connecticut and Rhode Island, and parts of Massachusetts,
Vermont and New Hampshire.
   In Pennsylvania, the weather service said it received
unconfirmed reports of a tornado that turned over a car and knocked
down trees and power lines near Gettysburg.
   Elsewhere:
   _In Georgia, 19 people were injured, four critically, and at
least 200 people were evacuated after a tornado strus.C., and a tornado
toppled trees, downed
power lines and damaged 20 houses near Greenwood, S.C. No injuries
were reported in either state.
   _Tornadoes caused minor property damage in Mississippi, Kentucky
and Indiana.
   _In West Virginia, high winds believed to be tornadoes swept
Jefferson County early today, overturning trailers, blowing roofs
off homes and downing power lines, authorities said. Four people
were injured, two seriously.
   _Heavy thunderstorms destroyed at least a dozen homes in
Alorton, Ill., killing one person and injuring 20 others, five
seriously, authorities said.
   The tornado struck Huntsville with virtually no warning
Wednesday afternoon as the city's streets grew busy with the
approach of rush hour. In a matter of seconds, cars were hurled
through the air and crushed, and apartments and stores looked as if
they had been bombed.
   ``It was fast,'' said Lucy Lee Rusk, whose apartment was
battered by debris. ``It was like one big pop and that's when
everything went.''
   The National Weather Service had issued a tornado watch earlier
in the day, but did not issue a more urgent tornado warning until
4:39 p.m. CST, when the tornado was spotted at the municipal golf
course. By then, it was already tearing up the city.
   A watch means a tornado is considered possible, while a warning
means a tornado is believed to exist.
   Huntsville Police Maj. Robert Moder said this morning that 463
people were injured by the twister, which plowed through a school
and rural areas as well as a shopping mall and adjacent apartments.
   Police Chief Richard Ottman initially put the number of dead at
19, but his clerk, Kitty Whitworth, later said the death toll was
lowered to 17 after police confirmed the count of bodies. She said
police had no firm reports of people missing.
   No children in the school were killed, but about 30 youngsters
were in a kindergarten class at the building, and five were
reported injured. Most of the dead were in apartments, stores or
cars.
   Mayor Steve Hettinger estimated the number of homeless at 1,000
and said officials were preparing a request for federal disaster
assistance.
   A worker at a building owned by the Madison County Jaycees said
42 people were staying there early today, and described the mood of
the survivors as ``shock, mostly, and disbelief.''
   ``They're thankful to be alive and they're thankful their
families are alive,'' he said, adding that the shelter had received
calls from around the country from worried relatives.
   The tornado was Alabama's deadliest since a 1975 twister killed
22 people in Birmingham, said Danny Cooper, state emergency
management director in Montgomery.
   Along a highway near a destroyed apartment complex, cars were
flipped and smashed into telephone poles and crushed by trees. The
roadway was strewn with used bandages and medical gloves left by
emergency workers treating the injured.
   Humana Hospital administrator David Miller said doctors had
difficulty reaching the hospital because of blocked roads.
   Those in the tornado's path spoke with awe of its fury.
   ``It came in with a huge roar, an enormous amount of water, and
it just started shaking and tearing at everything it could get hold
of,'' said real estate broker Ike Carroll, who was in his car.
   Heavy overhead power lines ``started snapping just like a circus
performer would snap his whip,'' Carroll said. ``All of these heavy
arcing, flashing lines that were just popping and snapping over the
top of us. ... It was as if you were looking into an arc-welder,
they were so bright.''
   Kenneth Lenhard had undergone an operation at the Crestwood
Hospital on Wednesday and returned to his room about an hour before
a window in the next room blew out as the tornado passed.
   ``There wasn't anything I could do, so I covered my head,''
Lenhard said. ``I thought, `What the heck, I'm already half dead.'
''
   The downtown Jones Valley Elementary School, the Waterford
Square and adjacent Queensbury apartment complexes were reduced to
rubble.
   Kindergarteners were the only pupils left at the school by the
time the twister hit.
   The city is home to NASA's Marshall Space Flight Center and the
Army's Redstone Arsenal, but no serious damage was reported from
the space agency or weapons testing center.
   At least two other tornadoes were reported in Alabama, injuring
at least three people in addition to the Huntsville total.
   Near Palmetto, Ga., resident Jeff Bryant said his home at the
Sweetbriar Mobile Home Park near Interstate 85 began to vibrate
when the twister approached.
   ``Then we heard a large, loud, swirling and humming noise,'' he
recalled. ``It didn't sound like a train like everybody says it
does. I lived near a train track. It did not sound like a train. It
sounded more like a jet aircraft at very close range.''
   Thomas Farr was driving on Interstate 85 when the tornado hit.
``It was picking up cars and tossing them like toys off the
interstate,'' he said. ``I saw one 18-wheeler flip over. The car in
front of us was flipped about 100 yards, and the guy was thrown out
of his passenger window and landed 50 feet from his car.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP891116-0191</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>16</DAY> <MONTH>11</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>With AM-Southern Tornadoes, Bjt</HL></HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE><HL>Eds: INSERTS items on Illinois and Ohio, changes death toll to 27
to reflect Illinois death, SUBS West Virginia item to CORRECT location
of Jefferson County.</HL></HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
   Here is a state-by-state look at the tornadoes and severe
thunderstorms that have killed at least 27 people, injured more
than 500 and left hundreds homeless since Wednesday:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   _Alabama: Seventeen people were killed in Huntsville on
Wednesday when a tornado touched down just before rush hour,
causing major damage. There were 463 injuries and about 1,000
people left homeless, authorities said. Three people were injured
in an earlier tornado in Clay County in eastern Alabama.
   _District of Columbia: Heavy thunderstorms packing 50-60 mph
winds swept through the Washington area during the Thursday morning
rush hour, flooding some streets. About 10,000 customers lost
power, mostly in the Maryland suburbs. No injuries were reported.
   _Georgia: 19 people were injured, four critically, and at least
200 people were evacuated Wednesday after a tornado struck two
mobile home parks and an interstate highway near Palmetto, about 25
miles southeast of Atlanta.
   _Illinois: Strong winds Wednesday morning destroyed about 15
homes and killed one woman in St. Clair County in southwestern
Illinois. Damage was estimated at $3 million to $5 million.
   _Indiana: A tornado was spotted Wednesday afternoon around
Richmond, close to the Ohio border. It ripped the top off a silo
and tipped a semi-trailer into a ditch. The driver was slightly
injured.
   _Kentucky: The storm Wednesday left at least 28 people injured;
damage was estimated at $2.5 million or more. A storm believed to
have been a tornado cut a mile-long swath of destruction through
the town of Flaherty in Meade County. Damage was also reported in
Bullitt, LaRue, Hardin and Pendleton counties.
   _Maryland, Delaware: Heavy winds on Thursday leveled a church
building in Kent County, Md., lifted roofs from buildings in
Baltimore and cut power to tens of thousands of utility customers,
authorities said. Reports of tornado damage came from Kent County,
Md., and Hockessin, Del. National Weather Service officials were
unable to immediately confirm the reports. No injuries were
reported.
   _Mississippi: Scattered damage and power outages were reported
Wednesday after radar showed tornadoes in Neshoba and Kemper
counties in the east-central portion of the state. No injuries were
reported.
   _New Jersey: High winds and tornadoes were blamed for one death,
at least four injuries and widespread damage and power outages
Thursday. A tornado touched down in Piscataway shortly after noon,
collapsing on house and damaging 10 to 12 others. One person
suffered a minor injury. A bridge connecting Elizabeth with New
York City was closed after two tractor trailers overturned in heavy
winds; one truck driver died and a passenger was injured. Two minor
injuries were reported in Bergen County.
   _New York: A severe thunderstorm Thursday sent a tree crashing
through an elementary school roof in Newburgh, about 60 miles north
of New York City, killing at least seven children and injuring 18,
authorities said. In New York City, a woman was killed by a 12-foot
steel beam that apparently had blown off her apartment's water
tower. Tornadoes were reported in Peekskill, just north of the city.
   _North Carolina: A pair of tornadoes were reported Wednesday in
Henderson County, where a vacant house was destroyed. No injuries
were reported.
   _Ohio: High winds described by local authorities as a tornado
hopscotched across north-central Ohio on Wednesday, ripping roofs
off barns and houses, destroying farm sheds and damaging trailer
homes. One man was hospitalized from a lightning strike and a woman
was slightly injured by flying debris.
   _Pennsylvania: High winds and funnel clouds ripped off roofs and
downed trees in eastern Pennslyvania on Thursday, shattering
windows in Philadelphia skyscrapers. No serious injuries were
reported, but at least 75,000 customers in southeastern
Pennsylvania lost power.
   _South Carolina: A tornado Wednesday downed power lines and
damaged 20 houses near Greenwood. No injuries were reported.
   _West Virginia: High winds knocked over trees, ripped roofs off
houses and toppled a trailer early Thursday in Jefferson County,
just west of Frederick, Md., injuring four members of one family,
two seriously. The National Weather Service said the storm probably
was a tornado.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP900619-0006</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>19</DAY> <MONTH>06</MONTH> <YEAR>90</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>Midwest Sees 1990 Tornado Parade</HL></HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE><HL>With PM-Flash Floods</HL></HEADLINE>


<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>

<TEXT>
   1990 is fast becoming one of the worst
years on record for tornadoes and flooding across the middle and
southern sections of the nation.
   So far this year, 726 tornadoes have touched down nationwide,
well ahead of the 640 tornadoes recorded during the first six
months of last year, and the 30-year average of 482 tornadoes
recorded between January and July, said Frederick Ostby of the
National Severe Storms Forecast Center here.
   The nation had 747 tornadoes in the first six months of 1973 _
one of the biggest years for tornadoes since 1950, when the
forecast center began keeping reliable records of the storms. There
were 756 tornadoes reported in 1982.
   ``We seem to be on a pace that would put us up with those two
years,'' Ostby said.
   The culprit in this tornado barrage across the Plains is a
persistent West Coast pattern of low pressure in the upper
atmosphere that is keeping the jet stream anchored at a southern
latitude.
   This year's storms seem particularly violent, as illustrated by
the March 13 tornado that cut a swath a mile wide and brought winds
of 300 mph to a field in Kansas. The tornado was the strongest to
hit the United States since 1985.
   The first weekend in June saw the worst outburst of tornadoes
since 1974. Ostby said 101 tornadoes touched down from Kansas to
Kentucky, leaving nine people dead.
   But a break in the storm pattern may be at hand.
   As summer wears on, the land warms up and cold air from Canada
retreats. This moves the boundary of the jet stream to the north,
Ostby said.
   ``Our longer range computer forecasts are suggestive of that.
There is some kind of a readjustment beginning to take place in the
upper atmosphere,'' he said.
   However, a study of tornado trends indicates parts of the
Midwest, particularly Kansas and Missouri, are heading into a
six-year period of more intense tornadoes.
   The study of tornadoes since early this century shows that they
are concentrated in regions for five- or six-year periods, said
Michael Smith, president of WeatherData Inc.
   But warning of impending storms is becoming more sophisticated,
leading to fewer deaths. Tornadoes have caused 20 deaths this year,
while an average year in the 1980s saw 52 deaths, and in the 1970s
nearly 100, Ostby said.
   ``There are better watches, better warnings and a better
response,'' Ostby said.
   Ostby credited the quicker response to computers that allow
meteorologists to see many sources of data, such as satellite
readings, more clearly.
   Flooding in the South and the Plains has been as destructive as
the tornadoes.
   The death toll from last week's flash floods in Shadyside, Ohio,
rose to 21 on Monday, making the flood one of the most deadly in
recent years. Authorities held out little hope for more than a
dozen others listed as missing.
   Wegee and Pipe creeks overflowed during storms that dumped 5{
inches of rain in 3{ hours. The floods destroyed as many as 70
houses and damaged up to 40, officials said.
   Flooding in Texas has been blamed for at least 16 deaths since
April. An estimated 10,000 people were forced from their homes, and
high water caused hundreds of millions of dollars in damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA070190-0073</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA </SOURCE>

<DATE> <DAY>1</DAY> <MONTH>7</MONTH> <YEAR>90</YEAR> </DATE>


<HEADLINE><HL>
'MR. TORNADO' DEVOTES LIFE TO UNDERSTANDING NATURE'S AWESOME DESTRUCTIVE POWER 
</HL></HEADLINE>

<DATELINE>
CHICAGO 
</DATELINE>

<TEXT>
<P>
Tetsuya Theodore Fujita saw his only natural tornado near Denver in 1982. "It 
was like meeting my lover," he says. 
</P>
<P>
"Since then, my passion really went up," said Fujita, a professor of 
geophysical science who has been studying tornadoes for 42 years and is 
considered one of the world's foremost authorities on the violent storms. 
</P>
<P>
Fujita, 69, spends much of his time in his lab at the University of Chicago 
creating tornadoes for research. 
</P>
<P>
He creates tornadoes over a large fan, which makes a swirling motion; another 
fan above simulates a low-pressure system by adding an updraft to the mix. With 
a bit of steam added to make the phenomenon visible, he creates twisters six to 
eight feet tall. 
</P>
<P>
The miniature versions are as impossible to redirect or squelch as their 
full-size cousins, he says. He has tried by crawling right up next to them and 
using rulers or books to change their direction. 
</P>
<P>
Fujita came to the United States from Japan in 1953, partly because there are 
so many tornadoes in this country. 
</P>
<P>
"Tornadoes are very rare in Japan," Fujita said. "They have about 10 to 15 a 
year. But one occurred within about 15 miles of my hometown. I was quite 
impressed with the localized severity of the wind." 
</P>
<P>
When he saw his first tornado, he and a team of scientists were studying wind 
shear and its effect on aircraft. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a beautiful thing," Fujita said. "Of course, I was 20 miles away from 
that one. 
</P>
<P>
"If you're in it," he added, "it's a terrible thing." 
</P>
<P>
Forecasters still have trouble predicting tornadoes. 
</P>
<P>
But Fujita has helped define the conditions most likely to spawn them. Groups 
of thunderstorms are not as likely to spawn tornadoes as single, large storms 
because multiple storms in the same area compete. 
</P>
<P>
"Each one tries to rotate, but they all can't. They're just like human beings: 
The rich may become richer and the poor may get poorer." 
</P>
<P>
Fujita also discovered that most strong tornadoes are actually six or seven 
small twisters he calls suction vortices, rotating around the center of a 
larger tornado. 
</P>
<P>
"A suction vortex can pick up a car or a small house or something, but when 
you're standing right next to it you can be completely safe." 
</P>
<P>
He has studied tornadoes that have dropped houses into lakes, made off with one 
car and left another right next to it untouched, and moved whole flocks of cows 
and sheep -- which lived through the experience. 
</P>
<P>
He also developed the Fujita scale for measuring the strength of tornadoes. It 
runs from zero -- a tornado that might break twigs on trees -- to five -- a 
twister that can rip houses from their foundations. 
</P>
<P>
But Fujita considers his work on other air movements called downbursts and 
microbursts among his most significant achievements. 
</P>
<P>
Downbursts are powerful drafts of air moving down from a thunderstorm cloud. 
Scientists long thought the drafts dissipated before reaching the ground. 
</P>
<P>
Microbursts are smaller versions of downbursts, but are more dangerous because 
they give pilots less time to react, Fujita said. 
</P>
<P>
The National Transportation Safety Board has cited microbursts, a term coined 
by Fujita, as the cause of 17 aircraft accidents in the last 15 years, causing 
577 fatalities. 
</P>
<P>
Among them was the 1985 crash of a Delta L-1011 in Dallas that killed 137 
people. A downburst also was implicated in the collapse of a wall at a school 
in Newburgh, N.Y., that killed nine children. 
</P>
<P>
Fujita's work helped persuade the Federal Aviation Administation to begin 
installing a new radar system at 47 major airports beginning in the early 
1990s. 
</P>
<P>
The Doppler radar system was credited with helping three jetliners at Denver's 
airport avoid potentially catastrophic microbursts last year. 
</P>
<P>
Fujita retires from teaching this year, but will continue his research at the 
university. 
</P>
<P>
"In Texas one time, five people were killed when they drove right into a 
tornado. They just didn't know any better," Fujita said. "I want to make people 
safer." 
</P>
</TEXT>

</DOC>
</CORPUS>
