<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE CORPUS SYSTEM "unified.dtd" >
<CORPUS>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP880517-0226</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>17</DAY> <MONTH>05</MONTH> <YEAR>88</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>Single-Engine Airplane Crashes; Five Killed</HL></HEADLINE>


<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>

<TEXT>
   A single-engine airplane crashed
Tuesday into a ditch beside a dirt road on the outskirts of
Albuquerque, killing all five people aboard, authorities said.
   Four adults and one child died in the crash, which witnesses
said occurred about 5 p.m., when it was raining, Albuquerque police
Sgt. R.C. Porter said.
   The airplane was attempting to land at nearby Coronado Airport,
Porter said. It aborted its first attempt and was coming in for a
second try when it crashed, he said.
   State police said the red-and-white Cessna P210, which seats six
people, was from Salt Lake City.
   Identities of the victims were not immediately available. The
bodies were taken to the Office of the Medical Investigator in
Albuquerque.
   Walter Ramazzini Jr., 17, of Albuquerque, said he was sitting
about 100 yards from the airplane when it crashed.
   ``He was going east, making a left turn from the airport,''
Ramazzini said. ``A gust of wind hit him from right to left.
   ``He did three banks. The wind made him bank to the left 30
degrees or so. To correct for that, he banked right and he kept
going and passed level flight as if to turn right,'' Ramazzini said.
   ``To correct again for that, he went again to the left ... and
went nose-first into the ground,'' said Ramazzini, a student pilot.
``He hit the ground and cartwheeled over.
   ``All I saw was a puff of smoke,'' he said.
   The airplane ``wasn't very high _ maybe 100 feet,'' Ramazzini
said. ``The weather was gusty and showery. It was sprinkling.''
   He said he was among the first four people at the crash site.
   ``We went up there and there was nobody alive,'' Ramazzini said.
``You could smell fuel. We were looking for fire extinguishers.''
He said the witnesses thought the airplane might blow up, so they
retreated.
   Firefighters arrived later and sprayed the crumpled airplane
with water before rescue crews removed the bodies from the craft.
   National Transportation Safety Board investigators were en route
to the crash site to conduct an investigation with the Federal
Aviation Administration.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP881222-0089</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>22</DAY> <MONTH>12</MONTH> <YEAR>88</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>Summary of Crash Developments</HL></HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE><HL>With PM-Britain-Crash Bjt</HL></HEADLINE>

<TEXT>
   Here, at a glance, are developments today involving the crash of
Pan American World Airways Flight 103 Wednesday night in Lockerbie,
Scotland, that killed all 259 people aboard and more than 20 people
on the ground:
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE><HL>THE CRASH</HL></HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
   The jumbo jet, a Boeing 747, apparently exploded in the air
before crashing and investigators focused on terrorist threats to
place a bomb on a Pan Am airliner.
   The crash occurred 54 minutes after takeoff from London's
Heathrow Airport following a routine climb to a cruising altitude of
31,000 feet. The only possible cause immediately ruled out was a
collision with another aircraft.
   Searchers recovered both the airplane's flight recorders.
   Scottish Secretary Malcom Rifkind, the chief British official at
the site, said the widespread wreckage indicated ``the aircraft
clearly experienced some form of explosion.''
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE><HL>LOCKERBIE</HL></HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
   The wreckage of the 747 scattered bodies and debris over 10 miles
of countryside and ravaged the village of Lockerbie.
   Twenty-two people were killed on the ground, most of them in cars
hits by wreckage, authorities said. Forty houses were destroyed when
the plane crashed.
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE><HL>SABOTAGE LIKELY</HL></HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
   The International Air Transport Association believes sabotage is
the most likely explanation for the crash.
   David Kyd, chief public relations officer, said ``it would seem
to us that the most likely hypothesis is an explosion aboard,'' and
that structural problems were unlikely to have been involved in the
crash because of the sudden loss of contact with the plane. The 747
has a reputation for ruggedness and is able to stay aloft even with
serious damage to the structure.
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE><HL>BOMB THREATS</HL></HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
   The State Department warned U.S. embassies that a bomb threat had
been made against Pan Am jetliners flying from Frankfurt to the
United States 2{ weeks ago and the Federal Aviation Administration
told Pan Am this month that the airline might be the target of a
terrorist bombing.
   An unidentified U.S. government source said a a person claiming
to belong to the Abu Nidal group, a radical Palestinian faction,
telephoned the U.S. Embassy in Helsinki, Finland, about two weeks
ago and said a bomb would be placed aboard a Pan Am plane and that
it would be carried by a woman.
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE><HL>CLAIM OF RESPONSIBILITY</HL></HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
   An anonymous caller to the AP office in London claimed
responsibility for the crash and said it was in retaliation for the
downing of an Iran Air Airbus by the U.S. Navy cruiser Vincennes in
July.
   ``We, the Guardians of the Islamic Revolution, are undertaking
this heroic execution in revenge of blowing the Iran air plane by
America a few months ago and keeping the Shah's family in America.
We are very proud,'' the male caller said, then hung up quickly.
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE><HL>CRASH-PLO</HL></HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior official of the Palestine Liberation Organization said
it was ``nonsensical'' to link Palestinians to the crash.
   ``It cannot possibly occur to the Palestinians or the Arabs to
commit such an act,'' Mahmoud Abbas, code-named Abu-Mazen, told
reporters when asked about reports that the plane may have been
downed by sabotage.
</TEXT>
<HEADLINE><HL>PLANE MAINTENANCE RECORD</HL></HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
   The jumbo jet that crashed had at least 24 mechanical problems
during the past eight years, including cracks, severe corrosion and
an on-board fire, according to FAA service records.
   FAA spokeswoman JoAnn Sloane said there have been problems with
minor cracks in 747s over the past few years, but inspections did
not find much cracking.
   ``Those are certainly very reliable airplanes,'' she said, adding
that the problems reported did not appear unusual given the length
of time the plane had been in service.
   Officials at Pratt &amp; Whitney in said they doubted their engines,
which powered the aircraft, caused the crash, and that the plane
could have continued to fly even if three of the four engines failed
at once.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>AP890111-0217</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> AP </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>11</DAY> <MONTH>01</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>



<HEADLINE><HL>Pilot Questioned, More Inspections For Engines</HL></HEADLINE>
<HEADLINE><HL>Eds: ADDS one graf Boeing comment at end.</HL></HEADLINE>


<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>

<TEXT>
   Authorities questioned the badly injured pilot of a
crashed Boeing 737 Wednesday, but revealed no clues as to why the
jet's undamaged right engine was shut down well before the crash
while the other engine burned.
   The Civil Aviation Authority, meanwhile, ordered increased
inspections on 37 airplanes with CFM56 engines, the type on the
Midland Airways jet that crashed Sunday. Investigators said much
more work was needed to pinpoint the cause of the crash, which
killed 44 people and injured 82.
   The government also ordered immediate checks of engine monitoring
systems on similar aircraft to verify that they correctly indicate
right and left, prompting speculation that a malfunctioning alarm
system could have misled the flight crew.
   Freddie Yetman, technical secretary of the British Airline Pilots
Association, said this showed that investigators ``must have some
suspicion of these circuits.''
   In the United States, the Federal Aviation Administration ordered
inspections of 300 Boeing 737s for possible cross-wiring of engine
warning systems.
   U.S. media reported that the crew of the jet shut down the wrong
engine, and Britain's tabloid newspapers drew similar conclusions in
banner headlines.
   ``Error on the Flight Deck,'' the Today newspaper said. ``Fatal
Error'' said the Daily Star. ``Pilot Shut Off the Wrong Engine''
said the Sun.
   The Transport Department said that ``evidence obtained early in
the investigation'' indicated both of the plane's engines ``might
have suffered a related failure'' and that possibility was still
being examined.
   The statement from the department's Air Accidents Investigation
Branch also confirmed that the airplane's left engine caught fire
and the right engine was shut down, and that pilot Kevin Hunt had
told ground control the fire was in the right engine.
   The reasons for shutting down the engine ``are not yet clear and
are still under investigation,'' it said.
   The jet, en route from London to Belfast with 126 people aboard,
plunged into an embankment a half-mile short of the runway at East
Midlands Airport in central England as it was trying to make an
emergency landing Sunday night.
   Hunt, whose back and legs were broken in the crash, was
interviewed for 45 minutes at the intensive care unit of Leicester
Royal Infirmary, said the hospital's deputy general manager Carol
Henshall.
   Mrs. Henshall said some of the ``wilder headlines'' had been kept
from Hunt, but friends and colleagues had told him of the news
reports.
   In the United States, NBC News quoted unidentified U.S.
government sources as saying ``the plane's flight recorders, which
monitor engine performance and the pilots' conversations, indicate
the crew shut down the wrong engine. The trouble was in one _ they
shut down the other.''
   But the network said investigators had yet to detemine whether
faulty instruments contributed to the crash.
   The Washington Post, quoting unidentified accident investigators,
said the crew believed they were making a routine, one-engine
emergency landing, and apparently thought they had solved the
problem when they shut down an engine.
   Spokesmen for both the FAA and the National Transportation Board
said they knew of no information reaching U.S. officials about the
flight recorders' contents.
   The airplane's two ``black boxes,'' the cockpit voice recorder
and digital flight data recorder, are being examined at the
government's laboratory in Farnborough, outside London.
   According to court documents and federal officials in America,
the FBI is investigating a General Electric Co. admission that test
records may have been falsified at a factory which made parts for
the CFM56 engine that failed here.
   The Seattle factory also made a check and flow valve for the F404
engine aboard the Navy's FA-18 fighter, GE spokesman Richard Kennedy
said Wednesday. A letter from a GE attorney last year said test
records may have been falsified for the fighter plane valves.
   The timer valve made by GE for the CFM56 engine could not have
caused the turbine to fail even if the valve malfunctioned, Kennedy
said.
   The plane took off at 7:52 p.m. Sunday. Government sources,
speaking on condition of anonymity, said Hunt reported at 8:06 p.m.
that ``I have an engine on fire.'' Then, at 8:14 p.m., the sources
said he told traffic control: ``I am shutting down the starboard
(right) engine.''
   The plane crashed 12 minutes later at 8:26 p.m.
   The Civil Aviation Authority said that on the advice of
investigators, it was issuing new instructions for the inspection
and monitoring of Boeing 737-300, Boeing 737-400 and Airbus A320
airplanes, all of which use the CFM56 engine.
   The engines are made jointly by U.S.-based GE and a French
company, SNECMA.
   Boeing Commercial Airplanes spokesman Craig Martin said in
Seattle of the FAA's inspection order, ``We certainly believe it's a
prudent measure to go out and check to make sure there's nothing
wrong with the fleet. But certainly this precautionary measure does
not imply there has been any cause identified (for the crash.)''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA072089-0140</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA </SOURCE>

<DATE> <DAY>20</DAY> <MONTH>7</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>


<HEADLINE><HL>
JET CARRYING 293 CRASHES, BURNS IN IOWA; 166 SURVIVE 
</HL></HEADLINE>

<DATELINE>
SIOUX CITY, Iowa 
</DATELINE>

<TEXT>
<P>
A crippled United Airlines DC-10 crashed a half-mile short of a runway while 
trying to make an emergency landing Wednesday afternoon, bursting into a 
cartwheeling fireball that broke into what one eyewitness described as "15,000 
pieces" and killing at least 123 of the 293 passengers and crew members on 
board. 
</P>
<P>
Remarkably, as many as 166 persons survived the violent crash, according to 
Richard Vohs, a spokesman for Iowa Gov. Terry E. Branstad. The fate of four 
others was not immediately known. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Tail Engine Explodes 
</P>
<P>
The plane's tail engine exploded before the crash but it was not immediately 
clear how the explosion contributed to what a Federal Aviation Administration 
spokesman called "complete hydraulic failure," an occurrence regarded as 
extremely rare in the wide-bodied DC-10, which has three independent hydraulic 
systems that operate all the plane's control surfaces on its wings and tail, 
and landing gear and brakes. 
</P>
<P>
As rescuers worked underneath floodlights to remove bodies from the crash site, 
original estimates of the death toll -- one as high as 190, which would have 
made the crash the second worst in U.S. history -- were reduced. 
</P>
<P>
"We don't have a firm count" of the dead, Vohs acknowledged at a press 
conference seven hours after the crash. "But right now, the number (of 
survivors) confirmed is 166." 
</P>
<P>
The survivors of Wednesday's United Flight 232 from Denver to Philadelphia via 
Chicago included several dozen passengers who managed to walk out of a dark, 
smoke-filled, upside-down section of the jet after it broke off and came to 
rest in a tall cornfield off the runway. 
</P>
<P>
"I walked out (through the back of the plane) and found myself in the 
cornfield," passenger David Landsberger told Cable News Network. "We were all 
walking around in shock. I just walked through it like it was a dream. I was a 
little dazed." 
</P>
<P>
"It's the goddamndest thing I ever saw in my life," said Charles Mertz of 
Castle Rock, Colo., another of those who walked away. 
</P>
<P>
Suitcases, paper, mail, clothes, chunks of burning metal and bodies were strewn 
over the inactive runway at Sioux Gateway Airport, where the plane crashed 
after desperately circling for a half-hour. 
</P>
<P>
One hundred ambulances, fire trucks and helicopters from as far away as South 
Dakota plucked out the victims. The search for bodies was difficult because 
some of them were scattered in the cornfield. Many of the survivors were listed 
in critical condition with burns or broken bones. 
</P>
<P>
United Airlines declined to comment on the number of survivors or to release 
the names of the 282 passengers and 11 crew members. 
</P>
<P>
Eyewitnesses said pieces of the 15-year-old airplane -- one of the oldest 
airliners in United's fleet -- were falling off as far as 75 miles from the 
site of the crash. 
</P>
<P>
A team of National Transportation Safety Board investigators left Washington 
Wednesday night for Sioux City. 
</P>
<P>
The hydraulic system that disintegrated Wednesday works the same way a power 
steering system operates in a car. By forcing liquid through a tube, the system 
provides enough power for a pilot to move an airliner's huge tail rudder and 
elevators, and wing panels known as flaps and ailerons -- all needed to steer 
an aircraft. 
</P>
<P>
Some aviation experts, speculating on why Flight 232 crashed after completing 
less than half of its scheduled 930-mile trip to Chicago, suggested that the 
explosion of the tail engine sent shards of metal through the tail section, 
somehow destroying common lines that serve the three hydraulic systems. 
</P>
<P>
There were reports from passengers and observers that the plane's right-wing 
engine also failed before the crash. 
</P>
<P>
In what survivors described as a heroic effort that nearly succeeded, the 
plane's Seattle-based captain, A. C. Haynes -- a 33-year veteran of the airline 
who along with the other 10 crew members survived the crash -- struggled for a 
half-hour to maintain control of the wobbling plane. Radio transmission 
indicated the plane's maneuverability was limited to right-hand turns. 
</P>
<P>
At one point, Haynes attempted a landing on Highway 20 near Cushing, Iowa, but 
chose not to touch down there in favor of trying to make Sioux City, a farming 
and livestock center of 82,000 in the northwest corner of Iowa along the 
Missouri River. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Preparing for Crash Landing 
</P>
<P>
"Then they said we were preparing for a crash landing. They said it would be 
about 30 seconds, but it was about five minutes," another passenger said. 
</P>
<P>
Haynes brought the plane into the airport's 9,000-foot-long southwest runway, 
surrounded by corn, soybeans and pasture with some trees seven miles outside 
downtown Sioux City. 
</P>
<P>
At about 4 p.m. CDT, the plane made its final approach. 
</P>
<P>
Onlookers watched hopefully. 
</P>
<P>
"We thought it was going to make it," said Glen Olson, city editor of the Sioux 
City Journal. 
</P>
<P>
It didn't. 
</P>
<P>
Shortly before touchdown the plane's right wing began to dip and the nose began 
to fall. 
</P>
<P>
The wing hit the ground a half-mile before the runway. The impact caused the 
aircraft to turn over several times as it slid down the runway, "breaking up 
very badly," catching on fire and then exploding, according to Bob Raynesford, 
an FAA spokesman. 
</P>
<P>
"I think it turned over a couple of times. I think it landed upside down," said 
passenger Melanie Cincala of Toledo, Ohio, who said the plane burst into flames 
after she got off. 
</P>
<P>
A large piece of the fuselage barreled onto the runway. Huge clouds of smoke 
and flames billowed upward as firemen sprayed foam over the wreckage. Rescue 
helicopters hovered overhead. 
</P>
<P>
"We were sitting there upside down and it began to fill up with smoke," said 
Cliff Marshall of Columbus, Ohio, who was returning home from Denver. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Push Little Girl Out' 
</P>
<P>
"Then God opened a hole in the basement (the bottom of the plane) and I pushed 
a little girl out. I grabbed another, kept pulling them out until they didn't 
come no more." 
</P>
<P>
Marshall said he thought he helped a half-dozen out and then he ran. 
</P>
<P>
Dr. Romaine Bendixen, clinic commander of Iowa National Guard's 185th tactical 
fighter group, said he was the first doctor on the scene, about three minutes 
after the crash. He had just landed in another plane. 
</P>
<P>
He said the living were scattered among the dead. 
</P>
<P>
"In one group of six seats, a woman sitting in the middle was barely injured, 
her husband beside her was dead and two behind her were dead," Bendixen said. 
</P>
<P>
He said rescuers pulled out three of the flight crew alive. 
</P>
<P>
Hewitt Graham, manager of Graham Flying Service, a charter service and 
corporate aircraft maintenance firm that operates out of the building closest 
to the crash site, said he was in his office, answering phones, when five crash 
victims -- a man, his wife and young son and two other men -- walked in. 
</P>
<P>
"It was amazing. They were in remarkably good shape. From looking at one or two 
of them you wouldn't know they were in the accident," Graham said. Their 
clothes were clean, not mussed, their hair was in place and they had no 
scratches he could see, he said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Survival Rate Remarkable 
</P>
<P>
C. O. Miller, former chief investigator for the National Transportation Safety 
Board, said the crash's survival rate was remarkable and was probably the 
result of the pilot's ability to maneuver the plane close to the ground before 
losing complete control. 
</P>
<P>
"If an airplane cartwheels, it is very fortuitous that anybody got out," said 
Miller, now a private aviation safety consultant in Sidona, Ariz. 
</P>
<P>
He said the huge mass of the DC-10 must have helped the pilot slow the plane as 
it approached the ground and helped keep portions of it intact. He said a 
smaller plane, such as a DC-9, would have been far more likely to break up more 
severely. 
</P>
<P>
St. Luke's Regional Medical Center said 80 to 90 crash victims had been 
admitted and of those 70 were expected to leave the hospital Wednesday night. A 
spokesman said they sustained light injuries. About 50 survivors were housed 
overnight at Briarcliff College. 
</P>
<P>
Lavonne Quirin of Alta, in Buena Vista County, 75 miles from the airport, said 
she and her husband found a cone-shaped section of the plane in a cornfield at 
their seed corn business. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Size of a Car' 
</P>
<P>
"It's about the size of a car," she said. She said no one at the farm saw or 
heard the object fall. 
</P>
<P>
McDonnell Douglas Corp., which builds the DC-10, said the plane was delivered 
to United in 1974. 
</P>
<P>
United, the nation's second largest airline, has one of the oldest fleets in 
the industry. The average age of its aircraft is 13.5 years. The average for 
the entire industry is 11.7 years. 
</P>
<P>
No unusual weather was reported. Wind speeds were clocked up to 30 m.p.h. 
</P>
<P>
A DC-10 was involved in the nation's worst air crash 10 years ago. 
</P>
<P>
On May 25, 1979, American Airlines Flight 191 lost an engine on takeoff, banked 
sideways out of control, slammed into a field and exploded. All 258 passengers 
and 13 crew members died, as well as two people on the ground. 
</P>
<P>
The National Transportation Safety Board cited "maintenance-induced damage" -- 
a 10-inch crack in the engine mount -- that caused the left engine to tear 
loose. The NTSB also criticized McDonnell Douglas' design as vulnerable to 
maintenance damage. 
</P>
<P>
McDonnell Douglas suspended production of the DC-10 airliner in 1983. DC-10 
orders collapsed in 1979 because of the recession and the May, 1979, crash. In 
all, 369 DC-10s were produced. 
</P>
<P>
Wednesday's tragedy was the worst in a recent series of accidents and mishaps 
involving United. 
</P>
<P>
Nine persons were hurled to their deaths last Feb. 24 when a cargo door popped 
open in flight, tearing a gaping hole in a United Boeing 747 jetliner. The 
cause of that accident, which took place over the Pacific near Hawaii, is under 
investigation. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Turns Up Deficiencies 
</P>
<P>
The accident probe has turned up deficiencies in United's procedures regarding 
the cargo doors. The airline told NTSB investigators that it had "somehow 
overlooked" an FAA recommendation to inspect the cargo door latch locks each 
time the door is closed manually, rather than electrically. 
</P>
<P>
On July 10, a United Boeing 747 was forced to make an emergency landing at 
Miami International Airport after the plane was damaged in heavy turbulence 
over the Florida-Georgia border. None of the airliner's 108 passengers were 
injured. On Tuesday, a United DC-10 with 249 people aboard slid 300 yards on 
the runway after landing at rain-soaked O'Hare International Airport in Chicago 
but there were no injuries. 
</P>
<P>
Last Dec. 23, a United DC-10 bound for Chicago with 287 passengers had engine 
problems after takeoff and dumped 52,000 gallons of fuel over the Pacific 
before returning safely to Los Angeles. 
</P>
<P>
The second-worst crash in U.S. history was an Aug. 16, 1987, crash that killed 
156 people when a Northwest Airlines jet crashed on takeoff at Detroit 
Metropolitan Airport. One child on the plane survived. 
</P>
<P>
J. Michael Kennedy reported from Sioux City and Bob Baker from Los Angeles. 
Also contributing to this story were Larry Green and Tracy Shryer in Chicago, 
Tamara Jones in Denver and Penelope McMillan and Denise Gellene in Los Angeles. 
</P>
<P>
HYDRAULIC LOSS -- The "complete hydraulic failure" reported by the United pilot 
is one of the most feared events in flying. Page 17 
</P>
<P>
RESCUE TEAMS READY -- The Sioux City, Iowa, fire-and-rescue operations had 
practiced for a major emergency. Page 18 
</P>
</TEXT>

<KEYWORDS>
EXPLOSIONS -- IOWA; ENGINES; AIRPLANE ACCIDENTS -- IOWA; DC 10 (AIRPLANE); 
DEFECTIVE PRODUCTS; EQUIPMENT FAILURES; AIRPLANE SAFETY; RESCUES; HEROISM; 
AIRLINE PASSENGERS 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA081489-0025</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA </SOURCE>

<DATE> <DAY>14</DAY> <MONTH>8</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>


<HEADLINE><HL>
LELAND CRASH SITE FOUND; ALL 16 KILLED; 
WRECKAGE OF PLANE WITH CONGRESSMAN SPOTTED IN ETHIOPIA 
</HL></HEADLINE>

<DATELINE>
ADDIS ABABA, Ethiopia 
</DATELINE>

<TEXT>
<P>
U.S. military helicopters on Sunday located the wreckage of a plane that 
crashed last Monday with Texas congressman Mickey Leland and 15 others aboard. 
Witnesses who visited the site said there were no survivors. 
</P>
<P>
U.S. rescue and recovery teams said that the plane hit a mountain about 4,300 
feet above sea level, having missed clearing the peak by about 300 feet. The 
crash site is about 75 miles east of the Fugnido refugee camp that Leland was 
flying to visit when the plane vanished in heavy weather last Monday. 
</P>
<P>
"If they would have flown over that peak they would have been home free," said 
Rep. Gary L. Ackerman (D-N.Y.), a colleague of Leland's who has accompanied 
search crews for the last two days and was aboard the helicopter that first 
spotted the wreckage Sunday. Ackerman said that the plane appeared to have hit 
"nose first, right into the rocks; its two wings sheared off, its engines 
melted, its fuselage gone." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Wreckage Examined 
</P>
<P>
Ackerman said that military paratroopers lowered themselves from his helicopter 
on ropes to examine the wreckage. 
</P>
<P>
"They told us everyone had died instantaneously," Ackerman said. 
</P>
<P>
The 44-year-old Leland, a Democrat, was making his sixth tour of refugee camps 
along the Ethiopia-Sudan border as chairman of the House Select Committee on 
Hunger, a panel he had helped to establish five years ago. 
</P>
<P>
Also aboard the plane were Hugh Anderson Johnson Jr. and Patrice Yvonne 
Johnson, both aides to Leland (who were not related); Joyce Francine Williams, 
an aide to Rep. Ronald V. Dellums (D-Berkeley), and an expert on child 
nutrition; Y. Ivan Tillen, a New York businessman and friend of Leland's; 
Robert Woods, a political and economic officer at the American Embassy in Addis 
Ababa; Gladys Gilbert, a special projects officer for the mission of the U.S. 
Agency for International Development attached to the embassy; Thomas Worrick, 
the acting AID representative in Ethiopia, and Worrick's wife, Roberta. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
7 Ethiopians Killed 
</P>
<P>
Also on board were Debebe Agonofer, an Ethiopian agricultural economist with 
the AID mission, and six other Ethiopians, including the plane's crew of three. 
</P>
<P>
Reaction to the news in the United States was one of sadness coupled with an 
outpouring of praise for Leland's work. A statement issued by President Bush 
said that "Mickey Leland and the other members of his traveling party, both 
Americans and Ethiopians, were engaged in a noble cause -- trying to feed the 
hungry." 
</P>
<P>
Dellums spoke of his staff aide who lost her life in the crash as "a close 
personal friend for over a decade" and said that everyone on the plane "shared 
a common commitment to helping the poor, the starving and the dispossessed in 
that war-torn, drought-stricken land." 
</P>
<P>
"Their deaths are a collective loss to all humanity," Dellums said. 
</P>
<P>
Discovery of the crash site ended what had been one of the most extensive 
American search and rescue operations ever conducted in a Third World country. 
By Sunday, 18 aircraft, including four American helicopters, two American C-130 
airplanes and 12 Ethiopian aircraft, were involved in the search. Three more 
American helicopters were reported to be en route from Eglin Air Force Base in 
Florida when word of the discovery came. 
</P>
<P>
The search on Sunday was hampered again by thunderstorms, poor visibility and 
other conditions that characterized many of the previous days of search. 
</P>
<P>
"The terrain was fairly rugged and the weather conditions were bad getting 
there," said Capt. Clair M. Gilk, commander of one of the two helicopters that 
were the first to spot the wreckage. 
</P>
<P>
Gilk said that the crash site, in a mountainous and heavily wooded region, is 
so remote and inaccessible that the nearest landing site for helicopters is 
half a mile away, a distance that he said could take as much as three hours to 
cover on foot. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Recovery Planned for Today 
</P>
<P>
Air Force personnel were assigned to remain near the site Sunday night to keep 
it secure. Recovery of the remains of those aboard the plane, a twin-engine 
Twin Otter, was to commence at first light today. 
</P>
<P>
Because of the site's inaccessibility, it could take at least two days to 
recover all of the bodies, according to Maj. Gen. James F. Record, who came 
here from Washington to oversee the search effort. Record arrived in Addis 
Ababa about 10 minutes after the first reports were received of the sighting of 
the crash site. 
</P>
<P>
In Washington, a Pentagon spokesman, Navy Capt. Stan Bloyer, said that the 
remains of the Americans will probably be returned to the United States through 
Torrejon Air Base near Madrid, where the American armed forces maintains full 
mortuary facilities. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Dellums to Accompany Bodies 
</P>
<P>
Dellums, House Majority Whip William H. Gray III (D-Pa.) and Republican Reps. 
Bill Emerson of Missouri and Jack Fields of Texas plan to fly to Addis Ababa to 
accompany the bodies back to the United States. 
</P>
<P>
Discovery of the crash site came at about 1:15 p.m. local time Sunday. Ackerman 
said that the helicopter he was traveling in set down during the morning at an 
airstrip near the village of Dembi Dolo. There, the crew came upon a Roman 
Catholic missionary who told them that he had heard reports from local 
villagers that a plane had been heard nearby last week. Presently, the crew 
found an Ethiopian surveyor who said he could guide them to an area near where 
the plane had been heard. The surveyor was taken aboard, crew members said, but 
on their way toward their destination they spotted the crash site. 
</P>
<P>
The location was described as very steep, with the plane resting on land that 
was pitched at an angle of about 60 degrees. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Mostly Rocks and Brush' 
</P>
<P>
Crew members described the site as "mostly rocks and brush" and indicated that 
the pilot of Leland's plane may have been trying to escape bad weather on 
Monday by following the pathway of a river flowing through a valley. Before the 
plane reached safety, it ran into the mountainside. 
</P>
<P>
Rep. Alan Wheat (D-Mo.), who with Ackerman had been flying with search crews 
for the last two days, said he telephoned House Speaker Thomas S. Foley 
(D-Wash.) from Addis Ababa soon after the discovery was made. He said that 
Foley was "heartbroken" at the news. 
</P>
<P>
The crash site was described by U.S. authorities as being about 20 nautical 
miles due east of the town of Gambela and 230 nautical miles west-southwest of 
Addis Ababa. It appeared to be near the village of Bure. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Area Had Been Covered 
</P>
<P>
The area of the site had apparently been searched within the first two days 
after the crash by American aircraft using electronic devices in an attempt to 
detect an emergency signal from the downed craft. However, Sunday was the first 
day that helicopters flew over the area to make visual inspections. 
</P>
<P>
The discovery, and indications that the passengers had died instantly, brought 
an end to charges that the American military response to the emergency was 
inadequate and tardy. Wheat, who was among those who had pressed Defense 
Department officials for the deployment of more aircraft in the search, said 
after the discovery Sunday: "We could have brought every plane in the world 
that we have, and it would not have made a difference." 
</P>
<P>
President Bush, in his Sunday statement, said: "I have known, admired and 
worked with Mickey Leland for many years. His sense of compassion and desire to 
help those in need has aided millions of people from Houston to Addis Ababa. 
Our hearts go out to (his widow) and to the families and friends of the 
congressional staff members, State Department, Agency for International 
Development and Ethiopian officials who joined Mickey on his important mission 
and who died with him trying to carry it out." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Best in Compassion' 
</P>
<P>
Foley said that "in his search to look into the plight of the world's most 
desperate and hungry individuals, Rep. Leland represented the best in 
compassion that we as a nation possess." 
</P>
<P>
Secretary of State James A. Baker III praised the congressman as "an 
outstanding statesman and humanitarian who died serving his country." Baker 
also thanked Ethiopia, a Soviet-allied country with which Washington has had 
strained relations for several years, for its "outstanding support" in the 
search for Leland's party. 
</P>
<P>
Bush offered U.S. help to the Ethiopian government for its investigation into 
the crash of the plane. 
</P>
<P>
Leland was a former Houston pharmacist who called the fight against hunger "my 
passion." He leaves a wife, Alison Walton Leland, and a 3-year-old son, 
Jarrett. Mrs. Leland is pregnant with the couple's second child. 
</P>
<P>
First elected to Congress in 1978, he represented a mostly black and Hispanic 
section of Houston after the retirement of Rep. Barbara Jordan, a fellow 
Democrat. 
</P>
<P>
Leland had no significant opposition for his congressional seat since he was 
first elected, winning his most recent election with 96% of the vote. 
</P>
<P>
Times staff writer Melissa Healy, in Washington, contributed to this story. 
</P>
</TEXT>

<KEYWORDS>
LELAND, MICKEY; AIRPLANE ACCIDENTS -- ETHIOPIA; MISSING PERSONS; SEARCH AND 
RESCUE; REFUGEES -- SUDAN; UNITED STATES -- ARMED FORCES -- ETHIOPIA 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA081589-0043</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA </SOURCE>

<DATE> <DAY>15</DAY> <MONTH>8</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>


<HEADLINE><HL>
MISSISSIPPI REP. SMITH DIES IN AIR CRASH 
</HL></HEADLINE>

<DATELINE>
ATLANTA 
</DATELINE>

<TEXT>
<P>
Freshman congressman Larkin Smith (R-Miss.) died in a light plane crash in 
Mississippi, authorities said Monday, making him the second member of the House 
killed in an aviation accident in a week. 
</P>
<P>
The single-engine Cessna 177 crashed Sunday night in thick woods near the tiny 
community of Janice. Smith and the pilot, Charles Vierling, who also was 
killed, were flying from Hattiesburg to Gulfport, according to federal and 
local officials. 
</P>
<P>
Searchers combed the heavily wooded DeSoto National Forest through the night 
but were unable to find the wreckage until Monday morning, when they spotted it 
from the air. "There was a 300-foot-long path cut by the plane," Harrison 
County Sheriff's Department Capt. Rick Gaston said in a telephone interview. 
</P>
<P>
Smith, 45, died the same day the wreckage of a plane carrying Rep. Mickey 
Leland (D-Tex.) and 15 others was found on an Ethiopian mountainside. Leland's 
plane had been missing almost a week after he took off on a fact-finding 
mission to combat hunger. 
</P>
<P>
News of Smith's death was followed by an outpouring of sympathy from 
Mississippi to Washington, even as Smith's colleagues were still mourning 
Leland's death. 
</P>
<P>
At the White House, spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said President and Mrs. Bush 
"deeply regret" Smith's death, adding that Smith, who was elected to a seat 
vacated by Sen. Trent Lott (R-Miss.), "was just beginning a promising career in 
the Congress." 
</P>
<P>
Smith, a former sheriff and police chief, was already developing a reputation 
on the House Judiciary Committee as a zealous opponent of illegal drugs. 
</P>
<P>
"We (the congressional delegation) had come to depend on him in the fight 
against drugs," said Rep. G. V. (Sonny) Montgomery (D-Miss.) "This is a 
tremendous loss to his family, his state, and the nation." 
</P>
<P>
Smith had thrown out the first ball at the Dixie Youth World Series baseball 
tournament Sunday and was heading home to Gulfport, taking off at about 9:10 
p.m. for the 35-minute flight. 
</P>
<P>
Jack Barker, a Federal Aviation Administration spokesman here, said the plane 
"lost radar contact" at 9:25. He said area residents "heard the airplane crash" 
and notified officials. Barker said visibility was 4 to 6 miles, and "rain was 
reported, but not heavy." 
</P>
<P>
Lamar Breland told the Associated Press that "my wife was preparing to go to 
bed, and we heard a plane coming over. I thought at the time it was unusual for 
a plane to be in the area at night." He said he heard a "revving sound and then 
a crash." 
</P>
<P>
In Miami, Jorge Prellezo, regional director of the National Transportation 
Safety Board, said a team of investigators had been dispatched to the scene. 
Investigators generally take months to establish a probable cause of such 
incidents. 
</P>
<P>
The plane belonged to the Institute for Marine Mammal Studies Inc. in Gulfport. 
The institute immediately issued a statement saying that Smith had requested 
use of the plane "to accommodate his busy schedule." Jody Canady, a 
spokeswoman, said Smith was to reimburse the institute. 
</P>
<P>
The statement said the plane, manufactured in 1973, and purchased by the 
institute last year, had a "current inspection." The pilot received his license 
in 1964 and had a physical examination on June 28, the statement said. 
</P>
<P>
Smith was elected last November to represent Mississippi's 5th congressional 
district. He was Harrison County Sheriff from 1984 to 1989, and was Gulfport 
police chief from 1977 to 1983. As sheriff, Smith coordinated anti-drug efforts 
of federal, local and state agencies across five states. 
</P>
<P>
Smith, survived by a wife and one child, was lauded by Mississippi Gov. Ray 
Mabus, who called his death "a tragic loss" for the state and ordered flags on 
state property flown at half staff. 
</P>
<P>
Friends and former associates in Gulfport were stunned and saddened. Gaston, 
who worked for Smith nine years both in the sheriff's department and earlier 
when Smith was Gulfport police chief, called Smith "a pillar of strength. He 
was progressive, and above all, honest. You just never thought something like 
this would happen." 
</P>
<P>
Researcher Edith M. Stanley in Atlanta and staff writer Lori Silver in 
Washington contributed to this story. 
</P>
</TEXT>

<KEYWORDS>
SMITH, LARKIN; MISSISSIPPI -- GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS; AIRPLANE ACCIDENTS -- 
MISSISSIPPI; UNITED STATES -- GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS; LELAND, MICKEY 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>LA092189-0123</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> LA </SOURCE>

<DATE> <DAY>21</DAY> <MONTH>9</MONTH> <YEAR>89</YEAR> </DATE>


<HEADLINE><HL>
BOMB SUSPECTED IN CRASH OF FRENCH PLANE IN AFRICA 
</HL></HEADLINE>

<DATELINE>
PARIS 
</DATELINE>

<TEXT>
<P>
A French DC-10 jetliner with 171 people aboard experienced a powerful 
high-altitude explosion, possibly from a terrorist bomb, before crashing in a 
remote desert region of Niger in northern Africa, officials in France said 
Wednesday. 
</P>
<P>
In Washington, intelligence specialists said they believe that the jetliner may 
have been bombed by people seeking to retaliate against France for its recent 
actions in Lebanon. 
</P>
<P>
For several months, France has played an active part in the Lebanon crisis, 
attempting to broker a settlement between Christian and pro-Syrian forces. 
</P>
<P>
Late last month, the French government sent a naval task force of five warships 
into Lebanese waters as part of what President Francois Mitterrand called a 
"rescue mission" for several thousand French nationals living in the war-torn 
country. But the action was widely perceived as an attempt to provide 
protection and support for Maj. Gen. Michel Aoun and his Maronite Christian 
forces against Syrian troops and Muslim militias in Lebanon. 
</P>
<P>
Ever since, one intelligence official said Wednesday, the French government has 
realized that its planes were being targeted for some sort of terrorist attack. 
</P>
<P>
The DC-10 operated by the French airline UTA crashed Tuesday after taking off 
from N'Djamena, Chad, on a flight that originated in Brazzaville, Congo. French 
military helicopter crews who visited the crash site in the desolate reaches of 
the Sahara Desert late Wednesday afternoon found no survivors. Included among 
the presumed dead was the wife of the American ambassador to Chad. 
</P>
<P>
On Wednesday, Michel Friess, a spokesman for UTA, said that "the wide surface 
over which the debris of the airplane has been found suggests a high-altitude 
explosion that leads one to think of a criminal attack." 
</P>
<P>
Anonymous callers to the airline office in Paris and to a Western news agency 
in London claimed responsibility for the crash on behalf of the Shiite Muslim 
terrorist organization Islamic Jihad. 
</P>
<P>
The London caller linked the attack to the seizure of a Shiite cleric, Sheik 
Abdel Karim Obeid, by Israeli forces in southern Lebanon on July 28. 
</P>
<P>
Saying he was reading a statement from Islamic Jihad, the London caller 
declared: "We are proud of this action, which was very successful. We would 
like to say the French are warned not to exchange information regarding Sheik 
Obeid with the Israelis no more. We demand the freedom of Sheik Obeid, and 
otherwise we will refresh the memories of the bombings in Paris of '85 and '86. 
Long live the Islamic Republic of Iran." 
</P>
<P>
However, the message made little sense in the context of France's limited role 
in the Obeid matter. 
</P>
<P>
A more likely possibility, speculated terrorist experts and one intelligence 
source in Washington, was a terrorist attack on behalf of pro-Syrian Muslim 
forces in Lebanon. 
</P>
<P>
The French Foreign Ministry declined to comment Wednesday about the possibility 
of a terrorist attack. "The pieces are widely scattered, so it didn't crash on 
impact," a Foreign Ministry spokesman said. 
</P>
<P>
Air controllers lost contact with UTA Flight 772 less than an hour after it 
took off from N'Djamena. The sudden loss of contact was another explanation 
given by the French airline authorities supporting the theory of a terrorist 
explosion. 
</P>
<P>
"If there had been a very serious problem on board, other than an explosion or 
the sudden disintegration of the airplane," said UTA spokesman Friess, "there 
would have been at least several seconds or minutes for the crew to 
re-establish contact." 
</P>
<P>
UTA officials insisted that the DC-10 was in good working condition, having 
completed 60,000 hours of flying time on 14,700 flights in 16 years of service. 
Since it was formed in 1949, UTA, which specializes in African and Pacific 
routes, had never experienced a crash during a commercial flight. 
</P>
<P>
However, in 1984 a UTA DC-8 aircraft flying the same route was damaged by a 
bomb explosion before takeoff at the N'Djamena airport. Twenty-five people on 
board were injured in that attack, which the Chadian government blamed on 
Libya. Chad-Libyan relations have recently normalized after a 10-year guerrilla 
war. 
</P>
<P>
At the White House, Press Secretary Marlin Fitzwater said the U.S. government's 
information on Tuesday's disaster was limited. 
</P>
<P>
"We can't at this time state for a fact that (the plane) was blown up, but it 
does have those appearances," he said. 
</P>
<P>
In Santa Monica, a RAND Corp. analyst, Bruce Hoffman, said Wednesday he 
believed the attack was probably staged by Shiite Muslim groups concerned that 
France might intervene in Lebanon on behalf of the Maronite Christians led by 
Aoun. 
</P>
<P>
"It seems to me that there's a much stronger Middle Eastern context than an 
African context," Hoffman said. "It could be that the Maronites' opponents in 
general were determined to deliver some sort of a knockout blow in Lebanon, and 
(it) was designed as a warning to make the French think twice. 
</P>
<P>
"This would send a pretty clear message to France that they ought to back 
away," Hoffman added. He noted that by the end of August, "all the main Shiite 
players in Lebanon had threatened some sort of retribution against France." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Threats by Militants 
</P>
<P>
On Aug. 20, the Revolutionary Justice Organization threatened to "strike deep 
into the heart of French territory." Three days later, Hezbollah threatened to 
stage suicide attacks against French targets. On Aug. 25, a previously unknown 
group, the Organization in Defense of the Oppressed, threatened to strike "at 
French interests everywhere." 
</P>
<P>
An Air France flight on Aug. 28 was delayed for more than five hours before 
taking off from Dulles International Airport in Washington when security 
officials received a last-minute bomb threat. According to one well-informed 
intelligence official, both French and American officials took that threat 
seriously and searched all the luggage on the plane before allowing it to 
depart. 
</P>
<P>
While France's willingness to bargain with terrorists for the freedom of 
hostages had in the past created a modus vivendi that appeared to spare the 
country from violent attacks, Hoffman and other analysts suggested that the 
stakes in Lebanon had become too important for those old rules to apply. 
</P>
<P>
"In these people's eyes, we're really talking about Lebanon's future. That 
wrenches the entire struggle in Lebanon onto a higher plateau," Hoffman said. 
"The last battle for Beirut has yet to be fought." 
</P>
<P>
"If it's not the beginning of the end of things there, it's certainly the 
opening of a new wave of conflicts there," agreed another analyst, Jim 
Blackwell of Georgetown University's Center for Strategic and International 
Studies. 
</P>
<P>
Another analyst at the center, Robert Kupperman, discounted the possibility 
that a small terrorist group alone could have been responsible for the airborne 
bombing. 
</P>
<P>
"When someone puts a bomb on the plane, it normally takes the resources of a 
state, at least to set it up," Kupperman said. 
</P>
<P>
Apart from Syrian-backed Lebanese forces, Kupperman suggested that Libya and 
Iran also could have been motivated to stage such an attack. 
</P>
<P>
According to intelligence specialists, security at the airport in Chad at which 
the plane stopped is under the control of French officials. However, the French 
do not control airport security in Brazzaville, the city from which the plane 
took off. 
</P>
<P>
The waiting room at Paris' Charles De Gaulle Airport, where the flight was 
scheduled to land, was tense and somber after the plane was first reported 
missing Tuesday night. 
</P>
<P>
Included among the passengers was Bonnie Pugh, wife of the U.S. ambassador to 
Chad, Robert L. Pugh. The State Department said six other Americans were 
aboard. 
</P>
<P>
Mrs. Pugh was on her way to the United States for her daughter's wedding, 
according to her sister, Sally Johnson, of Brawley, Calif. The ambassador's 
wife, who was born in Los Angeles in the 1920s and later moved to the Imperial 
Valley, had decided to travel ahead of her husband to help plan the October 
wedding of their 26-year-old daughter Anne in suburban Washington, D.C. 
</P>
<P>
Another passenger aboard the plane was Chadian Planning Minister Mahamat 
Soumaila, en route to Washington to attend a meeting of the International 
Monetary Fund. 
</P>
<P>
Most of the passengers were African. French officials said the victims included 
31 Frenchpassengers. 
</P>
<P>
Tempest reported from Paris and Mann from Washington. Times staff writer 
Douglas Jehl, in Washington, contributed to this story. 
</P>
</TEXT>

<KEYWORDS>
EXPLOSIONS -- NIGER; AIRPLANE ACCIDENTS -- NIGER; BOMBINGS -- NIGER; FRANCE -- 
FOREIGN RELATIONS -- LEBANON; LEBANON -- REVOLTS; TERRORISM -- NIGER; DC 10 
(AIRPLANE); UTA (AIRLINE); THREATS; ISLAMIC JIHAD; OBEID, ABDEL KAREEM (SHEIK) 
</KEYWORDS>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>WSJ870818-0002</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> WSJ </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>18</DAY> <MONTH>08</MONTH> <YEAR>87</YEAR> </DATE>
<HEADLINE><HL> Northwest Jet That Crashed in Detroit
Had Engine Problems in Prior Years
</HL><HL>
A Wall Street Journal News Roundup</HL></HEADLINE>
<DATE> <DAY>18</DAY> <MONTH>08</MONTH> <YEAR>87</YEAR> </DATE>


<TEXT>
   The Northwest Airlines jet that crashed Sunday in Detroit, killing at least 154 people, was involved in two incidents of engine failure in the past two years. 
   According to Federal Aviation Administration records, the McDonnell Douglas Corp. MD-82 jet made emergency landings in 1985 and 1986 following the loss of power in one of its two engines. 
A Northwest spokesman confirmed that the incidents happened, but said they weren't related to Sunday's crash of Flight 255. 
   Though federal investigators were looking into a number of possible causes for the crash, which occurred shortly after takeoff, engine failure appeared to be a likely culprit. 
According to Associated Press reports, some witnesses to the crash, including an air traffic controller, said they saw blue flame coming from one of the jetliner's engines just before it hit the ground and exploded into a fireball. 
   The accident, the second-deadliest ever in the U.S., could have a broad range of effects on the airline industry regardless of the specific causes, aviation specialists said. 
Following a summer of near-misses, delays and other snafus, some airline specialists said the accident could serve as a catalyst for a reassessment of the nation's air-travel system. 
   Unlike the recent near-misses, the Detroit accident doesn't appear related to air-traffic control problems. 
Even so, some congressional aides believe there will be a "spillover" effect, and that all aviation safety issues will now get closer scrutiny. 
Moreover, although service problems have been the focus of much of the attention in recent months, the debate may now center more strongly on safety issues. 
   "There is going to be a lot of noise from Capitol Hill," said John Galipault, president of the Aviation Safety Institute. 
"This one is going under the microscope." 
Added a Senate Commerce Committee staff member: "Delays and other consumer concerns will end up in the back seat." 
   In Detroit, federal crash inspectors and representatives of United Technologies Corp.'s Pratt &amp; Whitney unit, the engine maker, arrived at the accident scene. 
Officials said that the aircraft's flight recorders, which record cockpit conversations, had been found in wreckage that extended over half a mile. 
   The MD-82 jet, which has a good safety record, is designed to be able to take off and land even if one engine fails. 
Safety officials wouldn't speculate on whether the plane's heavy load may have contributed to the crash. 
   In addition to a large fuel load for the flight to Phoenix, Ariz., the flight was jammed with passengers. 
There were 153 people on a plane with 143 passenger seats. 
The extras included six crew members, two babies who were being held by passengers and two Northwest employees riding on two of the plane's jump seats. 
Wire-service reports said two persons on the ground also were killed, and that a 4-year-old girl was hospitalized in critical condition. 
Late last night, the Associated Press reported that the girl was identified by her grandfather. 
Her father, mother and brother were passengers on the Northwest airliner and died in the crash. 
   The JT8D-219 engines used on the jet have been the subject of some concern among federal safety officals. 
In April, the National Transportation Safety Board urged the FAA to conduct a safety investigation of the 200 series of JT8D engines after some dangerous in-flight engine failures. 
   The board made the recommendation after a March 23 incident in which an American Airlines MD-82 plane approaching the Minneapolis airport experienced an engine surge and loss of power. 
The engine, a JT8D-217A, was shut down, and the plane landed without further trouble. 
A later inspection showed that all 44 of the pins used to lock jet-engine turbine-vane clusters to the outer part of the turbine case had fractured. 
   The board recommended that the FAA order inspections of the JT8D engines to detect any pin fractures and to replace existing ones with improved pins. 
The board said similar incidents involved Pacific Southwest Airlines and Muse Airlines. 
   The FAA, in a May 29 response, told the board it essentially agreed with its recommendations and would take steps to require inspections of the engine and replacement of parts where necessary. 
The new rules, proposed last month, will go into effect this fall, FAA officials said. 
   In its April report, the National Transportation Safety Board warned that "many" of the 330 MD-80 series airplanes operated by 12 U.S. and 14 foreign airlines world-wide "are potential candidates" for engine failure. 
More than 900 of the engines have been manufactured, according to the board. 
However, engineering changes have been made in some engines. 
In others, airlines have made changes, based on a Pratt &amp; Whitney service bulletin, to reduce the risk of pin failure. 
   Thomas Haueter, of the safety recommendations staff of the safety agency, said that the board hadn't put out an emergency recommendation for immediate replacement of the pins because it was unclear if the problems that had occurred were merely isolated incidents or reflected system problems. 
   FAA officials at the crash scene wouldn't speculate on the reasons for the crash or comment on the plane's engines. 
John Lauber, one of five members of the National Transportation Safety Board, said at a news conference at a hotel near the airport last night that there was no evidence at this point that either engine exploded or caught fire during flight. 
He stressed that it was too early to draw any firm conclusions. 
A board spokesman said it will take nine to 12 months to determine the probable cause of the accident. 
   Despite an excellent safety record, Northwest could be hurt in a number of ways by the crash. 
Among other things, the accident has focused attention on its recent service problems as well as discord among its workers. 
The airline early yesterday denied that its labor troubles may have played a role in the crash. 
   Such concerns arose following reports of a work slowdown by Northwest mechanics. 
In January, the Federal Bureau of Investigation began investigating incidents of alleged tampering with Northwest planes in Minneapolis. 
   Northwest, a unit of Minneapolis-based NWA Inc., also has had a rash of service problems since its acquisition of Republic Airlines last year. 
There were reports yesterday that relatives of crash victims being flown in from Phoenix were asked to switch from one Northwest jet to another because of mechanical problems. 
   The MD-82 that crashed was a former Republic jet that Northwest acquired as part of the merger. 
The two emergency landings that involved the jetliner, number N312RC, took place in Minneapolis and San Francisco. 
In the Minneapolis incident, the plane landed missing part of its tail cone. 
A Northwest spokesman said the engines involved in those two incidents had since been replaced by other JT8D-200 series engines. 
   The FAA said in Washington that air-traffic controllers in Detroit gave the Northwest flight takeoff clearance for Runway 3C, the center of the airport's three runways. 
The controllers reported that shortly after the jetliner lifted off, it pitched from left to right, according to FAA spokesman John Leyden. 
   Then they "saw a blue flash from the left engine," Mr. Leyden said. 
"The left wing hit the ground, and the aircraft burst into flames," according to the controllers' account. 
   FAA records show that besides those incidents that involved the plane that crashed, problems with the turbine sections of JT8D-200 series engines occurred on three Republic flights in the past four years. 
None of those problems resulted in a serious accident. 
   In one such incident, in September 1983, falling debris from an engine caused fire damage to several homes around John Wayne International Airport in Orange County, Calif. 
In another incident, at the Detroit airport in October 1985, an engine on an MD-82 "popped and began to unspool" on takeoff. 
Later inspection revealed extensive turbine damage to the engine, the FAA report said. 
   An FAA official said all jetliners, in order to be certified, must be capable of completing their takeoff ascent even if one engine fails, provided the aircraft is within prescribed weight limits. 
Why the Northwest airliner failed to make the climb and whether it was carrying too much weight will be subjects for federal investigators, he said. 
   Congress is expected to act on a half-dozen major aviation bills this fall. 
Staff members now expect those bills to attract new measures aimed at improving safety. 
"Aviation is going to be a hot topic," said an aide to Sen. Robert Byrd (D., W.Va.). 
"When people get back (from their August recess), they will be looking for an opportunity to do something." 
   For example, Sen. Byrd and Sen. Ernest Hollings (D., S.C.), chairman of the Senate Commerce Committee, have already drawn up legislation that would require small planes to be equipped with altitude-reporting devices at hundreds of airports across the U.S. 
   Sen. Frank Lautenberg (D., N.J.), chairman of the Senate Appropriations Subcommittee on Transportation, predicted that the accident will "accelerate movement by the Congress and the Transportation Department to do whatever can be done -- either by hiring more maintenance inspectors or reducing air traffic to meet the capacity of the system, to reduce the chances of future accidents." 
   He added, "We will want to hear a thorough examination of everything that took place with that airplane and what was going on at the airport." 
   Sunday's crash was the first time in 24 years that passengers were killed in an accident involving a Northwest plane. 
In June 1963, a DC-7 operating as a military charter crashed into the Pacific Ocean, killing all 101 people onboard. 
In March, a commuter plane affiliated with Northwest crashed in Detroit, killing nine people. 
The worst airline accident ever in the U.S. was the 1979 crash of an American Airlines jet in Chicago. 
   ---
              Previous Airline Accidents In U.S.
                   Involving U.S. Carriers
 AIRLINE           LOCATION               YEAR      DEATHS
 American          Chicago                1979       273
 Pan Am            Kenner, La.            1982       153
 PSA               San Diego              1982       144
 Delta             Dallas                 1985       135
 TWA, United       New York               1960       134
 Eastern           New York               1975       112
 Alaska            Juneau                 1971       111
 Eastern           Miami                  1972        99
 American          New York               1962        95
 TWA               Berryville, Va.        1974        92
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO>WSJ910304-0005</DOCNO>
<SOURCE> WSJ </SOURCE>
<DATE> <DAY>04</DAY> <MONTH>03</MONTH> <YEAR>91</YEAR> </DATE>

<HEADLINE><HL>
   Crash of United
   Jetliner Kills
   25 in Colorado
   </HL></HEADLINE>
<DATE> <DAY>04</DAY> <MONTH>03</MONTH> <YEAR>91</YEAR> </DATE>





<TEXT>
   A United Airlines Boeing 737-200 jetliner carrying 25
passengers and crew members crashed into a dry lake area near
Colorado Springs, Colo., municipal airport, apparently
killing all aboard.
   As National Transportation Safety Board investigators
hurried to the scene, there weren't any early indications on
why the jet might have crashed. One focus of the inquiry,
however, is expected to center on whether there were unstable
or gusty winds at the time of the crash. The plane hit the
ground several miles south of the airport at about 11:40 a.m.
EST yesterday, UAL Corp.'s United Airlines said. The plane
was traveling from Denver.

   
   Local news reporters quoted witnesses as saying that the
plane appeared to nosedive into the earth.
   The crash comes at a particularly sensitive time for the
travel industry. Although it has always been difficult to
measure the effect of crashes on travel, this accident comes
just as people were starting to get over fears of terrorism
related to the Persian Gulf war.
   Airlines have been slashing their flight schedules and
laying off employees because of the downturn. Some travel
agencies have gone to four-day workweeks. Most of the travel
sector has resorted to sharp discounting to spark travel.
   This, in fact, may have been one reason why the load on
the United flight was light. The jet, which can hold at least
100 passengers, carried 20 passengers and a crew of two
pilots and three flight attendants.
   Yesterday's marks the third crash of a United jet in the
past three years. In July 1988, a United DC-10 crashed in
Sioux City, Iowa, after an engine broke apart in flight,
killing 112 people. In February 1989, the cargo door on
United Boeing 747 burst open near Hawaii, tearing a gaping
hole in the fuselage. Nine passengers died.
   About two hours before yesterday's crash, the National
Weather Service in Colorado Springs issued its first high
wind warning for the area since January, according to James
Hall, a meteorological technician observer in Colorado
Springs.
   Moments after the crash, the average wind speed was 23
miles per hour, gusting to 32 mph, Mr. Hall said. "When it's
gusty like that, the conditions are quite choppy. It would be
like a turbulent river current. It's essentially like water
hitting rocks and splashing and foaming over."
   A Federal Aviation Administration official said, "There
were some reports of gusting winds but whether or not that
had any impact or whether there was any kind of mechanical
problem, I can't speculate."
   Another FAA official said that although it is too early to
pinpoint the cause, "wind shear would be a major area of
investigation." If preliminary reports that there was wind
shear in the area are true, then "that would indicate there
was some instability in the atmosphere," he added.
   Wind shear is a sudden, violent shift in wind direction.
It can smash an airplane into the ground.
   However, he said that wind shear is most dangerous when an
aircraft is flying at a very low altitude, either shortly
before landing or right after takeoff. In Sunday's crash, the
jetliner was a few miles from the airport and so should have
been at a somewhat higher altitude.
   The last major U.S. wind shear accident occurred in Dallas
in 1985, when a Delta Air Lines jet crashed on approach.
Since then, the FAA and the industry have revamped pilot
training on wind shear and have devoted considerable
resources to dealing with the hazard.
   No buildings or structures on the ground were damaged by
the crash, according to the El Paso County Sheriffs
Department. An eight-year-old girl who was playing nearby,
was treated for a head injury and released.
   The jet involved in the crash is almost nine years old. It
was delivered in May 1982 to now-defunct Frontier Airlines.
United acquired the plane in June 1986. The plane was
operated by an engine manufactured by United Technologies
Corp.'s Pratt &amp; Whitney division.
   ---
   Brett Pulley in Chicago contributed to this article.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</CORPUS>
